<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Five seasonable sermons. As they were preached before eminent auditories, upon several arguments. / By Paul Knell Master in Arts, of Clare-Hall in Cambridge. Sometimes chaplain to a regiment of curiasiers in His late Majesties Army.</title>
            <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1766_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868523</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868523</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 220:E1766[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Five seasonable sermons. As they were preached before eminent auditories, upon several arguments. / By Paul Knell Master in Arts, of Clare-Hall in Cambridge. Sometimes chaplain to a regiment of curiasiers in His late Majesties Army.</title>
                  <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664.</author>
                  <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664. Israel and England paralelled.</author>
                  <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664. Looking-glasse for Levellers.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 188 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The convoy of a Christian", "The assumption of the Messiah", "Israel and England paralelled", "A looking-glasse for Levellers", and "A severe sentence against secure citizens" have separate dated title pages; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "January.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170350:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FIVE SEASONABLE Sermons. As they were preached before Eminent AUDITORIES, Upon ſeveral ARGUMENTS.</p>
            <p>BY PAUL KNELL <hi>Maſter</hi> in <hi>Arts,</hi> OF <hi>Clare-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes <hi>Chaplain</hi> to a <hi>Regiment</hi> of <hi>CURIASIERS</hi> in <hi>His</hi> late <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170350:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170350:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>SACRED MAJESTY,</hi> OF THE <hi>Moſt High and Mighty</hi> MONARCH, CHARLES <hi>the</hi> Second, BY THE Eſpecial <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God King</hi> of Great <hi>Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland, Defender</hi> of the <hi>Faith,</hi> &amp;c,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere not <hi>your Regal</hi> Clemency and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour very eminent, the Tenuity of that which here I offer to <hi>your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170350:3"/>might indict me for famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity. But as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were not to appear before the <hi>Lord</hi> their <hi>God,</hi> ſo neither durſt I before my <hi>Lord</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> empty-handed. <hi>Silver and gold</hi> indeed <hi>I have none,</hi> ſcarce ſo much as that which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>is like Apples of Gold in pictures of ſilver;</hi> but ſuch as I have, I moſt humbly offer to <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> knowing, that as <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> did not diſdain <hi>two</hi> handfuls of <hi>ordinary water</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to him by <hi>Synaetas;</hi> ſo <hi>your Royal</hi> hand will graciouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>one</hi> handfull of <hi>Sanctuary-water</hi> from him, who as in duty bound, hath both actively and
<pb facs="tcp:170350:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſſively approved himſelfe a faithfull <hi>Subject</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> and a dutifull <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that hath no better <hi>Preſent. One</hi> of theſe ſlender <hi>Sermons</hi> hath already been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with <hi>your Royal ear</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> they all now humbly crave a glance from <hi>your graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eye</hi> at <hi>White-hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Inſcription</hi> indeed and <hi>ſubſcription</hi> of this <hi>Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> are ſo vaſtly diſtant, that ſome large <hi>Apology</hi> ought to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene. But <hi>your Majeſties</hi> many important affairs diſpenſe with no further avocation. I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly add therefore only a ſhort <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah</hi> and <hi>Hoſanna, Bleſsing</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170350:4"/>the <hi>Lord</hi> by whom <hi>Kings</hi> reign for ſo <hi>ſignally viſiting your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty,</hi> and ſo ſeaſonably <hi>redeeming your diſtreſſed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Beſeeching</hi> alſo the <hi>ſame Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords</hi> to <hi>ſave</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend your Royal Perſon,</hi> as with a <hi>ſhield,</hi> to make your <hi>Throne</hi> here as the <hi>dayes</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and hereafter to <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late You</hi> to an <hi>Heavenly Throne,</hi> which is the due and daily <hi>ſacrifice</hi> offered up with a true <hi>heart</hi> fervently by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Sacred Majeſties Moſt Humble</hi> AND <hi>Moſt Loyal SUBJECT</hi> PAUL KNELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE CONVOY OF A Chriſtian. A Sermon PREACHED Before His MAJESTY, <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> OF Ever bleſſed Memory, at <hi>Matſon</hi> near <hi>Glocester,</hi> in time of the <hi>Siege</hi> there on <hi>Tueſday, Auguſt</hi> 22. 1643.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170350:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>THE CONVOY OF A Chriſtian.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ISAI. 43.2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, I will be with thee, and thorow the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou walkest thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Uem miſerum video, hominem ſcio,</hi> Trouble is the very badge and cognizance of humanity; we are born to it, holy <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, as the ſparks flie upward, to this end were we born, and for this cauſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170350:6"/>came we into the world. Or if this be not <hi>Finis intentionis,</hi> yet it is <hi>Finis executionis,</hi> I am ſure; if we came not hither on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be troubled, yet without great trouble we cannot get from hence, from the <hi>Cradle</hi> to the <hi>Coffin,</hi> being like <hi>Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>'s roul, full of Lamentation, and Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Woe. There are ſome indeed (I mean the traiterous <hi>Reformers</hi> of our Age) that live wholly at eaſe in their uſurped poſſeſſions, they come in no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune like other folk, neither are they plagued like other men. But theſe look like the Devils Darlings, or rather like the worlds Baſtards; though we may be <hi>men</hi> therefore without Trouble, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it we cannot be loyal Subjects, we cannot be good <hi>Christians;</hi> in the world ye ſhall have tribulation, were the words of our departing <hi>Saviour</hi> to his <hi>Church.</hi> But he told them juſt before, that in him they ſhould have Peace, and he telleth them in effect the ſelf ſame in our <hi>Text,</hi> That he will deliver them in ſix troubles, yea, that in ſeven there ſhall no evil touch them, that in Famine he will redeem them from death, and in War from the power of the ſword; let their troubles be external, corporal corrections; let their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170350:6"/>Troubles be internal, ſpiritual deſertions, yet their <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and their <hi>Joſhua</hi> will deliver them out of all, <hi>When thou,</hi> &amp;c. In which words we may obſerve four parts, The <hi>Paſſenger,</hi> the <hi>Paſſage,</hi> the <hi>Concomitant,</hi> and the <hi>Conſequent.</hi> The <hi>Paſſenger</hi> is the <hi>Church, Cum tranſieris, when thou paſſest.</hi> The <hi>Paſſage</hi> is two-fold, <hi>Per aquas, &amp; per ignes,</hi> thorow waters, and thorow fire, <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, when thou walkeſt thorow the fire.</hi> The <hi>Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant</hi> or Convoy is Almighty God, <hi>Tibi adſum,</hi> I am, or will be with thee. The <hi>Conſequent</hi> is the Churches ſafety, <hi>Flamina non operient, flamma non incendet, the rivers ſhall not over-flow thee, the flame ſhall not kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle on thee.</hi> And of theſe parts in order. I begin with the <hi>Paſſenger,</hi> which is the <hi>Church, cum tranſieris, when thou paſſeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Had we retained our firſt integrity, we might eaſily have ſtept to heaven, with as great facility, as from one room to another, from the <hi>Parlour</hi> of an earthly, to the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence-Chamber</hi> of an heavenly <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> But ſin hath placed a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a great gulf between us and heaven; we that were ſometime; near, are now afar off; whoſoever will hereafter enter into <hi>Canaan,</hi> he muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo a tedious paſſage thorow the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170350:7"/>
                  <p>There are four Titles that pertain to the very beſt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſons, <hi>Advenae, Inquilini, Hoſpites, Peregrini,</hi> we are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, we are Sojourners, we are Gueſts, we are Pilgrims. But of all four, the laſt, methinks, fitteth our condition beſt: <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrini,</hi> we are Pilgrims; <hi>Viatores,</hi> we are Travellers; <hi>Tranſeuntes,</hi> we are Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers; here we have no continuing City, but we ſeek for one to come. Look upon the Patriarch <hi>Abraham,</hi> the great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ye ſhall find him, like St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in journeying often, from <hi>Caldea</hi> to <hi>Charran,</hi> from <hi>Charran</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> where he ſojourned; the Apoſtle telleth us, as in a ſtrange Countrey, dwelling in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> he had there none inheritance, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> no not ſo much as to ſet his foot on: to teach him, and us all, that we muſt not ſet up our ſtaff here, <hi>Plus ultra,</hi> we muſt go farther, we being but Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims on the Earth. This we know like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to have been the condition of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> who wandered in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a ſolitary way, and found no City to dwell in. Their own houſes were <hi>Tents,</hi> Gods houſe was but a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> all por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, to be carryed up and down from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170350:7"/>one place to another; They had neither <hi>Tenement</hi> nor <hi>Temple,</hi> till they were ſetled in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> nor have we any certain dwelling place, till we come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where the <hi>Lamb</hi> is the <hi>Temple.</hi> For while we are at home in the body, we are not properly at home, we are but <hi>in via,</hi> in the way that leadeth us to it: we are born from <hi>above:</hi> and therefore there is our <hi>Native countrey;</hi> all the while we are on earth, we are, as it were, going a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage to heaven. And the application of this now may be two-fold.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Seeing we are but Paſſengers here and Pilgrims, this may ſerve to ſet ſpurs to us, and haſten us towards our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. For no Paſſenger would willingly tarry long upon the way, but maketh all the haſte he can to get him home. So let us think it our greateſt puniſhment (next to this rebellious reformation) that we are conſtrained to dwell with <hi>Meſech,</hi> to have our habitation among the Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> and therefore let us wiſh with holy <hi>David,</hi> to have the wings of a Dove, that ſo we might flie home to Heaven, and be at reſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Though here we are but Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, yet ſeeing heaven is our home,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170350:8"/>this may comfort us amidſt all our plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings and perſecutions; all our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and diſtreſſes. For let a paſſenger meet with never ſo bad entertainment by the way, yet he will not greatly murmure at it; I have better at home, he will ſay, and it will not be long, I hope, e're I get thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So, as long, Brethren, as there are Quarters taken up for us in Heaven, if we have any Chriſtian Courage, let us not faint by the way, be our uſage never ſo courſe, be our paſſage never ſo perilous, which leadeth me from the firſt part of the Text, the <hi>Paſsenger,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> to the ſecond, which is her <hi>Paſſage,</hi> and this I find to be two-fold, <hi>per aquas, &amp; per ignes,</hi> thorow waters, and thorow fire, <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, when thou walkest thorow the fire.</hi> Her firſt paſſage is <hi>per aquas, when thou paſſeſt thorow the waters.</hi> Which <hi>waters</hi> have ſundry acceptions in holy Scripture; the literal is firſt in nature, and muſt be ſo in order. And <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> will have an <hi>Alleotheta</hi> here, one tenſe put for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Tranſieris</hi> for <hi>Tranſibas,</hi> when thou paſſeſt, or ſhalt paſs, inſtead of when thou paſſedſt, or didſt paſs, alluding to the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Noah</hi> in the Deluge, or rather to that of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thorow the red-ſea. But
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170350:8"/>whether theſe or no be the meaning, theſe examples ſuit well with the Text; and of the ſame nature we have ſome other in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ, the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> of the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> I ſhall anon touch upon theſe in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, I ſhall here only ſhew you the ſeveral acceptions of theſe <hi>Waters:</hi> The <hi>literal</hi> I have briefly pointed at alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>By Waters</hi> we may underſtand the <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by holy <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 88.17. <hi>They came round about me daily like water, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me together on every ſide.</hi> And <hi>Pſalm</hi> 144.7. He prayeth after this manner, <hi>Send down thine hand from above, deliver me, and take me out of the great Waters, from the hand of ſtrange children.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15. The Angel expounding the viſion of the great Whore, which ſat upon many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, telleth St. <hi>John</hi> in expreſs words, <hi>The waters which thou ſaweſt, where the Whore ſitteth, they are people, and multitudes, and nations, and tongues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, by <hi>waters</hi> we may underſtand <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and doctrines of Devils. So <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retius,</hi> and others expound that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.15. Where we read, that the <hi>Serpent</hi> caſt out of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170350:9"/>his mouth water as a flood after the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that he might cauſe her to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away of the flood.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, by <hi>waters,</hi> we may underſtand the <hi>Abyſs</hi> of deſperation. So we may conſtrue that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 69. The waters are come in even unto my ſoul, <hi>verſe</hi> 1. I am come into deep waters, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. Let not the water-flood drown me, <hi>verſe</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>The Churches ſecond <hi>paſſage</hi> is, <hi>per ignes, when thou walkeſt thorow the fire:</hi> which <hi>fire</hi> is firſt literally to be taken, and we have examples of ſome in Scripture that found a ſafe paſſage thorow this fire, as <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and the three Children.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, by <hi>Fire,</hi> we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand perſecution and affliction, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 66. <hi>Thou laydſt trouble upon our loynes,</hi> Ingreſſi ſumus per ignem, <hi>we went thorow the fire.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> uſeth the ſame Metaphor, Think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery tryal which is to trie you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  <p>The reſult then of all is briefly this, That it is the portion of the Church to paſs thorow fire and water; it is her deſtiny to ſuffer perſecution and affliction.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170350:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark was a notable repreſentation of the Church, that was toſſed upon the waves in the general inundation, ſo is this in the worlds troubled ſea which cannot reſt. The <hi>Diſciples Ship,</hi> in the Goſpel, was another figure of the <hi>Church,</hi> that was covered with waves, almoſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with a raging Tempeſt; ſo this is filled with the ſcornfull reproof of the wealthy, the deep waters of the proud are ready to run even over her ſoul. The <hi>Church</hi> is a <hi>Ship,</hi> the world is the <hi>Sea,</hi> a Sea of glaſs mingled with fire, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2. Of glaſs, there is the brittle and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant condition of the world; mingled with fire, here are the troubles of the Church, St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s fiery Tryal. Troubled alas! ſhe is, and ſo hath ever been. Look upon <hi>Jacob,</hi> look upon <hi>Joſeph,</hi> look upon <hi>David,</hi> look upon the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> the time would fail me to tell you of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, of the <hi>Martyrs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours,</hi> and other holy men of God, how they paſſed thorow the waters, how they walked thorow the fire, how they had Trial of cruel Mockings and Scourgings, yea, moreover alſo of bonds and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, how they were ſtoned, as Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> how they were ſawn aſunder, as the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170350:10"/>Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> how they were ſlain with the ſword, as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> how they were beneaded, as St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> how they were hanged, as <hi>Tomkins</hi> and <hi>Chalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Yeomans</hi> and <hi>Bourchier,</hi> how they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred about in deſerts, and mountains, and in dens, and caves of the earth, in ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins, and Goat-skins, being deſtitute, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, tormented. Thus we ſee that all which will be loyal to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> all that will live godly in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution. Till our Saviour came into the ſhip, the Sea was calm and quiet; but when he was once aboard, there ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way aroſe a mighty Tempeſt. So long then as thou art without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or without <hi>God</hi> in this world, the Devil will make fair weather round about thee; but when once <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> is, as it were, come aboard thy ſoul, then will Satan raiſe a ſtorm to try if he can make ſhipwrack of thy faith; when thou haſt liſted thy ſelf a ſouldier to fight under thy <hi>Saviours</hi> and thy <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns</hi> banner, then look for a whole ſhewer of fiery arrows from the wicked one, for the Meſſenger of Satan to buffet thee, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> both by inward tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, and outward tribulations, by private ſuggeſtions, and publick perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170350:10"/>the Devil will ſtrive to ſplit thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rock of deſperation. But take this for thy comfort, that although thou art dangerouſly toſſed, yet thou ſhalt not be caſt away, for even <hi>He</hi> that upholdeth the Heavens is thine upholder. Which leadeth me from the ſecond part of the Text, the Churches <hi>Paſsage,</hi> thorow fire and water, to the third, which is the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant</hi> or <hi>Convoy,</hi> Almighty God, <hi>I am,</hi> or <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I that am the great Creator of Heaven and Earth, I that fill all places, and am contained in none; I that am about thy path, and about thy bed, and ſpie out all thy wayes, <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what need then is there of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe? For we may ſay it without Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that God muſt ſtill be with us, it being as impoſſible for him to deny his Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as to deny himſelf, he can ſooner ſeparate heat from fire; he did that in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s furnace he can ſooner ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate light from the Sun: He did this at our <hi>Saviours</hi> expiration: The <hi>Creator</hi> can better do any thing, than divorce or divide his preſence from his Creatures, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not only our well-being, but our very being doth conſiſt, ſhould he ſubſtract his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170350:11"/>preſence from us, we muſt return into our firſt nothing. He is not far therefore from every one of us, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> nay, he is neerer to us, than we are unto our ſelves, <hi>I will be with thee.</hi> But, ye know, there is a twofold preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. Firſt, His general preſence, which is his univerſall power and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whereby he governeth and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all things, both in Heaven and Earth, and under the Earth, according to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſalm 139. <hi>If I climb up into heaven, thou art there; if I go down to hell, thou art there alſo: If I take the wings of the morning, and remain in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea, even there alſo ſhall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me.</hi> Secondly, There is Gods ſpecial preſence, whereby he is preſent with his Elect only; either to prevent their Troubles, or elſe to comfort and ſupport them. And chiefly is he with his ſervants in his Temple, at his publick Worſhip, which may eaſily be explained by an example. The <hi>King</hi> is, or ought to be by his Power in all parts of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet he is ſaid to be there eſpecially, where his <hi>Courtiers,</hi> where his <hi>Retinue</hi> is: In like manner the <hi>King of Kings</hi> by his unbounded Power and Providence is at all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170350:11"/>times, in all places, yet we may know him to be with us after an eſpecial manner in the <hi>Temple,</hi> from the <hi>Retinue</hi> of heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Courtiers</hi> that are there attending on him. For it was not for Ornament only that the Walls of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple were carved round about with <hi>Cherubims,</hi> but alſo to ſignifie that the holy <hi>Angels</hi> are ever about us at our publick ſervices. And if <hi>Angels</hi> be there, much more is the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Saints, Tibi adſum,</hi> I am, or <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are three things eſpecially that will continually be with us; The <hi>Air,</hi> our <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Almighty <hi>God.</hi> We may as well be without our being, as without our breath; take but away this from us, and take away us too. The <hi>Air</hi> leaveth us not till death: Our <hi>Conſcience,</hi> this goeth further with us, it remaineth with us after death to all Eternity. Do not therefore the leaſt ſin, though none be with thee but thine own conſcience, for this will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company thee to thy death-bed; nay, this worm will live for ever. And thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not more inſeparable from thee then thy <hi>Creatour;</hi> whiſper never ſo ſoftly he will hear thee; hide thy ſelf never ſo cloſely, he will ſee thee; run away never
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170350:12"/>ſo ſwiftly, he will ſtill be at thine el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, <hi>Tibi adſum,</hi> I am, or <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I ſhould not ſpeak ſo much of <hi>Gods general</hi> preſence, his <hi>ſpecial</hi> preſence is that which I muſt here inſiſt upon. That preſence which he promiſed his <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> that preſence which our Saviour promiſed his <hi>Apoſtles, Lo; I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world,</hi> Mat. 28. ult. Alway, there is no <hi>Intermiſsion.</hi> To the end of the world, that is, world without end, here is no <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> We may have men for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions that will forſake us in diſtreſs; or if they ſtick to us all our life, they muſt leave us in our death. But if God be our Companion, if God be preſent with us, it is not diſtreſs, it is not death ſhall ever part us; nay, death ſhall unite us more neerly than ever we were before; we ſhall alway be with him, he will alway be with us, <hi>Tibi adſum,</hi> I am, or <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if God be thus alway preſent with his <hi>Church,</hi> we may then expoſtulate here, as <hi>Gideon</hi> once did with the Angel, <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Oh my Lord, if the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us?</hi> Why is the blood of his dear ſervants ſhed like water on every ſide? Why ſuffereth he the Turk
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170350:12"/>Turk and Pope to drink themſelves drunk with the blood of <hi>Saints,</hi> and with the blood of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> of <hi>Jeſus?</hi> I anſwer, though ſeemingly God abſent himſelf from his Church for a ſeaſon, yet never will he finally forſake her. Seemingly, I ſay, for indeed he abſenteth not himſelf at all, it is but in our apprehenſion that he is ever from us; if we can but believe it, he is preſent with us alway, <hi>Tibi adſum,</hi> I am, or <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Application of this now may be twofold. Firſt, Here is comfort for all that mourn in <hi>Sion,</hi> and with good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> turn their face to the Wall. Let them be caſt into priſon as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was; Let them be caſt into a dungeon as <hi>Jeremy</hi> was; let them be caſt into a den, as <hi>Daniel</hi> was; let them be caſt into the water, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was; let them be caſt into the fire, as the <hi>three</hi> Children were; let them go thorow fire and water, famine and ſword, never ſo many dangers, never ſo great diſaſters, yet ſo long as they have God with them, this will ſweeten all their pills, in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the ſorrows, which they have in their hearts; his comfortable preſence will refreſh their ſouls. Secondly; Seeing God is ſtill with <hi>us;</hi> this ſhould teach us
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170350:13"/>likewiſe to be ſtill with him, ſeeing he vouchſafeth to keep company with us on earth, therefore our converſation ſhould be with him in Heaven. When we are lying down to ſleep, to him we ſhould commit our ſpirits; when we wake up likewiſe, we ſhould be preſent with him. It was <hi>Jacob</hi>'s vow, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. That if <hi>God</hi> would be with him, then the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould be his <hi>God.</hi> We need not ſpeak ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, for <hi>God</hi> is certainly with thoſe that fear him, not only by his general, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by his ſpecial preſence, to direct and protect them, to deliver and to defend them, which leadeth me from the third part of the Text, the <hi>Concomitant,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty <hi>God,</hi> to the fourth and laſt, which is the <hi>Conſequent,</hi> the <hi>Churches ſafety, Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina non operient, flamma non incendet, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee, the flame ſhall not kindle on the.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I propounded four acceptions of theſe <hi>Waters,</hi> ye ſhall ſee that the Church paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſafely thorow them all.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Thorow waters, taken in the <hi>lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> ſenſe, as we may ſee by ſundry exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. The firſt may be that of <hi>Noah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sin had once ſo ſoiled the earth, that God was fain to lay it a ſoak; it was ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170350:13"/>foul, that nothing would cleanſe it but a flood. There were <hi>Gyants</hi> in <hi>ſin,</hi> as well as in <hi>Stature,</hi> the wickedneſs of man was great in the earth. And <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum,</hi> this depth of ſin called for as deep a deluge, the flood-gates therefore were pluckt up, the windowes from on high were opened. And what diſtreſs of Nations was there then with perplexity, the ſea and the waves roaring, and mens hearts failing them for fear? Methinks I ſee how abruptly their Marriage-feaſts are diſſolved, what haſte they make out adoors, that they may get up into trees; how ſome climb the tops of mountains, <hi>Tamen ultra pergere tendunt.</hi> But the waters continually following them at heels, when all hope that they ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape drowning was taken away; methinks, I hear them curſe the day that ever they were born, and wiſh, if it were poſſible, that they might be metamorphoſed into fiſhes. <hi>But Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord,</hi> when the flood was brought in upon the world of the ungodly. For though it rained, as if heaven and earth would have come together, though the waters were ſo grown, as to over-top the higheſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, yet heavens great <hi>Palinurus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>Noah</hi> in this <hi>Ocean, Elumina non operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170350:14"/>the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> may be a ſecond example, whoſe preſervation was indeed far ſtranger than <hi>Noah</hi>'s; for <hi>Noah</hi> had a ſhip, the <hi>Iſrealites</hi> had none, which made them think that there was no way in the world with them but drowning, <hi>Mars</hi> in the rear, and <hi>Neptune</hi> facing of them; they thought that one of theſe muſt needs devour <hi>Iſrael</hi> with open mouth. But <hi>He</hi> that brought light out of darkneſs, brought ſafety out of their greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: what they feared would be their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, this God made their preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for rather than <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, <hi>Jordan</hi> ſhall forget his fluid nature, the floods ſhall ſtand upright as an heap, and the depths ſhall be congealed in the heart of the <hi>Sea.</hi> Gods people need not fear the waters; the waters ſaw them, and were afraid, and therefore ran away with might and main, to make way for them. The waters indeed faced, as if they had known the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> drowning the hoſte of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> but inmmuring the hoſte of <hi>Iſrael, Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> may be a third example to this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170350:14"/>purpoſe. There were never two crueller <hi>Tyrants</hi> than <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> one drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the male Children, the other cut their throats. But as Chriſt eſcaped from <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> ſo from <hi>Pharoah Moſes,</hi> whoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents durſt not long entertain him in their houſe, when he was but a quarter old, they ſhipt him in an <hi>Ark</hi> of ruſhes. But how properly may that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> be applyed to him. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 27.10. <hi>When my father and my mother forſook we, then the Lord taketh me up.</hi> Or rather indeed the <hi>Lady</hi> did this, even <hi>Thermutis,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>'s daughter, <hi>Flumina non opertent, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to theſe examples, I may add <hi>Elijah's</hi> and <hi>Eliſha's</hi> paſſage over <hi>Jordan,</hi> the <hi>Diſciples</hi> with our <hi>Saviour</hi> in the ſhip, and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s moſt dangerous voyage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Rome;</hi> all corroborating and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming this Aſſertion in our Text, <hi>Flumina non operient, the Rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord ſitteth above the water-flood,</hi> Pſal. 29.9. I remember a ſtory of one that wondered why any man would go to ſea, ſeeing ſo many die at ſea, to whom one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, he might wonder as well, why any man will go to bed, ſeeing ſo many di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170350:15"/>their beds. <hi>Dii maris &amp; terrae,</hi> may be put into <hi>Gods</hi> royal Title, <hi>His way is in the ſea, and his paths in the great waters;</hi> he that was able without a ſhip to walk ſafely on the ſea, muſt needs be able to ſave thoſe that go down to the ſea in ſhips: while they are following their honeſt vocation, they may be aſſured of his protection, he ſhall give his <hi>Angels</hi> charge over them to keep them in all their wayes, the Angel of the water mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5. This <hi>Angel</hi> ſhall be their Pilot, and conduct them to their wiſhed haven. <hi>Flumina non operient, the Rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, By <hi>Waters</hi> we underſtand the <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> neither ſhall theſe waters be able to overflow her. The ſeed of the <hi>Serpent</hi> will ſtill be warring with the <hi>womans</hi> ſeed; the <hi>Dragon</hi> and his, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Michael</hi> and his <hi>Angels.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> will ever be maligned by the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue</hi> of <hi>Satan;</hi> but though theſe waters ſwell, yet they ſhall not prevail againſt her. <hi>David</hi>'s enemies were daily in hand to ſwallow him up; but theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the proud had bounds, which they could never paſs. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was both In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded and beſieged by the <hi>Aſſyrians;</hi> but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170350:15"/>how ſtrangely was he preſerved from him that had drunk ſtrange waters, and who <hi>with the ſole of his feet had dried up all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of beſieged places.</hi> I have not time to ſhew you all the particular preſervations of Gods people, how he hath ſaved them ſtill from the reproof of thoſe that would have eaten them up.</p>
                  <p>And from this experience of Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, together with the promiſes of Gods future favour, we may draw this applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we may here put on the reſolution of holy <hi>David,</hi> not to fear, though the earth be moved, and though the hills be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the midſt of the ſea, though the waters thereof rage and ſwell, and though the mountains ſhake at the tempeſt of the ſame. Let the Heathen never ſo furiouſly rage together, and let the people imagine a vain thing; let the Rulers ſtand up, and take Counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his <hi>Anointed,</hi> and againſt his <hi>Church;</hi> Let <hi>Gebal,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleck,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> with them that dwell at <hi>Tyre;</hi> let <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, Antichriſt</hi> and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Turk,</hi> nay, let all the devils in hell be confederate againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> yet ſtill ſhe ſhall be ſafe, the ſon of wickedneſs ſhall not hurt her, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170350:16"/>gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt her, <hi>Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let me apply this more particularly to my <hi>Soveraign Lord</hi> the <hi>King.</hi> The floods have riſen, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh, the floods lift up their voice, the floods lift up their waves. But theſe floods of ungodly men I truſt ſhall not overflow him, though the waves of the ſea are mighty, and rage horribly, yet the <hi>Lord</hi> (that's one good turn) which dwelleth on high, is mightier, and he will ſend down from the high to fetch him, he will take him out of many waters; he will make theſe Traitors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our common phraſe, as weak as water, as water ſpilt upon the ground, which cannot be gathered up; he ſtills the raging of the ſea, &amp; the noiſe of his waves, and the madneſs of the people; from the waters of ſtrife, he will bring the <hi>King</hi> to the ſtill waters, he will deliver him from the ſtrivings of the people, and he will make him the head of the heathen, the fierceneſs of theſe wicked men ſhall turn to his praiſe, and the fierceneſs of them he will certainly refrain, <hi>Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſeen, ſaid <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſo have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170350:16"/>we, <hi>Servants upon horſes, and Princes walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ſervants upon the earth;</hi> but I hope we ſhall not much longer ſee this ſight. Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is a good <hi>ſervant,</hi> but a bad <hi>Maſter;</hi> God therefore, I truſt, will ſhortly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of an arbitrary <hi>Anarchy,</hi> from the Soveraignty of our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſubjects, <hi>Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, By <hi>Waters,</hi> we underſtood <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies</hi> and doctrines of devils; neither ſhall theſe waters overflow the <hi>Church.</hi> The Devil is ever changing Gods Truth into a lie; if <hi>God</hi> have ſaid, ye ſhall, <hi>Satan</hi> will ſay, ye ſhall not die. And God ſendeth ſome ſuch ſtrong deluſions, that, as <hi>Eve</hi> did, they believe a lie; the <hi>Dragons</hi> flood of errours quite drowneth them in perdition. But the <hi>Church</hi> ſhall not miſcarry for all this <hi>Dragon-water,</hi> the earth (as it is <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.) ſhall ſwallow up the floods; The <hi>Earth,</hi> that is, the earthly minded, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly of the world, ſhall ſwallow up the flood, that is, ſhall approve of, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain theſe wicked errours. Not a little of this water hath been emptied into the river <hi>Tyber,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed down a great part of this <hi>Dragons</hi> flood. The reſidue hath been ſwallowed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170350:17"/>by <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Antinomians, Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Novatians; Marcionites</hi> and <hi>Manichees, Socinians</hi> and <hi>Arminians, Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents, Browniſts</hi> and <hi>Burtoniſts, Sciſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Separatiſts, Familiſts</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts,</hi> while we that are right <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> take in none but living water, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the water of Truth out of the well of ſalvation; the flood of errour ſhall never ſurround or overwhelm us, <hi>Flumina non ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient, the rivers ſhall not overflow us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, by <hi>Waters</hi> we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Abyſs</hi> of deſperation, neither ſhall theſe waters overflow the <hi>Church.</hi> One while the devil telleth men that God is made up of all mercy; another while, that his Mercy is not ſo great as their ſins; firſt, he would flatter them into <hi>Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then he would fright them into <hi>deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</hi> And when he hath brought them to this latter ſtate, then they are apt to drown themſelves, like that Lunatick, which oft-times fell into the water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.15. But the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to deliver the godly out of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. He will not ſuffer them to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred above that they are able, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that they may be able to bear it.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170350:17"/>
                  <p>Art thou come therefore into deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo that the floods are running over thee? Hath Satan brought thee to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry brink of deſperation? why, yet he ſhall never be able to bring thee any further, if thou belong to Chriſt; he could not drown the ſilly ſwine without <hi>Chriſts</hi> leave; (and thy Saviour will never licence him to do thee ſuch a miſchief) he is but like a dog in a ſtring, like a Dragon in a chain, ſo that thou maiſt aſſure thy ſelf, he can do thee no hurt without Gods ſpecial warrant and commiſſion. Though thou walkeſt therefore thorow the valley of deſpair, yet fear no evil, for there is a way to heaven juſt by the gates of Hell. It is the nature of clay to dam up the eyes, yet our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> put clay upon the blind to make him ſee. It is the nature of water to put out fire; yet <hi>Elijah</hi> poured water upon his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to make it burn. God many times bringeth about his ends by means, which to our thinking, are quite contrary. As he letteth ſome therefore ſoar with <hi>Icarus</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wings of preſumption (I mean the <hi>Rebels</hi> of our age) <hi>ut lapſu graviore ruant,</hi> that their down-fall may be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the heat of Gods wrath melting them, as wax melteth at the fire, and they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitating
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170350:18"/>head-long into the ſea of deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So God ſuffereth others ſometimes to fall into deſpair, that the depth of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery may invoke the depth of mercy, he throweth them as it were balls againſt the ground, to make them bound the higher. When thou thinkeſt therefore he hath quite left thee, then he is neareſt to thee; when thou walkeſt thorow the brook of deſpair, then he will lift up thy head, his rod and his ſtaffe ſhall conduct thee thorow theſe <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> waters, <hi>Flumina non operient, the rivers ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. And ſo ye have the <hi>ſafety</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in her firſt paſſage, which was, <hi>per aquas, thorow the waters.</hi> Ye ſhall ſee her <hi>ſafety</hi> likewiſe in her ſecond paſſage, which is, <hi>per ignes,</hi> thorow the fire, <hi>when thou walkeſt thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non combureris, thou ſhalt not be burnt,</hi> Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. It hath therefore been the practice of perſecutors in al ages to burn up al the <hi>Bibles</hi> that they could lay hands on, knowing this to be the ready way for them to deſtroy the faith of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But how ſtrangely hath the <hi>Bible</hi> ſcaped even in the moſt fiery perſecutions! though ſome part
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170350:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>of it may be loſt, as the prophecy of <hi>Enoch</hi> and the book of <hi>Jaſher,</hi> yet there is ſo much left ſtill, as containeth in it all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, God would never ſuffer all of it to be made fewel for the fire, <hi>Non combureris, thou ſhalt not be burnt. Neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> The damned in hell are ever burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, never burnt, but who can dwell with thoſe everlaſting burnings? They could with a good will put up that petition, <hi>Hic ure, hic ſeca,</hi> that God would cut them all in pieces, and then burn them up to very nothing. But ſhould they make many ſuch prayers, there would none of them be heard, they ſhall not be burnt, <hi>The flame ſhall not kindle on them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to come nearer to the <hi>Text</hi> we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouded ſome examples out of the Scripture, of men that paſſed ſafly thorow fire literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken the Firſt may be <hi>Lot.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. God uſually proportioneth the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sodome</hi> burned in <hi>luſt,</hi> and was therefore burnt with <hi>Fire,</hi> but though brimſtome and fire were rained upon the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> yet God delivered <hi>Lot</hi> out of the midſt of the overthrow, <hi>Non combureris, thou ſhalt be burnt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170350:19"/>
                  <p>The ſecond example may be <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who came very neer the fire, behold the fire and wood, nay, behold he is laid on the <hi>Altar upon the wood.</hi> Yet for all this, God ſuffered not <hi>Abraham</hi> to do him any hurt, he made an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to offer up <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the will went for the deed, <hi>Non combureris, thou ſhalt not be burnt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third example may be the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in whoſe company the fire was kindled, there went out a fire from the Lord, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the two hundred and fifty men that offered incenſe, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.35. But though the flame burnt up the ungodly <hi>mutiniers,</hi> yet every obedient <hi>Iſraelite</hi> eſcaped, <hi>Non combureris, thou ſhalt not be burnt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth example may be the three <hi>Salamanders,</hi> in the furnace <hi>Dan</hi> 3. who though they walked thorow the fire, yet their coats were not changed, nor ſo much as the ſmell of fire had paſſed on them. And this laſt example is without example; I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of any <hi>fire-proof</hi> before, for <hi>Fire</hi> is of a moſt devouring and conſuming na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, turning all combuſtible things into aſhes that come neer it, yet the children of the fire, the ſparks hurt not theſe three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with the ſhields of their faith they quench'd the violence of fire, <hi>when they wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170350:19"/>thorow the fire, they were not burnt, neither did the flame kindle upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to theſe I might adde, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what out of order, the example of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> whom God brought out of <hi>Ur</hi> of the <hi>Caldees, Gen.</hi> 15.7. Now <hi>Ur,</hi> as <hi>Huge</hi> obſerveth, ſignifyeth fire, the Greek word, from which our Engliſh word ſeemeth to come, hath but one Letter more; and therefore the <hi>Hebrews</hi> had a tradition, that becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> would not worſhip the <hi>Fire,</hi> as the <hi>Caldeans</hi> did, he ſhould have been caſt into the fire, had not God given him notice of it, and ſo preſerved him.</p>
                  <p>But though <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> ſignifie fire, yet the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Gloſſe</hi> taketh it not for a <hi>common,</hi> but a <hi>proper</hi> Name, for the Name of the town or village where <hi>Abraham</hi> dwelt. This example therefore cannot claim kindred of the Text: I might more properly bring in our preſervation from the <hi>Powder-treaſon,</hi> but I will rather anſwer a queſtion that may riſe from our Text: for is this promiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes performed? Thou ſhalt not be burnt, the flame ſhall not kindle on thee. What ſhall we ſay then to that fiery perſecution in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes, when there were ſo many <hi>Bethels</hi> in this Kingdome, ſo many <hi>Cities</hi> wherein mens bones were burnt?</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170350:20"/>
                  <p>I Anſwer, it is true that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> this <hi>Church</hi> in particular hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the fiery triall. But as <hi>Rex non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur,</hi> ſo <hi>Eccleſia non comburitur,</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> is never buried, ſo the <hi>Church</hi> is never burnt, <hi>James</hi> may die, and ſo may <hi>Charles,</hi> (yet God maintaine his life) but the <hi>King</hi> (let rebels do what they can) never dieth: So <hi>Latimer</hi> may be burnt, and <hi>Cranmer</hi> may be burnt, but the <hi>Church</hi> is never burnt. If <hi>Pagans</hi> ſhould prevail ſo farre (which God forbid) as to burne up all the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> or if <hi>Puritans</hi> ſhould prevaile ſo far (which God forbid too) as to burne up all the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> yet I verily believe that out of their very aſhes, God would raiſe up a new <hi>Phoenix, Cinis Mariyrum</hi> ſhould be <hi>Semen Eccleſiae,</hi> the aſhes of an old ſhould be the ſeed of a new Church, ſhe ſhall not be ſo burnt, as to be quite extinct, <hi>neither ſhall the flame ſo kindle upon her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Application hereof now may be briefly thus. Seeing God will not ſuffer his Church to be finally burnt up by others, this may teach us (as it were) to ſet on fire our ſelves, not with the fire of <hi>lust,</hi> it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to marry than ſo to burn; nor with the fire of <hi>wrath,</hi> rather heap coals of fire upon the head of the enemies; but let it be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170350:20"/>with the veſtal fire of <hi>devotion</hi> and <hi>affection,</hi> let our hearts burn within us with love to God and men. So ſhall neither the ſun burn us by day, nor the moon by night, the Lord ſhall preſerve us form all evil, it is even he that will keep both our bodies and our ſouls, when the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, when the earth, and the Works therein ſhall be burnt up, he will preſerve and keep us from everlaſting fire, and exalt us to his <hi>Coelum empyreum,</hi> his fiery heaven, there for ever to behold him, whoſe eyes are as a flame of fire, and his feet like unto fine braſs, as if they burned in a furnace: And ſo ye have the <hi>ſafety</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in her paſſage thorow fire <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally</hi> taken. Ye ſhall ſee her <hi>ſafety</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as ſhe paſſeth thorow the fire of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and perſecution; <hi>When thou walkeſt thorow this fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is the nature of fire <hi>Congregare homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genea,</hi> and <hi>Segregare heterogenea,</hi> to bring together things of the ſame kind, and to ſeparate things of divers kinds; A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer therefore is wont to bring his Myne to the fire, and by this means he ſevereth the ſilver from the droſs, which is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170350:21"/>wiſe the very practice of Almighty God, it is the Prophet <hi>Malachie</hi>'s ſimilitude word for word, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.3. <hi>He ſhall ſit as a Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Purifier of ſilver, and he ſhall purifie the ſons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and purge them as gold and ſilver.</hi> And the ſweet <hi>Singer of Iſrael</hi> harpeth upon the ſame ſtring, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 66.9. Thou, O God, haſt proved us, thou alſo haſt tried us, like as ſilver is tried. <hi>Non ſicut foenum, ſed ſicut argentum, non in cineres convertiſti, ſed ſordes abluiſti,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin,</hi> God trieth us not with a conſuming, but with a cleanſing fire, turneth us not into aſhes, only taketh away our ſullage and our aſhes from us, purely purgeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our droſs, and taketh away all our tinne. God purgeth men by affliction, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were to purge the ſpoil of the <hi>Midianites.</hi> Numb. 31.23. <hi>Every thing that may abide the fire, ye ſhall make it go thorow the fire, and it ſhall be clean.</hi> God trieth men by affliction what metal they are made of, they that endure this fiery tryal, they are good gold, they are Gods Children; they that endure it not, they are but droſs, they are but Caſt-awayes. Good men are like <hi>Shadrach, Meſhack</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> though they walk thorow the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170350:21"/>furnace of Affliction, yet they are not burnt up, no not ſo much as ſinged; but wicked men are like the ſouldiers that bound and caſt them in, when they are yet but at the mouth of the fiery furnace, when the fire of Affliction but beginneth to ſeize upon them, it prevaileth againſt them, and conſumeth them in a moment.</p>
                  <p>Good men are, in this, like <hi>clay,</hi> the fire of Affliction ſtrengthneth and confirmeth them; but wicked men are like <hi>wax,</hi> as wax melteth at the fire, ſo do the ungodly periſh in the fiery tryal; Affliction to them is like the fire that burneth up the wood, and like the flame that conſumeth the mountains; God maketh them like a fiery oven in time of his wrath, the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth them in his diſpleaſure, and the fire conſumeth them. Affliction maketh wicked men a great deal worſe, as water becometh much colder after heating, than ever it would have been, if it had never been heated. As for the Righteous; it is not ſo with them. God burneth them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed throughly, as the bricks of <hi>Babel</hi> were, but this is only as a Potter frameth his veſſels in the fire, that ſo they may be veſſels unto honour, and for the Maſters
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170350:22"/>uſe, <hi>though they walk thorow the fire, yet they are not burnt, neither doth the flame kindle upon them.</hi> When <hi>Job's</hi> wife heard of all the evil that God had brought upon her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſhe grew ſo mad, ſo out-ragious and impatient, that ſhe would fain have perſwaded him to make away with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, what, ſaith ſhe, all that ever thou hadſt taken away from thee? Is this the reward thou haſt for thine integrity? Well, ſerve God, who will, I would ſerve him no longer, make good the devils words, if thou wilt be ruled by me, do, as he ſaid thou wouldeſt in ſuch a caſe, even curſe God and die, <hi>Job</hi> 2.9. But ye have heard of the patience of <hi>Job,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> let his wife therefore ſay what ſhe will, he will have none of her counſel, thou talkeſt like an Aſſe, ſaith he, thou ſpeakeſt like one of the fooliſh women. And indeed (as he goeth on) ſhall we receive good at the hand of God, and not receive evil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo? Shall we receive health and not ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wealth and not poverty, peace and not War, honour and not diſhonour, liberty and not reſtraint? yea, my brethren, if we be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we muſt reſolve to endure all. And if we do this, then we may aſſure our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170350:22"/>ſelves, that although we ſow in tears, yet we ſhall reap in joy, though God have long ſuffered wicked men to ride over our heads, though we have gone thorow fire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet God in his good time will bring us and our Soveraign out into a wealthy place, he will caſt theſe rods of his anger into the fire, and then mercy ſhall embrace us on every ſide, our light affliction, which is but for a moment, ſhall work for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; which God of his infinite mercy grant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE ASSUMPTION OF THE Meſsiah.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon PREACHED Before His MAJESTY, <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> the II<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. AT THE <hi>HAGUE</hi> in <hi>HOLLAND,</hi> on <hi>Sunday May</hi> 29. old ſtile 1649.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:24"/>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170350:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>THE ASSUMPTION OF THE Meſsiah.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ACTS 1.9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>And when he had ſpoken theſe things, while they beheld, he was taken up, and a cloud received him out of their ſight.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which is ſpoken of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the firmament, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.6. St. <hi>Austin</hi> upon that place applieth unto the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs, His going forth is from the end of heaven,</hi> there, ſaith he, is <hi>Chriſts</hi> deſcenſion from the boſome of his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170350:25"/>
                     <hi>Father; and his circuit unto the ends of it,</hi> here, ſaith he, is his aſcenſion to the place from whence he came. And our <hi>Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath much ſuch another paſſage, <hi>John</hi> 16.28. Which place may not unfitly be compared unto a Circle; <hi>I came forth from the Father, and am come into the world,</hi> there is the ſemicircle: again, <hi>I leave the world, and go to the Father,</hi> here is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Circle.</p>
                  <p>And by this we may ſee what agreement there is between the <hi>material Sun</hi> and the <hi>Mystical.</hi> The <hi>Sun</hi> in the firmament is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to light the day: ſo as long as I am in the world, ſaith our <hi>Saviour,</hi> I am the light of the world, <hi>John</hi> 9.5. The <hi>Sun,</hi> though in the firmament, ſtoopeth to lighten us below: So, though our <hi>Saviours</hi> dwelling were in heaven, yet he humbleth himſelf to behold us here on earth. The <hi>Sun</hi> ariſeth, and the <hi>Sun</hi> goeth down, and haſteth to the place where he aroſe, <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 1.5. So the <hi>Sun</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> came from one hemiſphere, from light inacceſſible, from the place of bleſſed <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> that he might ſhine unto the other hemiſphere, to us their forlorn <hi>Antipodes,</hi> to us mortals that ſat in darkneſs, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170350:25"/>
                  <p>But as the <hi>Sun</hi> maketh haſt to the place where he aroſe, dwelleth not alway with us, but returneth again according to his circuits. In like manner the <hi>Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> having lightned his <hi>Apostles</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by his Doctrine, and having warmed and cheared their hearts by his promiſe of ſending them the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> having given them the word of reſolution, of inſtruction, and of benediction, he took his leave of the earth, and returned into heaven, <hi>And when he had ſpoken theſe things, while they beheld, he was taken up, and a cloud received him out of their ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Text then is a deſcription of our <hi>Saviour's Aſcenſion,</hi> wherein there are ſix particulars to be conſider'd, four plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, two neceſſarily implied. The firſt is <hi>Quis,</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> that aſcended, which was <hi>Christ,</hi> he that deſcended was the ſame alſo that aſcended, <hi>He</hi> was taken up. The ſecond is <hi>Quando,</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> of the aſcenſion, which may be conſidered two wayes, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> forty dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, or in reference to his laſt exerciſe, the reſolving his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> doubts, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing, and the bleſſing of them, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after this, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, when he had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170350:26"/>ſpoken theſe things. The third is <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde,</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> from whence he aſcended, which by comparing <hi>Acts</hi> 1.12. with <hi>Luke</hi> 24.50. we ſhall finde to be that part of mount <hi>Olivet</hi> next to <hi>Bethany,</hi> he was taken up from thence. The fourth is <hi>Quo,</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> whither he aſcended, which was heaven, he was taken up thither. The fifth is <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo,</hi> the manner of his aſcenſion, ſet down here two wayes, Firſt <hi>Poſitively,</hi> he was taken up. Secondly <hi>Expoſitively,</hi> a cloud received him out of their ſight. The ſixt and laſt are <hi>Teſtes</hi> the <hi>Spectatours,</hi> or the witneſſes of his aſcenſion, which were the Eleven <hi>Apoſtles, while they beheld he was taken up,</hi> &amp;c. And of theſe in order.</p>
                  <p>I begin with the firſt particular, <hi>Quis,</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> that aſcended, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> He was taken up.</p>
                  <p>He that was from the begining, nay, he that is the beginning, <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and the ending; He that is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Imamnuel,</hi> God with us, he that is one in <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Duality,</hi> he that made on <hi>Perſon</hi> of two <hi>Natures,</hi> And which of theſe <hi>natures</hi> then was aſcended? It was his <hi>Humane</hi> nature, as may eaſily be gathered from thoſe words of the <hi>Angels</hi> to the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts.</hi> 1.11. The ſame <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170350:26"/>which is taken up from you into heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into heaven. Now we know that our Saviour ſhall come to judgement, as he is man, according to that of <hi>St. Paul, Acts.</hi> 71.31. where he ſaith that God hath appointed a day wherein he will judge the world in righteouſneſſe, by that man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead. Our Saviour therefore aſcended according to his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity. The Royal <hi>Pſalmist</hi> ſeemeth to ſay indeed that his <hi>Divinity</hi> aſcended, <hi>Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Deus in Iubilo, Dominus in voce tubae,</hi> God is gone up with a ſhout, and the Lord with the ſound of the trumpet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.5. As for his <hi>Humamity,</hi> our Saviour ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to ſay that this was in heaven before, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.13. No man hath aſcended up to heaven, but he that came downe from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven. But to theſe and all other ſuch objections I anſwer with <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi> the Divine and Humane nature of our Saviour being Hypoſtatically united in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Perſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, thoſe things, which are proper to either of his <hi>Natures,</hi> are attributed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170350:27"/>and communicated to his whole <hi>Perſon,</hi> Thus S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that God was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the fleſh, and that God was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up into glory, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding therefore theſe objections, the <hi>Perſon</hi> that aſcended was <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>Humanity, He</hi> was taken up.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He,</hi> it is not ſaid <hi>She</hi> was taken up; The <hi>Papiſts</hi> have <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> or rather <hi>Aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-day</hi> for the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which they annually celebrate upon the fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> whereon they ſay, She was taken up corporally into heaven. But this is as true as that the Diſciples ſtole our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour out of his grave: I am very ſure there is not the leaſt mention of any ſuch thing in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and where the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> hath no tongue to ſpeak, nor pen to write, there muſt we have no eare to hear, nor any heart to believe. Not the <hi>Woman</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt's mother, but the <hi>man Chriſt Jeſus</hi> himſelf <hi>He</hi> was taken up.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I paſſe from the firſt part of the <hi>Text,</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> aſcending, which was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the ſecond part, <hi>Quando,</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> of his aſcenſion, which we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider firſt, in reference to his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> forty dayes after that, <hi>then</hi> he was taken
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170350:27"/>up. But here two queſtions may be moved, Firſt, Why <hi>Chriſt</hi> did aſcend ſo ſoon? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, ſeeing ſo ſoon, why no ſooner?</p>
                  <p>The firſt queſtion may be, why he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo ſoon after his reſurrection, why he deferred not his aſcenſion till the laſt day, that we might have been taken up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him? To which I anſwer two wayes. Firſt, that Chriſt ſhould aſcend ſo ſoon, was not convenient in reſpect of <hi>him.</hi> Secondly, That he ſhould aſcend ſo ſoon, was not expedient in reſpect of <hi>us.</hi> Firſt, That he ſhould aſcend ſo ſoon, was not convenient in reſpect of <hi>himſelf.</hi> And that firſt in reſpect of his glorified body. <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> was the moſt convenient place for his incorruptible and immortall body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Earth</hi> is a very <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a region of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, a place of dead mens skuls. Though <hi>Christ</hi>'s body therefore could not have ſeen corruption, had it continued ſtill on earth, yet the fitteſt place for ſuch a body were the incorruptible <hi>heavens.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, it was convenient that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould aſcend ſo ſoon after his reſurrection, that he might manifeſt and declare the truth of his <hi>Divinity. Earth</hi> is a region of death,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quocunque aſpicias nihil eſt niſi mortis imago,</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170350:28"/>All that ever came hither, have, or muſt die once; and I aſſure my ſelf that <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and all the reſt that were raiſed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> or by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> or by his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> died twice; ſhould <hi>Chriſt</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after his reſurrection have continued here longer than he did, men would ſcarce have taken him to be God, but have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken him for a meer Man; and they would have thought that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> like <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> had been to die the ſecond time. Thus ye ſee, it was convenient in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he ſhould aſcend ſo ſoon after his reſurrection as he did. Ye ſhall now ſee, that this was expedient in reſpect of <hi>us.</hi> And the expediency of it we have from <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s own mouth. <hi>John</hi> 16.7. <hi>It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for you,</hi> ſaith he, (and what he ſaith to them, we may apply to us) <hi>that I go away;</hi> and he giveth his reaſon in the very next words, <hi>If</hi> I <hi>go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you,</hi> but if I depart, I will ſend him unto you. And <hi>John</hi> 7.39. we read, <hi>That the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glorified.</hi> Had there been no <hi>Holy Thurſday,</hi> had not our Saviour aſcended from his Apoſtles on the fortieth day, there had likewiſe been no <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt had not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170350:28"/>deſcended upon the Apoſtles on the fiftieth day.</p>
                  <p>Again, Had <hi>Chriſt</hi> remained ſtill upon earth, he had not been ſo proper an object of our faith, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>The evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> Heb. 11.1. Thy <hi>Fides</hi> will not well ſtand with thy <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des;</hi> we do not properly walk by faith, when we walk by ſight, <hi>Apparentia non habent fidem, ſed agnitionem,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> fruition putteth a period unto faith, and therefore <hi>Credimus ut cognoſcamus, non cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcimus ut credamus,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> we come to knowledge by faith, and not to faith by knowledge; the nature of faith is to be exerciſed about things abſent, wherefore <hi>though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, yet now henceforth know we him no more,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond queſtion may be, ſeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended ſo ſoon, why did he aſcend no ſooner? Why did he not make one aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for all? As ſoon as he roſe out of the grave, why did he not aſcend immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into heaven? To which I return a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold anſwer. Firſt, This was not conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Secondly, it was not convenient in reſpect of his <hi>Diſciples.</hi> Thirdly it was not convenient in reſpect of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170350:29"/>
                     <hi>us.</hi> Firſt, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould aſcend ſo ſoon, was not convenient in reſpect of <hi>Himſelf,</hi> for we know what a tradition the <hi>Jewes</hi> have among them untill this day, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that his <hi>Diſciples</hi> ſtole him away, while the ſouldiers were aſleep. Had not <hi>Christ</hi> therefore ſhewed himſef alive after his paſſion, though not to all the people, yet to certaine ſelected witneſſes, the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Jewes</hi> might have paſſed for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant truth, it might have been doubted to this day, whether he had been riſen from the dead or no. Secondly, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould aſcend immediately after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, was not convenient in reſpect of his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> whoſe faith was almoſt quite ſhipwrack'd at his death; they little thought he would make his word good to riſe again, and therefore the relation of the woman ſeemed to them as an old wives tale, they believed it not; nay, when our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf appeared unto them, they would ſcarce believe that it was he, but were terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and affrighted, ſuppoſing that they had ſeen a ſpirit. It was fit therefore that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be converſant awhile with theſe raw <hi>Schollers,</hi> both to confirm their faith touching that truth of his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo to inſtruct them in thoſe things
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170350:29"/>that were pertaining to Gods Kingdome. Thirdly and laſtly, that Chriſt ſhould aſcend immediately after his reſurrection, was not convenient in reſpect of <hi>us.</hi> For his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> were not properly <hi>Apoſtles</hi> till after his reſurrection, a good while; if they were <hi>Apostles,</hi> their <hi>Dioceſs</hi> was very narrow, though they were <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to the <hi>Iews,</hi> they were no <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Go not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſaid our <hi>Saviour</hi> to them, but only to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Had not <hi>Christ</hi> then after his reſurrection enlarged their Commiſſion, we had not heard, I doubt, unto this hour, whether there had been a <hi>Chriſt</hi> or no. For his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> would not have been like the <hi>Mechanicks</hi> in our dayes, they would not have run about the world, and preached without Commiſſion; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an <hi>Ite, Praedicate,</hi> go, and preach, how ſhould they have preached, except they had been ſent? Our <hi>Saviour</hi> therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed his aſcenſion into heaven to furniſh his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> with a <hi>Catholick</hi> Commiſſion, that ſo their ſound might go out into all Lands, and their Words unto the ends of world.</p>
                  <p>And ſo ye have the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion in reference to his Reſurrection.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170350:30"/>Be pleaſed now to conſider it in reference to his laſt exerciſe, which was the Reſolving of his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> doubts, the Inſtructing, and the Bleſſing of them, by and by after this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, when had ſpoken theſe things.</p>
                  <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> keepeth much ado about <hi>Theſe things,</hi> ſhe would hereby have her unwritten Traditions to be underſtood.</p>
                  <p>But though all things are not written, which our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpake, yet all things neceſſary to ſalvation, I am ſure, are written; the <hi>Goſpell</hi> were imperfect, ſhould <hi>Traditions</hi> be entertained. So that we are not to heed mens inventions, but only <hi>Christ</hi>'s inſtructions, He was the way, and he ſhewed all men the way that they ſhould walk in, as he ſhewed it his Apoſtles here, when he had ſpoken theſe things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things,</hi> that is, Firſt when he had reſolved their doubts. They asked him whether he would <hi>at that time reſtore the kingdome to Iſrael, Act.</hi> 1.6. To which he returned them a ſhort anſwer, that <hi>it was not for them to know the times, or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his owne power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this firſt may teach the <hi>Laity</hi> to bring their <hi>Queries,</hi> their <hi>Queſtions</hi> to the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170350:30"/>the Prieſts lips muſt preſerve knowledg, and they muſt ſeek the Law at his mouth,</hi> Mal. 2.7.</p>
                  <p>And as the <hi>People</hi> muſt bring their que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, ſo the <hi>Paſtour</hi> muſt reſolve them. And to this end St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have him <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>apt to teach,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. he muſt be both able and alſo ready to teach, and reſolve doubts, our <hi>Saviour</hi> aſcended not till he had done this, till he had reſolved his Apoſtles doubts, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>when he had ſpoken theſe things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things,</hi> That is, Secondly, when he had throughly inſtructed his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> in the way to heaven. Having lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his own which were in the world, he loved them unto the end, he preached unto them, till he departed from them, till he was taken up into heaven.</p>
                  <p>And herein he was firſt a patterne to all that are <hi>Preachers</hi> of his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> who, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſet their hand to his plow, ought never to look back.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Levites</hi> at fifty years old were freed from the ſervice of the Tabernacle. But no age will exempt or diſcharge us of our office, we muſt not ceaſe to exerciſe it, till we are juſt putting <hi>off this Tabernacle,</hi> though we are never ſo ſuperannuated, though we are ſuch as <hi>Paul the Aged,</hi> or
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170350:31"/>though ſo feeble, that like St. <hi>Iohn</hi> we were fain to be carryed to the pulpit. For as the <hi>Echo</hi> repeateth only the laſt part of the voice; ſo the people are apteſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the laſt part of the Sermon, and the laſt Sermon beſt: And therefore St. <hi>Peters</hi> reſolution was, that he would not ceaſe to be a <hi>Preacher,</hi> till he ceaſed to be a <hi>man,</hi> as we read 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 13.15. I <hi>will not be negligent to put you alwayes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of theſe things, though ye know them, and be eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth. Yea, I think it meet, as long as I am in this Tabernacle, to ſtir you up by putting you in remembrance; moreover, I will endeavour that ye may be able after my deceaſe to have theſe things alwayes in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as this affordeth a leſſon for <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> ſo doth it for <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> who ought to give their children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants good inſtructions in their health, but then to do this eſpecially, when they lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their bed of ſickneſſe, when they have the ſentence of Death in them, when they are ready to depart out of this world, the beſt Legacies they can then give them are godly admonitions. For the words of a dying friend, like thoſe of our <hi>Martyred
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170350:31"/>Soveraign)</hi> live with us till our death, they are as goades, and as nailes faſtned by the maſters of <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> every ſillable ſeemetha ſentence to us, their words make a deep impreſſion in our minds and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, when therefore ye are going the way of all the earth, do as religious <hi>Ioſhua</hi> then did, call for your families, and charge them to perſevere in pious duties, to fear the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to ſerve him in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and truth: Charge them alſo as a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>David</hi> charged his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> to <hi>know the God of their Fathers, &amp; to ſerve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind.</hi> And after your benediction, give them St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s valediction, <hi>Finally</hi> (as he took leave of his <hi>Corinthians) Farewell, be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi> Or let our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be your patterne and enſample, who ceaſed not to inſtruct his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> till he was taken from them <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>when he had ſpoken theſe things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things,</hi> that is, laſtly when he had bleſſed them, ſo we read <hi>Luke</hi> 24.50, 51. <hi>he lift up his hands, and bleſſed them. And it came to paſſe while he bleſſed them, he was parted from them, and carried up into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170350:32"/>Thus <hi>Iacob,</hi> when he was a dying, bleſſed both the ſons of <hi>Ioſeph, Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeth, Geneſ.</hi> 48.16. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.21. Nor did he bleſſe them only, but alſo all the twelve tribes of <hi>Iſrael, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, according to his bleſsing he bleſſed them, Gen.</hi> 49.28. This was alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s cuſtome to cloſe all his Epiſtles with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction. And thus likewiſe the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is concluded. The <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> endeth with a threatned <hi>curſe, leſt I come and ſmite the earth with a curſe</hi> Mal. 4. <hi>ult.</hi> But the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> endeth with a bleſſing, <hi>The Grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with you all.</hi> Revel. 22. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this may ſerve to teach the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> not to diſmiſſe the aſſembly without a bleſſing, and the aſſembly to have ſo much patience as to tarry till it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. It may indeed teach all ſorts of people, <hi>Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Subject, Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity,</hi> not to part company at any time without <hi>a Dominus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>obiſcum</hi> on both ſides, <hi>the Lord be with you, the Lord proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you, we wiſh you good luck, in the name of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Herein indeed lies the difference between our bleſſings and our Saviours, Our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions are in the Optative mood, we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170350:32"/>do but wiſh them, but our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions (as that <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> hath an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in his prayer for a bleſſing upon the <hi>Treaty</hi>) our <hi>Saviours</hi> benedictions, I ſay, are Imperative, he commands them, he aſcended not till he had done this, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>When he had ſpoken theſe things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo I paſſe from the ſecond part of the Text, the Time of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s aſcenſion, to the third, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> from whence he aſcended, which was that part of Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> next to <hi>Bethany,</hi> as will appear by comparing <hi>Act.</hi> 1.12. with <hi>Luke</hi> 24.50. So that here we have three ſteps, Firſt he aſcended from a <hi>Mountain,</hi> Secondly from Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> Thirdly from that part of it next <hi>Bethany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, he aſcended from a <hi>Mountaine,</hi> And why ſo? He ſtileth himſelfe the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>valleys, Cant.</hi> 2.1. Why then did he not aſcend from the valley of <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> he ſhall from heaven come thither at the day of judgment, <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.12. Why then did he not from thence go into heaven? Was it to ſhew that he is the God of the mountaines only, and not alſo of the valleyes: or was it that he might be a little neerer to heaven, and by this meanes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170350:33"/>ſhorten his way thither? No ſuch matter, but he aſcended from a mountaine, chiefly for two reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to teach us, ſaith <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rinus,</hi> that we ſhould alway uſe meanes, where they may poſſibly be had. He could at all times have, walked upon the water, but he would not, when he came where ſhipping was, he went aboard. He could have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the multitude without food, he could have taken, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>way their Hunger with a word, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, be ye filled; but he would not, he fed them at one time with ſeven, at another time with five loves, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing meanes, though inconſiderable and weak. He could have cured him that was born blind with an <hi>Epphatha</hi> be opened, but he would not, he bade him go to the pool of <hi>Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and waſh. All to teach us that we ſhould not neglect meanes, and look for miracles. When we are ſick we muſt ſend for the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> not look for Gods help without his.</p>
                  <p>When an houſe is fired, we muſt caſt water on it, not hope that God will quench it by a ſhower. When perjured rebels have uſurped the Crown, to recover this out of their hands, we muſt put on, not only the armour of God, but the armour
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170350:33"/>of man too, we muſt not only have the ſword of the <hi>Lord,</hi> but of <hi>Gideon.</hi> For to look for help from God, and uſe no meanes, is not to truſt in God, but even to tempt him. And that we might avoid this, our <hi>Saviour</hi> would not aſcend from a Valley, but rather choſe the mediation of a Mountaine.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, he aſcended from a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, to teach us that as mountaines raiſe and elevate our bodies, ſo they ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe elevate our ſouls, they ſhould put us in mind of heaven and things above. VVhen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever therefore we go up an hill, we ſhould be thinking upon <hi>God</hi>'s hill, and we ſhould fix our cogitations upon him, who was tranſfigured upon a mountaine, mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> crucified upon a mountain, mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> and aſcended from a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, even from mount <hi>Olivet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And why from this mountaine of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? The reaſons ſeem to be chiefly two, Firſt, that as upon this mountain he ſhewed himſelf to be a frail <hi>man,</hi> ſo he might there ſhew himſelf to be the mighty <hi>God</hi> too, as he manifeſted the weakneſſe of his <hi>humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> upon this mountaine, by his agony and bloody ſweat, and by his groveling on the ground; ſo he might likewiſe manifeſt the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170350:34"/>power of his <hi>Divinity</hi> upon the ſame moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: by his glorious aſcenſion from thence into heaven, Secondly, the <hi>Olive-tree</hi> is the emblem and hierogliphick of Peace; good reaſon then that our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſhould aſcend from mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> ſeeing he is our <hi>Peace,</hi> the very <hi>Prince of peace,</hi> this was the Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that he bequeathed to his deareſt friends, <hi>Peace I leave with you, my Peace I give unto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as <hi>Christ</hi> aſcended from a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and from mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> ſo laſtly from that part of it next <hi>Bethany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Bethany,</hi> by interpetation, is the houſe of affliction, and fom <hi>Bethany</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> went unto his Paſſion, for juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his apprehenſion, <hi>he was in Bethany in the houſe of Simon the Leper, Math.</hi> 26.6. he went from the ſame place to his Croſs, and his <hi>Crown.</hi> And ſo muſt we, we muſt not think to go <hi>a delicjis ad delicias,</hi> as <hi>St. Jerome</hi> ſpeaketh, from the jollity of this world to the joyes of heaven, no, if hereafter we will have good, we muſt here have evill things. <hi>Per anguſta ad auguſta,</hi> through heavineſs to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Per varios caſus, per tot diſcrimina rerum,</hi> through many tribulations we muſt enter into the Kingdome of God, <hi>Acts.</hi> 14.22.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170350:34"/>
                  <p>Lift up therefore the hands which hang downe, and the feeble knees. For what if thou art impriſoned, and, as it were buried alive in thy bed of languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? What if ſickneſſe have taken ſuch hold upon thee, that thou are not able to look up? What if thou art feeble and ſore ſmitten, ſo that all the night thou waſheſt thy bed, and watereſt thy couch with thy teares? Why, yet let this conſideration be inſtead of an handkerchief to wipe thine eyes; conſider that thy <hi>Saviour</hi> (and thy <hi>Martyred Soveraign</hi>) went from <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thany</hi> to <hi>Bethel,</hi> from the houſe of affliction to their <hi>Fathers</hi> houſe, and if thou haſt faith and patience, thou ſhalt do ſo too, thy bed of ſickneſſe, or if it be thy ſcaffold, or thy gibbet; this ſhall be the ſame to thee that <hi>Bethany</hi> was to thy <hi>Saviour;</hi> thou ſhalt from thence be tranſlated and exalted into <hi>Abraham's</hi> boſom, thy light affliction, which is but for a moment, ſhall work for thee a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I paſſe from the third part of the Text, the <hi>Place,</hi> from whence <hi>Christ</hi> aſcended, to the fourth, <hi>Quo,</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he aſcended, which was <hi>Heaven,</hi> he was taken up thither.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170350:35"/>
                  <p>In the firſt chapter of <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, we read of four living Creatures, and every of theſe creatures had four faces, the face of a man, the face of an Ox, the face of a Lion, &amp; the face of an Eagle. Whereunto Expoſitors reſemble four actions of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> his <hi>Nativity,</hi> his <hi>Pasſion,</hi> his <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> his <hi>Aſcenſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At his <hi>Nativity,</hi> he was like a man, more than like, he was a man indeed, man of the ſubſtance of his mother, born in the world. At his <hi>Pasſion,</hi> he was like an Ox, offered up for us in ſacrifice upon the Altar of the <hi>Croſſe.</hi> At his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> he was like a <hi>Lion,</hi> even a lion of the tribe of Judah, he brake the bonds of death; becauſe it was not poſſible that he ſhould be holden of it. At his <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> he was like an <hi>Eagle,</hi> he ſoared up into heaven.</p>
                  <p>Into heaven? But did he go no higher? St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he <hi>aſcended farre above all heavens, Eph.</hi> 4.10 But for anſwer to this, we muſt obſerve that the <hi>Scripture</hi> maketh mention of a threefold heaven. Firſt the <hi>Air</hi> is called <hi>Heaven, he commanded the cloud above, and opened the doores of heaven, Pſa.</hi> 78.23. Secondly, the celeſtial orbes and ſpheres, are heaven, the Sun, Moon, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170350:35"/>Starrs are called <hi>Exercitus coeli; the host of heaven, Dent.</hi> 4.19. Thirdly and laſtly, the place of bliffe is heaven; <hi>the Lord hath prepared his ſeat in heaven, Pſal.</hi> 103.19. which diſtinction of heaven, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to allude unto, when he ſaith, that he <hi>was caught up into the third heaven,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. Now where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith that <hi>Christ</hi> aſcended far above all heavens, we are to underſtand it of the <hi>Orbes Celeſtial,</hi> he aſcended above the Orbes Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, above all viſible and materiall heavens.</p>
                  <p>But here then perhaps that of the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> may be objected, in the firſt book, <hi>De coelo,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, without, or above heaven there is no place, now it is eſſential to every body to be in ſome place or other, <hi>quod nuſquam eſt, non omnino eſt,</hi> if <hi>Chriſts</hi> body therefore be in no place, it will be ſo far from being every where (as <hi>Lutherans</hi> would have it) that it will ceaſe to be at all. To which I anſwer, that to ſpeak phyſically and ſtrictly, there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no place above the viſible heavens; But though there be not <hi>Locus,</hi> yet there is <hi>Ubi,</hi> though there be no place, yet there is a certaine ſpace, (as I may ſo ſpeak) and it is ſufficient for a body glorified to be in ſuch a ſpace, which our <hi>Saviour</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170350:36"/>calleth a place, <hi>I go to prepare a place for you. Ioh,</hi> 14.2.</p>
                  <p>And this was indeed the chief reaſon why he aſcended into heaven. <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin ſhut him out both of the earthly and the heavenly <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> there was no place for him in <hi>Eden,</hi> nor for his poſterity in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But the doores of heaven were opened upon <hi>Holy-Thursday,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and trampled upon death by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, he did open the kingdome of heaven by his aſcenſion. Not as if heaven were ſo faſt ſhut before, that none could enter in, no not in ſoul, till <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended thither in body, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> might have ſome kind of ground for their <hi>Limbus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,</hi> if this were ſo. That cannot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be the meaning of it; there were glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manſions prepared for us from the foundation of the world, as it is <hi>Math.</hi> 25.34. But though places of glory were from the beginning prepared for us, yet the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and the perfect preparation was made by <hi>Chriſts</hi> aſcenſion.</p>
                  <p>And ſeeing our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded corporally into heaven, this earneſt may aſcertaine us of our aſcenſion, our <hi>Head</hi> being aſcended, we ſhall alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend that are his <hi>Members.</hi> It may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170350:36"/>perhaps that fleſh and blood cannot inherit incorruption. I anſwer, it is true that our bodies, as they are now, are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of going to heaven; they muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be crumbled to very duſt and aſhes, and new moulded by him that made them at the firſt, before ever they can be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into that holy place. And as our bodies muſt be refined, ſo likewiſe muſt our ſouls. Heaven is a City of pure Gold, no unclean thing muſt come into it. We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay aſide every weight, and the ſinnes that do ſo eaſily depreſſe us; <hi>David</hi> could not go with <hi>Saul's</hi> armour, nor can we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to heaven with the weapons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe. If then we will aſcend thither at our death, we muſt begin our aſcenſion in this life, if we hope to go to heaven, when we take our farewell of the earth, then while we are here on earth, our converſation muſt be in heaven. For <hi>anima magis eſt ubi amat, quàm ubi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimat,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> the Soul is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where it loveth, than where it liveth; If therefore we love the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> let our affection be with him, where our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly treaſure is, there let our hearts be alſo, where the Load-ſtone is, that way let the Iron tend, where the carcaſe is,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170350:37"/>thither let the Eagles reſort; by religious meditations, and by aſſiduous ſupplications let us aſcend unto that place whither our bleſſed Lord and Maſter is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> would rather have been in <hi>hell</hi> with Chriſt, than be in <hi>heaven</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him. How then ſhould our hearts be inflamed with love of heaven, now we are ſure that our <hi>Saviour</hi> is aſcended thither? How ſhould we contemn, though not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the world, uſe it, I mean as though we uſed it not? Seing <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath left it, we ſhould ſtrive to leave it too, dying dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, though not in deed, yet in deſire, having a deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with <hi>Christ,</hi> our ſoules muſt be athirſt for him, our fleſh alſo muſt long after him, with an <hi>How long Lord Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> when ſhall we come unto thee? And ſo I paſſe from the fourth part of the Text, the <hi>Place</hi> whither <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended, to the fifth, <hi>Quomodo,</hi> the <hi>Manner</hi> of his aſcenſion, ſet down here two wayes, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the <hi>Poſitive</hi> part of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>he was taken up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Taken up,</hi> why ſo? Did he not go up of himſelf? <hi>Lazarus</hi> was taken up, <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by Angels into heaven.</hi> And theſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170350:37"/>up <hi>Elijah</hi> too, the charet and horſes of fire were holy <hi>Angels, the Charets of God,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, are twenty thouſand, even thouſands of Angels, Pſal.</hi> 68.17. But though they were carried up, yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> went up of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in his aſcenſion; of all circumſtances, <hi>Quibus auxiliis,</hi> came not in, <hi>Christ</hi> went up of himſelf, he aſcended by his own power. Why then doth our Text ſay that he was taken up? as if he had been ſome way aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his aſcneſion up to heaven?</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, the Text ſaith that he was taken up for this reaſon, to ſignifie and ſhew his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his <hi>Fathers</hi> Will, for otherwiſe he might have aſcended upon the very day of his reſurrection, every glorified body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that agility and lightneſſe, <hi>ut ubicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que volet eſſe anima, ibi ſtatim erit corpus,</hi> whereſoever the ſoul would be, there is the body ſtraight. But though <hi>Chriſt</hi> might have aſcended ſooner, yet he would not till his heavenly <hi>Father</hi> ſaw good, for which reaſon the Text ſaith that <hi>he was taken up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this may teach us not to lay violent hands upon our ſelves, thinking to get ſo much the ſooner into heaven. If we be in poverty, or ſickneſſe, in impriſonment, or baniſhment, yet we muſt not make away with our ſelves, nor muſt we repine or be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170350:38"/>impatient that we are let into heaven no ſooner, that we have ſo long ſought for death, and cannot find it, but we muſt tarry the Lords leiſure, we muſt not be our own carvers, all the dayes of our appointed time we muſt wait, till our change come; following the example of our bleſſed Lord and Maſter, who ſubmitted himſelf in all things to the Will of his heavenly Father, and therefore he aſcended not when firſt he might, but when his <hi>Father</hi> would have him <hi>taken up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo ye have the manner of his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>poſitively</hi> ſet down. I now proceed to the <hi>Expoſitive</hi> part of it, in theſe words, <hi>A cloud received him out of their ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He maketh the clouds his charet,</hi> Pſal. 104.3. Not that this cloud did any way help to lift him up, but he uſed the Miniſtery of a cloud chiefly for two reaſons. Firſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and manifeſt his <hi>Divinity. Angels</hi> miniſter to men, but <hi>clouds</hi> after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, miniſter to <hi>God</hi> only. And the <hi>clouds</hi> were ſervants to our <hi>Saviour</hi> more than once. At his transfiguration, when he gave his Diſciples a glimpſe of his <hi>Divinity, a bright cloud overſhaddowed him.</hi> Mat. 17.5. So likewiſe at the day of Judgement clouds ſhall miniſter unto him, <hi>He ſhall come in the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170350:38"/>clouds of heaven with power and great glory,</hi> Mat. 24.30. As therefore in <hi>Herauldry</hi> it argueth a good familie, when a man hath clouds in his Coat of Arms; ſo in this place, it is an argument of Chriſts divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that he hath a <hi>cloud</hi> to ſerve him, his bearing is all <hi>Nebuly, a cloud received him out of their ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A cloud,</hi> I ſay, <hi>received him.</hi> His body then is not every where, as <hi>Lutherans</hi> would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us; that which is contained in any thing, muſt needs be leſs than the thing which doth contain it. The body of Chriſt was once contained in a virgins womb, and here a <hi>cloud</hi> received <hi>him.</hi> And it received him out of ſight, which maketh good that ſaying of our <hi>Saviour</hi> to his Diſciples, <hi>A little while and ye ſhall not ſee me,</hi> Joh. 16.16. And that was indeed a ſecond uſe of this cloud, namely, to take off the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> from curioſity. Had it been neceſſary for them to know any further what became of their departing <hi>Saviour,</hi> this cloud, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him out of ſight, had not been thus interpoſed. But to ſhew them that they had corporally ſeen him long enough, and that hereafter they were not to ſee, but to believe, to exerciſe their faith, and to abate their <hi>curioſity, a cloud received him out of their ſight:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170350:39"/>
                  <p>God alloweth us not to pry inquiſitively into hidden myſteries. When the <hi>Lord</hi> deſcended upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> there was a thick cloud upon the mountain, to keep the people from gazing, leſt they periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. which was alſo one main uſe of this <hi>Cloud</hi> at <hi>Christ's</hi> aſcenſion, that his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> namely, might not gaze after him as he aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                  <p>We muſt walk by faith now, and not by ſight. For the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> hath a two-fold eye, the eye of faith, and the eye of glory. As <hi>Jacob,</hi> therefore marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firſt of all blear-eyed <hi>Leah,</hi> before he could obtain beautifull <hi>Rachel;</hi> ſo we muſt fee <hi>Chriſt</hi> on earth, with the tender eye of faith, before we can in Heaven have the fruition of his glorious God-head. For he is not ſo gone up into heaven, but that we may ſee him ſtill on earth: We may ſee him in his Word, we do not only hear of him there, but we even ſee him. When we ſtedfaſtly believe what we hear out of Gods Word, we fare not only as if it were related in our ears, but indeed verily acted before our eyes. And as we may ſee Chriſt in his <hi>Word,</hi> ſo we may alſo ſee him in his <hi>Sacraments,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170350:39"/>in the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> of his holy <hi>Supper,</hi> and yet even in that <hi>Sacrament</hi> he is under a <hi>Cloud</hi> too. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> indeed would fain diſpel and diſſipate this cloud, telling us, that he is corporally and viſibly there preſent, handle and ſee, they bid us, that it is even he himſelf. But this Herefie is confuted ſo at large; that a bare denial of it might now ſuffice: yet let me me urge againſt it one Text of Scripture, which is <hi>Mark</hi> 7.19. Where our Saviour ſaith, that <hi>Whatſoever entreth into the belly, goeth out into the draught.</hi> And what horrid blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy were it to ſay thus of <hi>Christs</hi> bleſſed body? We can eat <hi>Chriſt</hi> with no other mouth, but that of our faith; not can we ſee him here with the eye of our fleſh, but of our faith. And faith indeed is the moſt perfect perſpective, when all is done. As <hi>Abraham</hi> therefore ſaid to the damned rich glutton in another caſe, If they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> neither would they believe, though one ſhould come unto them from the dead. So he that believeth not the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> the Hiſtory of our Saviour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> would not believe that he were the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> though he ſhould ſee him face to face; he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not St. <hi>Luke</hi> relating the manner of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170350:40"/>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s aſcenſion, would not have believed his own eyes, though they had been wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his Aſſumption, though he had been preſent upon Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was taken up into heaven, <hi>When a cloud received him out of the Apoſtles</hi> ſight. We muſt endeavour therefore by faith to ſee Chriſt in his Word and Sacraments; the exerciſing of this faith was one principal reaſon, <hi>Why a cloud received him out of their ſight.</hi> And as our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſo our <hi>martyred Soveraign</hi> was taken up in a cloud too. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was <hi>Royal Majeſty</hi> ſo diſguiſed, or under ſo thick a <hi>cloud,</hi> but that <hi>cloud</hi> was a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <hi>Charet,</hi> wherein he was carried up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven: the rebellious fools that murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, accounted his life madneſs, and his end to be without honour: But yet honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his <hi>Saints.</hi> And in ſpight of all their villany, <hi>He is among the children of God, and his portion is with the Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo I paſs from the fifth part of the Text, the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's aſcenſion,</hi> to the ſixth and laſt, which are <hi>Teſtes,</hi> the <hi>Spectators</hi> or <hi>Witneſses</hi> of his aſcenſion, which were the eleven <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>while they beheld.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The aſcenſion of our <hi>Saviour</hi> was not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170350:40"/>ſeen of all the people, but of certain <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes choſen before of God, even of thoſe who did eat and drink with him after he roſe from the dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The adulterous generation of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſought altogether after ſignes; Shew us a ſign from heaven, come down from the Croſs, that we may ſee and believe. But our <hi>Saviour</hi> would be the object of mens faith, not of their ſenſe: Now ſaith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God; if the <hi>Jewes</hi> therefore will believe <hi>Chriſt's</hi> aſcenſion, they have the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> let them hear them, they were eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his Majeſty, <hi>He was taken up while they beheld.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>While <hi>They,</hi> it is not while <hi>He</hi> beheld, for <hi>unus Teſtis nullus teſtis,</hi> one witneſs is as good as none: <hi>In the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall every word be establiſhed,</hi> Mat. 18.16. And yet <hi>Pluris eſt oculatus teſtis u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, quam auriti decem,</hi> one eye-witneſs is more worth than ten of thoſe that go by hear-ſay. Had the Apoſtle told the <hi>Jews</hi> that they heard <hi>Christ</hi> ſay, he would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend at one time or another, O how ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous had they been! who would have given any heed to this report? That the <hi>Apostles</hi> therefore might preach no uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170350:41"/>Tradition, they were made ſpectators of Chriſt's aſcenſion; he aſcended in their preſence, <hi>He was taken up while they beheld.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behold him then they did, and indeed how could they chuſe but behold him? It was one of St. <hi>Austins</hi> three wiſhes, that he might ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the fleſh. And this was the wiſh of many others long before <hi>St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> time, many <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Kings deſired to ſee thoſe things, and could not ſee them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Angels</hi> ſeemed to reprove the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> for their ſtedfaſt looking after their Maſter, <hi>Ye men of</hi> Galilee, <hi>why ſtand ye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing up into heaven?</hi> Acts 1.11. where the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> methinks, might have expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulated with the <hi>Angels</hi> after this manner, Thrice bleſſed <hi>Spirits,</hi> why ſhould ye ask us this? <hi>Ubi amor, ibi oculus;</hi> we could even look out our eyes, yet not be ſatisfied with ſeeing; our eyes naturally turn upward, and ſhall they not do ſo, eſpecially to ſee ſuch an object as this is? Think it not ſtrange that we are ſo loth to loſe this ſight, it being that which ye your ſelves ſo much deſire to ſee. But the Angels reproved not the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> love, it was their curioſity which they reproved; they would have them take off their eyes, and pry no further, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as one day they ſhould ſee that ſame
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170350:41"/>very ſight again; and not only they, but alſo all of us ſhall ſee him, <hi>we know that our Redeemer liveth, and that we ſhall ſee him not with other, but with theſe ſame eyes.</hi> Which may teach us to take heed of wanton luſtful eyes, to make a Covenant with our eyes, not to look laſciviouſly on a woman, to turn away our eyes, leſt they behold vanity. For how will ever thoſe eyes dare to look on our <hi>Chaſt Saviour,</hi> which have been <hi>eyes full of adultery?</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
                  <p>To conclude all therefore in one word, let us circumciſe, not only our hearts, but even our eyes too, let theſe often ſee themſelves here in their own tears, and they ſhall have the honour hereafter to ſee <hi>Chriſt, they ſhall behold his preſence in Righteouſneſs, and we ſhall be ſatisfied with it,</hi> ſatisfied for pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <hi>for in his preſence is fulneſs of Joy;</hi> and ſatisfied for perpetuity, <hi>For at his right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Of which God in his appointed time vouchſafe to make us all partakers, for the interceſſion ſake of his dear Son, who now ſitteth at his right hand.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170350:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170350:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ISRAEL AND England <hi>PARALELLED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Sermon PREACHED Before the Honourable <hi>Society</hi> OF <hi>GRAYES-INN,</hi> Upon <hi>Sunday, Apr.</hi> 16. 1649.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:44"/>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170350:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>ISRAEL AND England <hi>PARALELLED.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>AMOS 3.2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>You only have I known of all the Families of the earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THE firſt verſe plainly ſheweth us who are meant here in the ſecond, even the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the whole family that came out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Neither are theſe laſt words to be counted a <hi>Tautologie,</hi> for after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170350:45"/>of the ten Tribes from the houſe of <hi>David, Iſrael</hi> was one Kingdom, <hi>Judah</hi> was another, wee'l go no farther back to clear it, than the title of this Prophecy, which runneth thus, The words of <hi>Amos,</hi> which he ſaw concerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (that is, <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi>) in the dayes of <hi>Uzziah,</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> and in the dayes of <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Now though but ten Tribes were revolted from <hi>David,</hi> yet all twelve Tribes were revolted from <hi>God,</hi> the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the whole family that came out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Ceſar</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Brutus,</hi> will Gods children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> be ſuch Rebels? <hi>Ingratum ſi dixeris,</hi> &amp;c. ſo an heathen could conclude, that ingratitude was the abſtract and abridgement of all ſin, as if it had been <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the great offence. And even unreaſonable creatures will not be guilty of unthankfulneſs; <hi>The Ox knoweth his owner,</hi> he will not gore him, and ye remember the gratitude of that <hi>Lion</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtory, nay, (to go one ſtep lower) <hi>Non ingratus ager,</hi> that which hath not ſo much as ſenſe, is not unthankfull, the <hi>Earth</hi> doth not entomb, or alway keep the ſeed cloſe Priſoner, but moſt thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170350:45"/>returneth it to the ſower with increaſe. Yet the land of <hi>Iſrael</hi> proved a barren <hi>Common,</hi> whereon nothing but weeds, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but unthankfullneſs would grow; where as the Inhabitants ſhould not ſo much as have rendred evil for evil, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually rewarded God evil for good: He did not faſter multiply his benefits upon them, than they did their tranſgreſſions and rebellions againſt him. <hi>And ſhall I not viſit for theſe things,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Lord, ſhall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> Yes, ſeing fair means will do no good on them, I will try what foul will do, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they have forſaken me, and not walked in my judgements; having broken my Statutes, and not kept my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I will therefore viſit their offences with the rod, and their ſins with ſcourges. <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which words, any one will ſay, there are two general Parts. <hi>Commemoratio beneficij,</hi> the rehearſing or calling to mind of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer benefit, <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth,</hi> and <hi>Comminatio ſupplicij,</hi> the threatning of a future judgement,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170350:46"/>
                     <hi>therefore</hi> I <hi>will puniſh you for all your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But before I come to handle the parts in their order, it will not be amiſs to premiſe ſome brief explication of the words.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then, you only have I <hi>known.</hi> I ever thought that God had been <hi>Omniſcient;</hi> but our Text ſeemeth to deny it, In <hi>Jury</hi> is God <hi>known,</hi> and God knoweth none but thoſe of <hi>Jury, you only have</hi> I <hi>known of all the families of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But we muſt obſerve that this word <hi>Know,</hi> hath divers acceptions in the Holy Scripture. I ſhall inſtance but in three.</p>
                  <p>Firſt to <hi>know,</hi> is to behold, to diſcern and overlook. Thus God knoweth the whole world, and all that therein is, thus he knoweth all the fowls upon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and the wild beaſts of the field are in his ſight: thus there is not a word in our tongue, nor a thought in our heart, but he knoweth it long before, even long before we ſpake or thought it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly to <hi>know,</hi> is to approve, or to allow of. Thus the Lord knoweth the way of the righteous, that is, he appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170350:46"/>of it. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> As for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly (ſuch as are the Reformers of our age) it is not ſo with them, our <hi>Saviours</hi> word to theſe will be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I never knew you, that is, I never liked your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.27.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, to <hi>know,</hi> is to bleſs, to pity, or ſhew mercy to. And the phraſe ſeemeth to be borrowed from a cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, who ſeldome ſhew any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to perſons that they know, <hi>Ignoti nulla cupido,</hi> a ſtranger can ſcarce get any thing of them, but ill words; <hi>David's</hi> ſervants were ſtrangers to <hi>Nabal,</hi> and therefore the Churl would give them nothing; Shall I take my bread, ſaith he, and my water, and my fleſh, and give it unto men whom I know not whence they be? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.11. No; few or none will relieve any, but only ſuch as are well known to them. And to this cuſtome God ſeemeth to allude here in our Text, <hi>You only have I known,</hi> that is, I have bleſſed you only, on you have I multiplied my favours and loving kindneſſes, on you only, or at leaſt chiefly of all the families of the earth.</p>
                  <p>And in this ſenſe is the word <hi>Known</hi> uſed, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 31.7. I will be glad, and rejoyce
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170350:47"/>in thy mercy, for thou haſt conſidered my trouble, <hi>&amp; cognoviſti,</hi> and haſt <hi>known</hi> my ſoul in adverſities. Thou haſt <hi>known,</hi> that is, thou haſt pitied, thou haſt had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on my ſoul, <hi>cognoſcere eſt miſerari,</hi> ſo <hi>Agellius</hi> expoundeth the place. And <hi>Solomon</hi> hath a paſſage that may be referred to this purpoſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.10. A righteous man regardeth the life of his beaſts, ſo we read it, <hi>Novit juſtus, &amp;c.</hi> ſo it is in the Latin verſion; but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſo it is in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> a righteous man hath mercy on the ſouls of his beaſts. If now we put the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> together, we ſhall find that to <hi>Know,</hi> is to <hi>ſhew mercy to.</hi> In which ſenſe the word is likewiſe uſed here in our Text, <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if the <hi>Commemoration</hi> muſt be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued, why followeth there a <hi>Commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> becauſe God hath been ſo good to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is it therefore that he threatneth them? This indeed ſeemeth ſomewhat ſtrange. But if we take middle, and both ends, theſe things will ſoon be reconciled; <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth,</hi> we muſt hair here a while, <hi>Deſunt nonnulla,</hi> there ſeemeth to be ſomewhat wanting, but it cometh in at the end of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170350:47"/>verſe, we may paraphraſe therefore upon the <hi>Text</hi> after this manner, the words are, in effect, as if Almighty <hi>God</hi> ſhould have ſaid, <hi>I have nouriſhed, and brought up chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and (like our pretended <hi>Parliament</hi>) <hi>They have rebelled againſt me, deſtruction and unhappineſs is in their way, and the way of peace have they not known.</hi> I have known them, but they have not known me, <hi>The Ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters crib, but Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſider.</hi> I threaten them, not for the <hi>good</hi> I have done to them, but for the notorious <hi>evil</hi> they have done to me; <hi>You on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have I known of all the families of the earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Idcirco,</hi> therefore. Sin is the <hi>Cauſa im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſiva,</hi> that which moveth, and as it were, compelleth almighty God to puniſh. The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> putteth the Queſtion, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39. wherefore doth a living man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain? and he giveth an anſwer to it before the verſe be out, a man for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſins, that is, a man is puniſhed for his ſins; and therefore one old tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on readeth it thus,, let him murmur at his own ſins, theſe, theſe are the only cauſe of all his ſufferings, <hi>Idcirco, Therefore,</hi> Therefore I. <hi>Shall there be evil in the City,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170350:48"/>and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> Amos 3.6. <hi>Siracides</hi> telleth us indeed of <hi>Spirits</hi> that are created for vengeance, and theſe evil ſpirits many times lay on ſore ſtrokes, but they have <hi>Gods</hi> commiſſion, at leaſt permiſſion for what they do; they do this to pacifie the wrath of him that made them, <hi>Eecleſ.</hi> 39.28. As all puniſhment is for <hi>ſin,</hi> ſo it is from <hi>God.</hi> But how can this conſiſt with Gods goodneſs? yes, the very next particle will ſhew us, for he ſpeaketh not in the <hi>preſent,</hi> but in the <hi>future</hi> tenſe, <hi>I will,</hi> he giveth <hi>Iſrael</hi> warning of his intention, before he proceedeth to execution, that if they had any grace, they might repent, and ſo prevent the Judgement threatned; And he threatneth them but after a mild and gentle manner, he threatneth, not to plague and conſume them, but only to puniſh and correct them, <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo much for the connexion and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the words. It is high time now to come nearer to the parts. I begin therefore with the firſt, which is <hi>Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io beneficii,</hi> the rehearſing of a former benefit, in theſe words, <hi>You only have I known
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170350:48"/>of all the families of the earth.</hi> And that we may know how well God dealt with the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we may obſerve that he beſtowed upon them two ſorts of bleſſings, <hi>Privative</hi> and <hi>Poſitive</hi> ones. I begin with the firſt, Gods <hi>Privative</hi> bleſſings.</p>
                  <p>The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were for a long time bound <hi>Apprentices</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they were grievouſly oppreſſed by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his <hi>Task-maſters,</hi> who compelled them, not only to make <hi>brick,</hi> but it ſhould ſeem by the ſtory, they would have them make <hi>ſtraw</hi> too. From which intolerable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, God ſet them free at laſt, he eaſed their ſhoulders from the burthen, and their hands were delivered from making of pots. He brought forth his people with joy, and his choſen with gladneſs, and gave them the lands of the heathen, and they took the labours of the people in poſſeſſion. As for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, they were overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the red ſea, they ſunk down to the bottom as a ſtone. After this God made good his word to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> not ſuffering a man to ſtand before him all the dayes of his life. And what ſhall I more ſay? for the time would fail me to tell of <hi>Gideon,</hi> and of <hi>Barach,</hi> and of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and of <hi>Jeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thah,</hi> and of <hi>David,</hi> what marvellous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170350:49"/>God wrought for his people, diſcomfiting their enemies both by theſe <hi>Worthies,</hi> and by other <hi>Champions;</hi> the Sun, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. is compared to a ſtrong champion; and rather than <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be worſted, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible champions ſhall fight for them, the Sun ſhall ſtand ſtill in the midſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; the Starrs in their courſes ſhall fight againſt <hi>Siſera;</hi> ſo mightily did God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his people, even the ſons of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as God beſtowed many <hi>Privative</hi> bleſſings upon Iſrael, ſo many <hi>Poſitive</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings too: And theſe were of two ſorts, <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual.</hi> I begin with the firſt, Gods <hi>Temporal</hi> bleſſings, which are recorded, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>My beloved hath a vineyard in a very fruitful hill. And he fenced it and gathered out the stones thereof, and plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with the choiceſt vine, and built a Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the midſt of it, and alſo made a wine-preſs therein.</hi> It will be no digreſſion to touch briefly upon each of theſe particulars, the <hi>Situation</hi> of the vineyard meeteth us Firſt, which was <hi>in clivo uberrimo,</hi> in a very fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hill. The hill of <hi>Sion</hi> was a fair place, and the joy of the whole earth, <hi>Iſrael</hi> had a goodly heritage, <hi>Canaan</hi> flowed with milk and honey. And the fruitfulneſſe of it
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170350:49"/>is deſcribed at large. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8, 7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>Next to the fruitfull ſituation, Gods <hi>Fencing</hi> of the vineyard followeth. He made a <hi>Wall</hi> about it, ſaith the Margin, and <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. it is ſaid, he <hi>hedged</hi> it round about: Now an <hi>hedge</hi> ſerveth for two uſes, for <hi>diſtinction</hi> and for <hi>conſervation; Iſrael</hi> was hedged about both wayes; for <hi>diſtinction</hi> they had the <hi>Law,</hi> by this they were diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from other Nations, <hi>what Nation is there ſo great, ſaith Moſes, that hath ſtatutes and judgments ſo righteous, as all this Law which I ſet before you this day? Deut.</hi> 4.8. other Nations dwelt as it were in a <hi>Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an countrey,</hi> without a hedge, without a Law; but <hi>Iſrael</hi> was encloſ'd, &amp; hereby diſtinguiſh'd from all other people. God dealt not ſo well with any other Nation, neither had the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then knowledge of his Lawes. And as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had an hedge for <hi>distinction,</hi> ſo they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother hedge for <hi>conſervation,</hi> which was the providence of <hi>God,</hi> and the protection of his <hi>Angels, The hills,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> ſtand <hi>about Jeruſalem, even ſo standeth the Lord round about his people, from this time forth for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the next place, God gathered the <hi>ſtones</hi> out of his vineyard. VVhereby we are to underſtand the wicked Nations, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170350:50"/>to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 80.10. Thou haſt brought a vine out of Egypt, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puleras gentes,</hi> thou haſt caſt out the heathen, God gave away their land for an heritage, even for an heritage unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> his people; That is the next thing preſented to us, he planted it with the choiceſt <hi>vine,</hi> the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the Lord of hoſts was the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> were his pleaſant plant.</p>
                  <p>The next obſervable is Gods building of a <hi>Tower</hi> in his vineyard, and <hi>Turris, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas eſt ſacerdotalis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aretius, the Tower</hi> in Gods vineyard, is the office and authority of Gods Miniſters; for as <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> from a tower overlooking all the coaſt, give notice when any corporal enemies are approaching; ſo Gods <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are the <hi>watchmen</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> theſe give her warning of her ghoſtly enemies, ſo that neither the Boar of the wood can waſte her, nor yet the wild beaſts of the field devour her.</p>
                  <p>In the laſt place, God made a <hi>Wine-preſſe</hi> in his vineyard, whereby the juyce of good living was to be, as it were, preſſed out of the people. But to explain all this in three words. By the <hi>Fence,</hi> by the <hi>Tower</hi> by the <hi>Wine-preſſe,</hi> by all this care and coſt beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170350:50"/>upon the vineyard, there is ſignifyed Gods abundant love toward his people <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> ſo that he could not poſſibly do any thing elſe for them, having done more for them already than for all the world beſides, <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as God beſtowed upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Temporal,</hi> ſo alſo many <hi>Spiritual</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which are mentioned by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4, 5. where ſpeaking of the <hi>Iſraelities,</hi> he telleth us, that <hi>to them pertained the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the promiſes theirs were the Fathers and of them, as concerning the fleſh, Chriſt came.</hi> It will not be amiſſe likewiſe to examine briefly theſe particulars. And firſt to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the <hi>adoption,</hi> they were culled out of all nations to be Gods peculiar people, the quotations to this purpoſe are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I ſhall cite but only one, which is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. 1. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord that created thee, O Iacob, and he that formed thee,</hi> O <hi>Iſrael, fear not, for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name, thou art mine.</hi> Called thee by <hi>thy</hi> name? nay, I have called thee by my <hi>own</hi> name, ſo it is, 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 7.14. <hi>My people, which are called by my name.</hi> And <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.19. <hi>Thy City,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170350:51"/>the <hi>Prophet, and thy people are called by thy name,</hi> Whence we may obſerve that there was a twofold relation between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the relation of <hi>father</hi> and <hi>children,</hi> and of <hi>huſband</hi> and <hi>wife.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, they were related as <hi>father</hi> and <hi>children;</hi> Children bear their fathers name, God therefore calling <hi>Iſrael</hi> by his own name, this ſheweth that he was their <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> they his <hi>children.</hi> And the Prophet in their name teſtifieth as much, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. <hi>Doubtleſs thou,</hi> O <hi>Lord, art our father, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael acknowledge us not.</hi> Secondly God was related to <hi>Iſrael</hi> as an <hi>husband</hi> to his <hi>wife.</hi> The wife beareth her husbands name, it hath been thus ever ſince <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time, I am ſure, for God threatneth by him to ſend a ſword upon <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which ſhould make ſo great a ſlaughter and dearth of men, that ſeven women ſhould take hold of, or ſhould come a wooing to one man, ſaying, We will find our ſelves meat and cloathes, <hi>we will eat our own bread, and wear our own apparel, onely let us be called by thy name, Iſa.</hi> 4.1. Called by thy name? what do the women mean by this? why, the very next words will ſhew us, which are, <hi>to take away our reproach.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170350:51"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Barenneſs was a reproach among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> let us therefore be called by thy name to take away our reproach, that is, let us be married to thee, be thou our husband; God then calling the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by his own name, hereby ſheweth that he was, as it were, their <hi>Husband,</hi> they his <hi>wife.</hi> Almighty God was to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> both a <hi>father</hi> and an <hi>husband,</hi> as a <hi>father</hi> he nurtured them, as an <hi>husband</hi> he nouriſhed them; never did any one hare his own fleſh: God therefore muſt needs be loving unto <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> they being, as it were, bone of his bone, fleſh of his fleſh, they were his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> they were his <hi>Sons,</hi> to them pertained the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Glory,</hi> that is next, which glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſome would have to be a conſequent of their adoption, and indeed to be Gods own people was no ſmall dignity. But this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may be taken rather for the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God amongſt them, which he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted moſt eſpecially from off the <hi>Mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat</hi> that was upon the <hi>Ark,</hi> and therefore when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had loſt the <hi>Ark, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> his wife concluded that they had loſt the glory too, <hi>the glory,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Iſrael, for the ark of God is taken,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170350:52"/>
                  <p>And to <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo pertained the <hi>Covenants,</hi> for the Covenant that God made with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> runneth thus, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>I will eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee in their generations, for an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant to be a God unto thee, and unto thy ſeed after thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s next priviledge was the giving of the <hi>Law,</hi> that is, the <hi>Moral</hi> Law was given to them, and Almighty God himſelf was their <hi>Law-giver.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Promiſes</hi> were theirs too, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of long life here, and of eternal life hereafter, of the life that now is, and of that which is to come, <hi>To Abraham, and his ſeed were theſe promiſes made,</hi> Gal. 3.16.</p>
                  <p>Theirs alſo were the <hi>Fathers,</hi> the promiſes were made as well to their Fathers, as to them, according to that of St. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 3.25. <hi>Ye are the children of the Prophets, and of the Covenant, which God made with our fathers, ſaying unto Abraham, And in thy ſeed ſhall all the kindreds of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> In thy <hi>ſeed</hi> that is in <hi>Christ,</hi> who was the Iſraelites own <hi>Countryman,</hi> which is their laſt <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> recorded by the Apoſtle, <hi>Of whom, as concerning the fleſh, Christ came.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus ye have ſeen how God loaded the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170350:52"/>
                     <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with bleſſings, with <hi>Privative,</hi> and <hi>Poſitive,</hi> with <hi>Temporall</hi> and <hi>Spirituall, you only have</hi> I <hi>known of all the families of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> once ſaid, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. <hi>What doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in all his wayes, and to love him, and to ſerve the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But alas, the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is here forced to complain, that notwithſtanding all the coſt he had beſtowed upon his vineyard, when he expected grapes from it, it brought forth wild grapes, notwithſtanding thoſe many benefits he had beſtowed upon his people, they continually rewarded him evill for good, they thought not of his hand, nor of the day when he had delivered them from the hand of the enemy, how he wrought his miracles in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the field of <hi>Zoan,</hi> neither deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they the heathen, but learned their works, for they ſhed innocent blood, even the blood of their ſons and of their daughters, whom they offered unto the Idols of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the land was defiled with blood.</p>
                  <p>In generall termes, their ſins are ſet down, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.7. But they are more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170350:53"/>deſcribed in the third and fiſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> In the third chapter, ye may ſee their <hi>womens</hi> ſins, the <hi>Prophet</hi> bringeth you, as it were, into the <hi>Exchange,</hi> he ſheweth you the pride and vanity of their womens dreſſings, he giveth you ſuch an inventory of their toyes, as is able to make a very <hi>Cato</hi> change his countenance. In the fiſt chapter the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſheweth you their <hi>Mens</hi> ſins, after the catalogue of Gods benefits, he giveth you another catalogue of their ſins. At the ſeventh verſe he ſheweth you their oppreſſion and injuſtice, I <hi>looked for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but behold oppresſion, for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but behold a cry,</hi> At the eight verſe their encroaching coverouſneſſe, in <hi>joyning houſe to houſe, and field to field until there was no place, that they might be placed alone in the midſt of the earth,</hi> At the eleventh and twelft verſes, their drunkenneſs, and riot, in <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up early to follow ſtrong drink, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing untill night, till Wine enflame them, having the harp and the viol, the tabret and pipe, and wine in their feaſts.</hi> At the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth and nineteeth verſes, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſlighting of Gods word, in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this <hi>drawing iniquity with cords of vanity, and ſin as it were with a cart-rope; as</hi> who ſhould ſay, let him do his worſt, <hi>let
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170350:53"/>him make ſpeed and haſten his work, that we may ſee it; and let the counſel of the holy one of Iſrael draw nigh, and come that we may know it.</hi> ver. 20. Their hypocriſy, <hi>in calling evil good, and good evil, in patting darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, in putting bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter. Ver.</hi> 21. Their ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, <hi>Being wiſe in their own eyes, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in their own ſight,</hi> verſe 22. Their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valour, in that they were <hi>mighty to drink wine, and men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drink</hi> nverſe 23. Their bribery and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio, <hi>in justifying the wicked for reward, and in taking away the righteouſneſs of the righteous from him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſhall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord, ſhall not my ſoul be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on ſuch a Nation as this? yes, the wrath of <hi>God</hi> was kindr'd againſt his people, inſomuch that he abhorred his own inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: for three tranſgreſſions of <hi>Judah,</hi> &amp; for four, he reſolveth that he will not turn away the puniſhment thereof. And ſo I am fallen upon the ſecond part of the <hi>Text,</hi> which is, <hi>Comminatio ſupplicii,</hi> the threatning of a future puniſhment, therefore I will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you for all your iniquities. <hi>You only,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Ye have heard that God beſtowed upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> two ſorts of bleſſings, both which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170350:54"/>he threatneth to withdraw for their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſs. Firſt, his <hi>Privative</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, they muſt expect no more deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from him. He brought them forth out of the iron-furnace, even out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but they had ſo provoked him, that he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to bind them <hi>Apprentices</hi> there the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time. <hi>Apprentices?</hi> nay worſe, he threatneth to make <hi>ſlaves</hi> of them, ſo we read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. ult. <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſhall bring thee into</hi> Egypt <hi>again with ſhips, by the way whereof I ſpake unto thee, thou ſhalt ſee it no more again, and there ye ſhall ye beſold (offer your ſelves at leaſt) unto your enemies for bondmen and bondwomen, and no man ſhall buy you.</hi> God threatneth to ſell his people for nought, and to take no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for them. And whereas the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were wont to have the better of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they had ſo angred the Lord of hoſts, that he threatned to give their enemies the victory, ſo we read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.25. <hi>The Lord ſhall cauſe thee to be ſmitten before thine enemies, thou ſhalt go out one way againſt them, and ſhalt flee ſeven wayes before them, and ſhalt be removed into all the Kingdomes of the earth.</hi> And I am ſure they have been thus diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for many hundred years, they are ſtrangers in all Countries, they have loſt both their place and Nation.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170350:54"/>
                  <p>Secondly, God threatneth to withdraw his poſitive bleſſings from them. We have a plain Text for this, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.5, 6. <hi>I will tell you,</hi> ſaith <hi>God, What</hi> I <hi>will do to my vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyard,</hi> I <hi>will take away the hedge thereof, and it ſhall be eaten up, and</hi> I <hi>will break down the wall thereof, and it ſhall be troden down, and I will lay it waſte, it ſhall not be pruned, nor digged, but there ſhall come up briars and thorns; I will alſo command the clouds that they rain no rain upon it.</hi> So true is that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 107.34. <hi>A fruitfull land maketh he barren, for the wickedneſs of them that dwell therein.</hi> For though the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> were as the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> yet for the iniquity of the Inhabitants, it ſhall be turned into a wilderneſs, and though the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had the bleſſings of the right hand and of the left, yet for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude and diſobedience, God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to withdraw both, <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities:</hi> Therefore I will puniſh <hi>you: You</hi> that were my darlings, mine own peculiar people, you that were as dear to me as the apple of mine eye, becauſe ye have broken my Commandments, and been unmindfull of my loving kindneſs; therefore I will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170350:55"/>
                     <hi>you</hi> for all your iniquities.</p>
                  <p>And the obſervation from hence for our inſtruction is moſt obvious, Gods hatred againſt ſin is ſuch, that he will not let it go unpuniſhed in his deareſt Children. <hi>Adam</hi> was the Maſter-piece of all Gods workmanſhip, and highly in favour with him at the firſt, and yet as ſoon as ever he had taſted of the forbidden tree, God baniſhed this very <hi>Adam</hi> cut of <hi>Paradiſe. Moſes</hi> is often ſtiled the <hi>ſervant</hi> of God, but indeed he ſeemeth to have been more, with reverence be it ſpoken, to have been Gods familiar <hi>acquaintance,</hi> for <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.11. <hi>The Lord ſpake unto</hi> Moſes <hi>face to face, as a man ſpeaketh unto his friend.</hi> Yet as great, and gracious, and familiar as <hi>Moſes</hi> was with God, for one ſin of infidelity God fell out with him, as we read, <hi>Num.</hi> 20. Where when the people murmured for water, God bid <hi>Moſes</hi> but only <hi>ſpeak</hi> to the rock, and it ſhould give forth water, but <hi>Moſes</hi> thought, that <hi>ſpeaking</hi> would not do it, not a <hi>word</hi> therefore, but a <hi>blow,</hi> two of them for failing, he ſmote the Rock <hi>twice;</hi> and for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is he had his doom immediately, that he ſhould not enter into the Land of Promiſe. He that propheſied againſt the Altar at <hi>Bethel</hi> was Gods <hi>favourite,</hi> a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170350:55"/>man of God; yet foraſmuch as he diſobeyed the mouth of the Lord, in going back to eat and drink with the old Prophet, his carcaſe muſt not come to the ſepulcher of his Fathers. I ſhall give one ſignal exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf, that <hi>Lamb</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot, the only righteous perſon that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lived upon the earth; though he were Gods boſome <hi>ſon,</hi> and had not the leaſt ſin of his <hi>own,</hi> only took ours by imputation, yet how harſhly did his Father handle him? Never was there any ſorrow like unto his ſorrow, wherewith the <hi>Lord</hi> afflicted him in the day of his fierce anger. <hi>And if theſe things be done in a green tree, what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> Luke 23.31. <hi>The righteous ſhall be recompenced in the earth, much more the wicked and the ſinner,</hi> Prov. 11. ult. <hi>If Judgement begin at the houſe of God, what ſhall the end be of thoſe men that obey not the Goſpel of God? And if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appear?</hi> 1 Pet. 4 17, 18. If an <hi>Iſraelite indeed,</hi> in whom there is no guil, if this man ſhall be recompenced, ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the earth; with whom ſhall <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites</hi> have their portion, that are full of deceit and fraud, and under whoſe tongue is ungodlineſs and vanity? If a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170350:56"/>and upright man, one that feareth God, and ſtriveth to eſchew evil, if this ſhall be recompenced, ſhall be puniſhed in the earth, what will become of him that hath no fear of God before his eyes, but liveth as if there were no God, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all uncleanneſs, even with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? If a man of a ſtrict life and tender conſcience muſt be puniſhed, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thoſe rebellious Reformers of our age, whoſe conſciences ſeem to be ſeared with an hot iron? If <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>holy</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt be puniſhed, Lord, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> places every what as ſinfull as <hi>Sodome</hi> or <hi>Gomorrah?</hi> If God go ſo roughly to work with them he knoweth, oh how will he handle ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers without mittons? If he execute his Judgements upon <hi>Iury</hi> where he was known, oh what fiery indignation will he pour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heathen that have not known him, and upon the Kingdomes that have not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon his N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me.</p>
                  <p>This teacheth us to flee from ſin, as from the face of a Serpent, conſidering how odious and abominable it is in the ſight of God. Though <hi>Coniah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> King of <hi>Iudah</hi> were the ſignet upon his right hand; yet for ſin God threatneth to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170350:56"/>pluck him thence, <hi>Ier.</hi> 22.24. The <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will not pardon wilfull murder, though his chiefeſt <hi>Favourites</hi> ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it. The <hi>King</hi> of heaven and earth will let no ſin go unpuniſhed, no not in his <hi>Favourites,</hi> in his own people. And he will never connive at ſin in us, that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth here to puniſh it ſo ſeverely in <hi>Iſrael, You only have</hi> I <hi>known of all the families of the earth, therefore</hi> I <hi>will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi> And ſo I have gone thorow the ſeveral parts of the Text. A few words now of application, and I have done.</p>
                  <p>Truly God, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> is loving unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and truly he hath been as lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto <hi>us,</hi> he hath beſtowed many <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative</hi> and many <hi>Poſitive</hi> bleſſings on us. Firſt <hi>Privative,</hi> many deliverances, I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance but in three. The firſt was from <hi>Popiſh</hi> Tyranny and ſuperſtition; a Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more than <hi>Egyptian,</hi> an <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. The damned glutton, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired only a little water for his thirſt; but water will not quench the thirſt of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the whore muſt have blood; till ſhe make her ſelf ſtark drunk with it; no blood of <hi>beaſts,</hi> it muſt be of <hi>men;</hi> no blood of <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> it muſt be the blood of <hi>Saints;</hi> no blood of <hi>Malefactors,</hi> it muſt be the blood
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170350:57"/>of <hi>Martyrs;</hi> and theſe <hi>Martyrs</hi> none of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homets,</hi> they muſt be <hi>Martyrs of Jeſus, Rev.</hi> 17.6. Sad experience of this Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny we had in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes:
<q>Non miſſura cutem niſi plena cruoris hirudo,</q> the <hi>Romiſh</hi> horſleach would not give us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, till ſhe had full gorged her ſelf with our blood. Or indeed, it is a queſtion, whether ſhe would ever have been ſatisfi'd, had we not been ſtrangely delivered from her Tyranny by the <hi>Queen</hi> of all <hi>Queens,</hi> or rather by the <hi>King</hi> of all <hi>Kings, You only have</hi> I <hi>known of all the families of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſecond deliverance was from the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Armado</hi> in the year 1588. which <hi>Fleet,</hi> had it prevailed, our <hi>Thames</hi> had been turned into <hi>Tyber, Romiſh</hi> ſuperſtition had invaded us once more, and then by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Babylon</hi> we might have ſet down and wept, as often as we remembred this our <hi>Sion.</hi> But God brake the ſhips of the ſea through the Eaſt wind, <hi>You only have known of all the families of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A third deliverance was from that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Powder-Treaſon, November</hi> 5. 1605. which was carried on with ſo great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, that it made the <hi>man</hi> of ſin inſult,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170350:57"/>
                     <hi>Te<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> his, ait, eripe flammis,</hi> who is that God that ſhall deliver them out of my hands? But he that dwelleth in heaven laughed the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to ſcorn, and plucked us, as it had been fire-brands out of the burning, <hi>You only have</hi> I <hi>known of all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as God hath befriended us by his <hi>Privative,</hi> ſo by his <hi>Poſitive</hi> bleſſings, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to thoſe which be beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his vineyard. And firſt we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with <hi>Iſrael</hi> for a fruitfull <hi>ſituation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither under the <hi>torrid,</hi> nor the <hi>frozen</hi> zone, neither burned alway with parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heat, nor benummed alway with pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cold, but ſeated in a temperate Climate and fertile ſoil, our folds are full of ſheep, our valleys ſtand ſo thick with corn, that we may laugh and ſing. God hath alſo <hi>fenced</hi> us about, like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the red Sea, with a wall of water, the waters are a wall unto us on our right hand, and on our left. But eſpecially God hath fenced us by his providence and protection, ſalvation hath the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for walls and bulwarks. He hath likewiſe gathered the <hi>Stones</hi> out from us, he hath caſt out the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rabble, and hath planted our Land with the choic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170350:58"/>Religion, that of <hi>Orthodox Proteſtants.</hi> And he hath built a <hi>Tower</hi> among us, he hath ſet up <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Authority. Some think this <hi>Tower</hi> too high, and would fain have it quite demoliſhed; down with it, down with it, ſay they, even to the ground; But theſe are an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of birds that would fain build in others neſts; there are <hi>Presbyterian Levellers</hi> as well as <hi>Independent;</hi> but let them both do what they can, I hope I ſhall never ſee the day wherein theſe <hi>Towers</hi> fall. God hath, as it were a <hi>Wine-preſs</hi> among us too; No Nation under heaven hath better Laws than we; many of them of late yeers have been caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deep ſleep, but I hope that within ſhort time they will be wakened. And that in telling you of one bleſſing, I may tell you of all the reſt, God hath ſet over us a gracious and moſt religious, a prudent and moſt pious <hi>Prince,</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> for his faith and life unſpotted from the world, a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron</hi> and Pattern of good men and all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a Maintainer of his Countries Laws, and however Rebellion hath traduced him, a zealous Profeſſour and <hi>Defender</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O fortunatos nimium, bona ſi ſua nôrint, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligenas!</hi> Happy Nation we to be in ſuch a
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170350:58"/>caſe, happy nation we to have the <hi>Lord</hi> for our <hi>God,</hi> to have him as kind and good to us, as ever he was to <hi>Iſrael: You onely have I known of all the families of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now, <hi>England,</hi> what doth the <hi>Lord</hi> thy <hi>God</hi> require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walk in all his wayes, and to love him, and to ſerve the <hi>Lord</hi> thy <hi>God</hi> with all thy heart and with all thy ſoul?</p>
                  <p>But here <hi>God</hi> may as juſtly complain of us as he did of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that when he looked for grapes from us, we have brought forth wild grapes, there is not a ſin, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. charged upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but we ſtand guilty of it: I have not time to arraign all the ſins that raign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, the time would faile me to reckon up the oaths &amp; imprecations. Our ſins there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being as many, nay, more, I doubt, than thoſe of Iſrael, of two things one, we muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plead more priviledge to ſin than they had, which I am ſure, we cannot, or elſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great mercy, we muſt look for greater judgments, at leaſt to have God ſo threaten us, as here he threatneth the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, You only have I known of all the families of the earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will puniſh <hi>You, You</hi> that have ſeven years ſet in <hi>Counſel,</hi> been in covenant for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170350:59"/>him, but have armed your ſelves againſt him and have at laſt moſt traiterouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned mine <hi>Anointed,</hi> you that have turned judgement into wormwood, you that have turned your ſtill waters into blood, you that have turned your <hi>Kings</hi> houſe, nay your <hi>Gods</hi> houſe, into a den of thieves, you that imagine wickedneſſe and practiſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, you that have ſet your ſelves in no good way; you that dare do any thing but juſtice, you that dare rob your Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, nay, even your God, you that are made up of couſenage and contradictions, you that have no religion but rapine and rebellion, you that are <hi>Papists</hi> in practice, though ye will not own that name, you that neither fear your <hi>God,</hi> nor honour your <hi>King, You</hi> that reſolve to beggar all that refuſe to be ſuch <hi>Rebels</hi> as your ſelves, you that, with <hi>Herod</hi> are deeply dyed in blood of <hi>Innocents,</hi> that make no more of cutting a <hi>mans,</hi> than cutting off a <hi>dogs</hi> neck, you that have filled the <hi>grave</hi> with bodies, and <hi>hell</hi> with ſoules, <hi>therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You</hi> likewiſe of the ſilly <hi>Schiſmaticall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly,</hi> that, out of meer oppoſition, preach in Cloakes; you that are no legal <hi>Synod,</hi> but rather the <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> you that for a pious <hi>Liturgie,</hi> would give the <hi>Church</hi> a pure piece of <hi>Non-ſcence,</hi> you that would
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170350:59"/>baniſh the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and the ten <hi>Commandments,</hi> you that call evill good, and good evill, you that teach for doctrines the commandments of wicked men, you that preach up rebellion for four ſhillings a day, you that would be more than <hi>Deanes</hi> or <hi>Biſhops,</hi> though you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thoſe <hi>Titles;</hi> you that are greedy dogs, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thinking ye have enough, you that ſerve not the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but your own bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Therefore I will puniſh <hi>You</hi> for all your iniquities And <hi>You</hi> alſo of the <hi>Court</hi> for your flattery &amp; prodigality, &amp; <hi>You</hi> of the coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>City</hi> for your diſloyalty, <hi>You</hi> that dare fight gainſt none but your <hi>King;</hi> and you of the <hi>Country</hi> for your ſtupidity, and ſottiſhneſſe, in ſufferring your fellow ſubjects ſo long to enſlave you: <hi>You</hi> of the Clergy likewiſe for temporizing, for fearing the face of men, for not daring to ſpeak truth; <hi>You</hi> of the <hi>Laity</hi> for tenebrizing, for your <hi>Conventicles, You</hi> that are <hi>rich,</hi> for your covetouſneſs, <hi>You</hi> that are <hi>poor</hi> for your idlenes, <hi>You</hi> that are men for your <hi>day-ſins,</hi> gluttony and drunkenneſs, you that are <hi>Women,</hi> for your <hi>night-ſins,</hi> cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering &amp; wantonnes; all you that are againſt the <hi>King,</hi> for forſwearing of your ſelves, ſome of you that are for the <hi>King,</hi> for your cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary ſwearing, you that ſwear not as <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170350:60"/>did, by the life of your <hi>King,</hi> but by the life of your <hi>God,</hi> and by the <hi>Prince of life,</hi> whom ye ſwear over once a day from top to toe, as if ye would ſwear <hi>Christ</hi> in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or <hi>God</hi> out of heaven, <hi>Therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi> Ye have been told of this ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and if I now told you of it rightly, I ſhould tell you weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they who thus mouth their oaths, and their <hi>God damne them,</hi> they are no better than the very enemies of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi> Nor are they enemies to him only, but arrant <hi>Traitors</hi> alſo to their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> as arrant <hi>Traitors</hi> as thoſe that have impriſoned him, let them never tell me they are the Kings <hi>friends,</hi> for they are the worſt of <hi>enemies,</hi> becauſe of <hi>Swearing</hi> the Land mourneth, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.10. And mourn it will a great deal worſe, unleſs this, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other horrid ſins be baniſhed. We have ſeen hitherto, but, as it were, the morning of mourning, the beginning of ſorrows: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we repent, our land, like <hi>Rama,</hi> will be filled with bitter mourning, <hi>as the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, Zech.</hi> 12.11. For indeed how can we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hope to have God <hi>bleſſe</hi> us, when we are daily at him to <hi>damne</hi> and <hi>confound</hi> us? how can we hope for peace with <hi>men,</hi> ſo long as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170350:60"/>by oaths and other ſins we fight againſt our <hi>God?</hi> No, there is no peace to the wicked, their portion is deſolation, which, though we hope ſtill to out-run, yet in the end it will overtake us, <hi>Quod differtur non aufertur;</hi> as God hath <hi>leaden</hi> heeles, ſo he hath <hi>iron</hi> hands, though he hath ſpared us therefore a long time; yet he will pay us home at laſt, he will bruiſe us with a rod of iron, and break us in pieces like a potters veſſell. If a man will not turn, he will bend his bow. Now the farther back ye draw the bow-ſtring ere ye ſhoot, the more forcibly the arrow fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when ye ſhoot. So the longer God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layeth to puniſh us for our ſins, the more harſhly will he handle us, when once he beginneth with us. He hath long begun with us, I know, but, without our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, he will not make a full end; if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſin, our ſufferings ſhall be of long continuance; if we keep not the Laws of <hi>God,</hi> the Laws of the <hi>Land</hi> ſhall ſtill be kept from us, if we will not ſuffer <hi>Christ</hi> to raign over us, God will not ſuffer our <hi>Lord</hi> the <hi>King</hi> to raign.</p>
                  <p>To ſumme up all therefore in one word, let us repent, and be converted, or if we do not this for our <hi>own</hi> ſakes, yet let us do it for our poor <hi>Kings</hi> ſake, who, in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170350:61"/>my conſcience, hath a long time ſuffered for our ſins. Let not us, brethren, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>God;</hi> and he will never forget <hi>us,</hi> he will ſpeedily remember <hi>King Charles,</hi> and all his troubles; let us by a new life ſhew our thankfullneſſe for Gods former loving kindneſſe, and this will encourage him to confer new benefits upon us, he will be our <hi>God,</hi> We ſhall be his <hi>People;</hi> as he hath been good to us in former, ſo will he be in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages to us and our poſterity for evermore. he will turn <hi>Ours</hi> and our <hi>Soveraigns</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity as the rivers in the South; he will turn our heavineſſe into joy, he will take off our Sackcloth; and gird us with gladneſſe, he will put a new ſong into our mouth, even a thankſgiving unto our <hi>God,</hi> though the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi> have been <hi>Tragical,</hi> yet the <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe</hi> ſhall be <hi>Comical,</hi> God will make good to us that promiſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.19. <hi>The fast of the fourth moneth, and the faſt of the ſift and the faſt of the ſeventh month, and the faſt of the tenth ſhall be to us joy and gladneſſe, and chearfull feaſts.</hi> Which God of his infinite mercy vouchſafe to grant unto us, for the merits of his eternal Son, our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A <hi>LOOKING-GLASSE</hi> FOR LEVELLERS.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon PREACHED At S<hi rend="sup">T</hi>. <hi>Peters Pauls-wharf,</hi> Upon <hi>Sunday, Sep.</hi> 24. 1648.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:62"/>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170350:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A <hi>LOOKING-GLASSE</hi> FOR LEVELLERS.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>LUKE 20.14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>But when the Husbandmen ſaw Him, they rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned among themſelves, ſaying, This is the Heir, Come, let us kill him, that the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance may be ours.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt particle is <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and ſevereth the <hi>Text</hi> from the foregoing verſes, wherein our <hi>Saviour</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth, as it were, a <hi>dark Lanthorn</hi> to the chief Prieſts, that ſeeing they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170350:63"/>might ſee, and not perceive; and that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they might hear, and yet not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Or rather he ſheweth them their faces in a glaſs, wherein they might plainly ſee what manner of men they were. The <hi>Looking-glaſs</hi> is this preſent Parable of the Vineyard, wherein he inſiſteth chiefly on three things. Firſt, He ſheweth the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent and Pedegree of the <hi>Prieſthood, A certain man planted a Vineyard, and let it forth to husbandmen.</hi> Secondly, He upbraideth the ingratitude of theſe husbandmen in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing their Landlords ſervants, they beat them, they intreated them ſhamefully, they wounded them, they killed them. Thirdly, he threatneth a puniſhment for their ingratitude, which is no leſs than a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter, the Lord ſhall deſtroy theſe Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſhall give the Vineyard to others.</p>
                  <p>But more punctually to ſurvey and view this Parable, by this <hi>Certain man,</hi> the <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of this <hi>Vineyard,</hi> we are to underſtand the worlds <hi>Creator,</hi> God himſelf. By the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> his <hi>Church,</hi> confined for a long time to <hi>Judea,</hi> Iſa. 5.7. By the <hi>Husbandman,</hi> to whom the Vinevard was let out, we are to underſtand the <hi>Chief Prieſts,</hi> who by their Doctrine and Example were, as it were, to prune and dreſs <hi>Gods</hi> vineyard,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170350:63"/>that ſo it might be fruitful in good works. By the <hi>Servants</hi> ſent to demand ſome of the fruit of this Vineyard, we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the inſpired <hi>Prophets,</hi> who were ſent by <hi>God</hi> to call the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> to repentance, to bring forth fruits worthy of amendement of life. <hi>Trium autem mentiofit, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Areti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> God is ſaid to have ſent ſeverally three <hi>Servants</hi> to the Husbandmen, becauſe <hi>three</hi> is a perfect number, and is therefore uſed to ſhew Gods unceſſant deſire of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nceſſant,</hi> I ſay, it was, for though it knew a little <hi>Intermiſsion,</hi> yet it knew no <hi>termination</hi> though the word of the <hi>Lord</hi> were preci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us in the dayes of <hi>Eli,</hi> even then <hi>God</hi> raiſed up <hi>Samuel</hi> to reprove the lewdneſs of the <hi>Priests;</hi> there was no time, there was no place, but the <hi>Jewiſh Priests</hi> had <hi>Prophets</hi> ſent among them. Before their captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> they had <hi>Iſaiah, Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Amos, Micah, Zephany,</hi> and others. In time of their captivity, they had <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Daniel.</hi> After their captivity they had <hi>Haggai, Zachary</hi> and <hi>Malachy.</hi> And the laſt was not the leaſt, for among thoſe that were born of women, there was not a greater <hi>Prophet</hi> than <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what entertainment found theſe <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> amongſt their Maſters <hi>Tenants?</hi> juſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170350:64"/>ſuch as we, that will not preach Treaſon, meet with in theſe dayes; juſt ſuch as the Meſſengers of Truth have ever found, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitia, Verbera, Vulnera,</hi> as <hi>Stella</hi> ſpeaketh, Revilings, Blowes, Wounds; nay, very death it ſelf: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſawn aſunder, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> and <hi>Zechary</hi> were ſtoned, <hi>Amos</hi> had his brains beaten out with a club, <hi>Micah</hi> was thrown down head-long from a rock; and all the reſt did the <hi>Jews</hi> either kill; or at leſt hunt after them; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as St. <hi>Stephen</hi> asked them, <hi>Which of the Prophets did not their Fathers perſecute?</hi> Acts 7.52.</p>
                  <p>Yet ſee the never wearied goodneſs of Almighty <hi>God;</hi> though the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> had killed his <hi>Prophets,</hi> and had ſtoned them that were ſent unto them, yet he did ſo long to do them good, that <hi>Nullum non movebit lapidem,</hi> he will leave no ſtone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled, no not the <hi>Corner-ſtone;</hi> he had but one boſome-<hi>Son,</hi> and he ſendeth him to them for his rent, preſuming that for ſhame they would not ſend him away empty; they will reverence, ſaith he, their young <hi>Land-Iord,</hi> when they ſee him. <hi>But when the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen ſaw him, they reaſoned among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaying, This is the Heir, Come, let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170350:64"/>
                  <p>The Text then, ye ſee, is a conſpiracy againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where we meet together the four cauſes of it. Firſt here is the <hi>Efficient</hi> cauſe or Conſpiratours, the <hi>Huſbandmen.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>Material</hi> cauſe or perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt, the <hi>Heir,</hi> when they ſaw <hi>him.</hi> Thirdly the <hi>Formal</hi> cauſe or manner of their conſpiracy, <hi>they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, come, let us kill him.</hi> Fourthly and laſtly, the <hi>Final</hi> cauſe or end of their conſpiracy, which was, that they might be Lords of the Mannour, <hi>that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance may be ours.</hi> Theſe are the parts, of which in order briefly, and very plainly. I begin with the firſt part, the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, which are <hi>Coleni,</hi> the <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the firſt <hi>Man</hi> had been a good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, there had been no <hi>Husband-man,</hi> the Earth need have had no <hi>Mid-wife,</hi> ſhe would have brought forth of her ſelf. But <hi>Haec maledictio Adae &amp;c.</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> this was a curſe entailed on <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, that for his ſake the ground it ſelf was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, his barrenneſs in obedience made the very Earth grow barren. Which may therefore ſerve to mind us ſinners of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the husbandry of the hand may teach us the husbandry of the heart, even to break
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170350:65"/>up our fallow ground; and ſow in tears. But I muſt not inſiſt upon theſe <hi>Georgicks,</hi> I muſt lead you from <hi>corporal</hi> to <hi>spiritual</hi> husbandmen. And theſe are the painful <hi>Preachers</hi> of Gods word. For as the Earth muſt be plowed and harrowed by the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man,</hi> before ſhe will ever bring forth her increaſe; So the men of the earth muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and corrected by the <hi>Church-man,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will bring forth the fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. The <hi>Clergy,</hi> like the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> are a kind of <hi>Plow-men.</hi> They that do, as it were, drive the plow, are ordinary <hi>Miniſters.</hi> They that hold the Plow, are the reverend <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the Plow would not go ſo well, ſhould <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy</hi> be aboliſhed. Let theſe <hi>Labourers</hi> therefore have their due, they are worthy of their hire. And let them likewiſe have a reſpectful eſtimation ſet upon them, for the <hi>Courtier</hi> cannot live without the <hi>Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the King</hi> himſelf <hi>is ſerved by the field,</hi> Ec. 5.9. As then where no <hi>Husband men</hi> are, the people ſterve; So Likewiſe where no <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> where no viſion is, the people periſh.</p>
                  <p>Which admoniſheth Gods <hi>Husbandmen,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> to be induſtrious. There is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion more laborious than that of <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen,</hi> who in the ſweat of their face moſt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170350:65"/>commonly eat their bread. And herein they are a pattern and enſample unto us, who indeed ſhould labour more abundantly than they all; becauſe they labour but to ſuſtain mens bodies, we to feed their ſouls. We muſt therefore abound alwayes in the work of the <hi>Lord;</hi> we muſt preach the word as St. <hi>Paul</hi> charged <hi>Timothy,</hi> not ſlothfully, but painfully, we muſt labour in the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> we muſt be inſtant, and eager, and earneſt in our preaching, in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, in time of peace, in time of War, we muſt reprove, we muſt rebuke, we muſt exhort with all long-ſuffering and doctrine, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
                  <p>And as we muſt be fervent, ſo we muſt be perſeverant in our office, having put our hand to Gods plow, we muſt reſolve not to look back: we muſt not with <hi>Demas</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our function, and embrace the world; nor muſt we ceaſe to exerciſe it, till we juſt put off this Tabernacle, though there be never ſo great danger in the exerciſing of it: Husbandmen will not give over plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a ſhower of rain, nor muſt we give over preaching, becauſe of perſecution, though we are never ſo ſuperannuated, though we are ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> the aged, or though ſo feeble, that with St. <hi>John,</hi> we muſt be carried to the Pulpit.</p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170350:66"/>
                  <p>Neither muſt we lord it over <hi>Gods</hi> heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, like theſe chief Prieſts in our Text, who, that they might be Lords of the vineyard, conſpired to murder the right Lord of it; the conſpirators, our Text telleth us, were <hi>Coloni,</hi> the <hi>Husbandmen.</hi> And ſo likewiſe <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi> told our <hi>Saviour,</hi> thine own nation, and the chief Prieſts have delivered thee unto me, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.35. What prodigious unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful miſcreants were theſe! there can be no <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithet</hi> bad enough for ſuch Traitors. For they that taught the people, taught they not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? They that were dreſſers of the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, durſt they conſpire againſt the owners of it? Durſt men of the <hi>Temple</hi> venture on the worſt of treaſons?</p>
                  <p>Well, we ſee by this the truth of that old axiome, <hi>Corruptio optimi eſt peſsima,</hi> the beſt wine, maketh the ſharpeſt vineger, if <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> once turn Traitors, they are incarnate dviils. So our Saviour ſtiled the Traitor <hi>Iudas,</hi> &amp; thus likewiſe all <hi>Synod-traytors</hi> may be ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And ſo I paſſe from the firſt part of the Text, the <hi>Efficient</hi> cauſe of this conſpiracy, or the Conſpirators, the Husbandmen, to the ſecond, the <hi>Material</hi> cauſe of it, or the Perſon conſpired againſt, which was the <hi>Heir, when the Husbandmen ſaw Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Heir.</hi> The wiſe God of peace and order, will not have every man his own
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170350:66"/>carver, for the beſt weapon would then be the beſt evidence, the ſtrongeſt arm would be the ſureſt title. But as he hath ordained a ſucceſſion of <hi>Men,</hi> ſo of <hi>Eſates,</hi> their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt be their <hi>Heirs,</hi> they muſt leave their ſubſtance to their Babes. <hi>Dominio non fundatur in gratiâ,</hi> they that call themſelves babes of grace, all things are not theirs; had not <hi>Iacob</hi> ſupplanted <hi>Eſau,</hi> this grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe one had been <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Heir. For the inheritance was ever chalenged by the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſon; and therefore this title of <hi>Heir</hi> muſt needs be due to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was the firſt-begotten of his heavenly <hi>Father,</hi> the firſt-born of his earthly <hi>Mother,</hi> the firſt-born of every creature, the firſt-born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many brethren, by right of primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture he was the <hi>Heir,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, faith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heir of all things, Heb.</hi> 1.2. The earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the compaſſe of the world, and they that dwell therein, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.1. And he that is owner of all things, maketh his Eldeſt Son a promiſe of them, he promiſeth to give him the Heathen for his inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for his poſſeſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. The Devil, I know, made his brags once, that he was the Heir of the World, when he ſhewed our <hi>Saviour</hi> all the Kingdomes of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170350:67"/>it, and told him, they were <hi>His:</hi> But as he was a <hi>Murderer,</hi> ſo he was a <hi>Lyar</hi> from the beginning. It is true, <hi>Abraham</hi> had a promiſe that he ſhould be heir of the world, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teſtifyeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. But though to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed there were ſuch a promiſe made, yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> for all this was ſtill to be the <hi>Heir,</hi> it is the ſame <hi>Apoſtles</hi> obſervation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>He ſaith not, to ſeeds, as of many, but to thy ſeed, as of one, which is Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But here we muſt not be miſtaken, for though our <hi>Saviour</hi> be ſtiled the <hi>Heir;</hi> yet we muſt know that his inheritance is no <hi>temporal</hi> but a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> inheritance, his Kingdome, his Church, his heritage is not of this world. And as we Chriſtians are not of it, ſo our inheritance properly is not in it, we are heires to a better country, that is, an heavenly, though not by nature yet by grace, though not by birth, yet by faith we are made partakers of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Saints in light, we are heirs of <hi>God,</hi> coheires with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we have an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, &amp; that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for us, where we ſhall ſee the Son of man ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the right hand of God, where we ſhall ſee our pierced Saviour, not to our
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170350:67"/>terrour, but our triumph, where we ſhall ſee him with no other, but with theſe ſame eyes; the ſame numerical, though not the ſame <hi>mortal</hi> eyes, where we ſhall ſee that which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſo much wiſhed to ſee, <hi>Chriſtum in carne,</hi> Chriſt in the fleſh, and that which many Prophets and Kings deſired to ſee, and could not ſee it. They ſaw this ſight indeed afar off, which did not a little chear their hearts, <hi>Abraham rejoyced,</hi> ſaith our <hi>Saviour, to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad,</hi> John 8.56. But when <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaw him in the Temple, his eyes were ſatisfied with ſeeing; cloſe them now, <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaid he, let me die in peace, <hi>For mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation.</hi> And we may obſerve here by the way, that if ever we will ſee Chriſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we muſt firſt ſee him upon earth, for though we cannot ſee him as <hi>Simeon,</hi> and theſe chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> did, with the eyes of our body, yet we may ſee him as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did, with the perſpective of our faith; we may, and we muſt ſee him thorow this glaſs darkly, before ever we can ſee him face to face. A <hi>Christian</hi> muſt not be like a <hi>Cyclop,</hi> with one eye, the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Peraldus</hi> obſerveth, muſt have two, <hi>Oculum fidei,</hi> and <hi>Oculum glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170350:68"/>the eye of <hi>Faith,</hi> and the eye of <hi>Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> We muſt walk by Faith, before we can walk by ſight. We muſt, like <hi>Jacob,</hi> be firſt married to blear-eyed <hi>Leah,</hi> before we can obtain beautifull <hi>Rachel;</hi> we muſt firſt ſee our <hi>Saviour</hi> with the tender eye of faith, before ever we can behold him with the brighter eye of glory.</p>
                  <p>Now though our <hi>Saviour</hi> pronounce them bleſſed that have not ſeen, and yet have believed; and though Faith be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> the evidence of things not ſeen, yet <hi>Segnius irritant animos, &amp;c.</hi> as the Poet ſpeaketh, a man will give more credit to his eyes, than to his ears; Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> would not go by hear-ſay, except he might ſee, he reſolved not to believe. But the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> were ſo perverſe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t they would not believe their own eyes, for they conſpired againſt our <hi>Saviour,</hi> though they ſaw him, though they knew him, though they knew him to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and could ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>This is the Heir.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From whence we may obſerve, that as there is a zeal without knowledge, ſo there is a knowledge without faith. The very <hi>Devils</hi> knew our <hi>Saviour,</hi> they knew him to be the Son of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Jeſus I know,</hi> ſaid the evil ſpirit to thoſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170350:68"/>
                     <hi>Exorciſts, Act</hi> 19.15. But their knowledge was meerly <hi>hystorical,</hi> like their faith. And juſt after this manner did the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> know <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are indeed ſome places of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> that ſeem to contradict our <hi>Text,</hi> and to ſay, that the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> knew not <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> knew not that he was the <hi>Heir.</hi> For St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith plainly, <hi>That the world knew him not,</hi> John 1.10. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding the Jewes for killing the <hi>Prince of life,</hi> uſeth theſe very words, <hi>I wote that through ignorance ye did it, as did alſo your Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> Act. 317. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of God, which I take to be his <hi>Son,</hi> telleth us in expreſs words, <hi>That none of the Princes of this world knew it, for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.8.</p>
                  <p>But I anſwer, Firſt, To that of <hi>St. John,</hi> the world knew not Chriſt, that is, the <hi>greateſt</hi> part of it. To that of St. <hi>Paul, None</hi> of the Princes of this world knew him, that is, <hi>few</hi> of them. To that of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> and their <hi>Rulers</hi> ſlew him ignorantly, that is, <hi>ſome</hi> of them did ſo, thus the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gloſs would have thoſe places con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I anſwer, That the <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170350:69"/>of the Chief Prieſts was not <hi>Purae negationis,</hi> but <hi>Pravae diſpoſitionis,</hi> if they were ignorant of Chriſt, it was becauſe they would be ignorant, as the people uſed to ſay to their <hi>Seers, See not,</hi> ſo theſe <hi>Seers</hi> themſelves ſeem to have ſtopped their ears, and ſhut their eyes, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they could not chuſe but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the <hi>Meſsiah;</hi> becauſe all the propheſies of his coming were fulfilled. Firſt, That prophecy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the time of his birth, <hi>The Scepter was then departed from Judah,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> paid contribution, they were Tributaries to the <hi>Romans.</hi> Secondly, that prophecy, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.2. pointing out the place of his Nativity, he was born in <hi>Bethleem</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> which was the place aſſigned for <hi>Chriſt's</hi> birth, as theſe chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> or their <hi>predeceſſours</hi> told King <hi>Herod.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if neither the time, nor place of his birth, yet his <hi>miracles</hi> might perfectly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them that he was the <hi>Meſsiah.</hi> And therefore when St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſent two of his Diſciples to ask him if he were <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all the anſwer he would return by them was this; <hi>Go, and ſhew</hi> John <hi>again thoſe things ye do hear and ſee; the blind receive their ſight, the deaf hear, the lame walk,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170350:69"/>the Lepers are cleanſed, the dead are raiſed up</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.4, 5. And when <hi>Christ</hi> cometh, ſome asked the queſtion, ſhall he do more miracles than theſe which this man doth? <hi>John</hi> 7.31. Though the chief Prieſts then would not believe his <hi>words,</hi> yet they might have believed him for his works ſake. But neither of theſe would prevail with them; they had ears, yet would not hear; they had eyes, yet would not ſee, which was a moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aggravation of their Treaſon, for had they been ſtark blind, their ſin haply might have been remitted; but becauſe ſeeing they would not ſee, therefore their ſin remaineth. And this ſin of theirs ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be no better than the very ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> for againſt conſcience, out of meer malice they conſpired to put this <hi>Heir</hi> to death. And I pray God the <hi>Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders</hi> of our rebellious Reformation be not guilty of the ſelf-ſame ſin, for it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be out of a deſpetate, inveterate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that they perſiſt in their conſpiracy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the beſt of <hi>Kings.</hi> But theſe Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours ſhall bring up the rear of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. I paſs therefore from the ſecond part of the Text, the perſon that the chief Prieſts conſpired againſt, which was the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170350:70"/>
                     <hi>Heir,</hi> to the third, which is the <hi>Formal</hi> cauſe, or <hi>Manner</hi> of their conſpiracy, <hi>They reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, Come, let us kill him.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>they reaſoned.</hi> Treaſon is a ſin of deliberation, a ſtudied ſin. Theſe chief Prieſts reaſoned, they argued the caſe. All ſins are not <hi>Cognita,</hi> known ſins, there are ſins of ignorance, as well as ſins of knowledge. But there is neither <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rartia facti,</hi> nor <hi>Ignorantia juris</hi> in <hi>Treaſon,</hi> it is wilfully contrived and complotted, it is a premeditated ſin. To ſin out of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity or ignorance, to be overtaken in a fault, this is but (as it were) <hi>Chance-medly,</hi> pardonable by the Law of God and man. But to ſin with a full career, of ſet purpoſe to conſult about it, this is no leſſe than <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful murder,</hi> a ſin that never muſt goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardoned; and yet this was the ſin of theſe chief <hi>Priests</hi> in our Text, <hi>They reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, Come, let us kill him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Come,</hi> wicked men uſe to call and invite one another to commit ſin, they are a ſociable ſort of people, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to go to hell alone, they entiſe and engage as many as they can to be partakers with them, they are in league and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; there is a combination among them,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170350:70"/>eſpecially among <hi>Traitors,</hi> ſuch as theſe chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> were, who conſpired againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> juſt as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren againſt him, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Come let us kill him. Ioſeph</hi> indeed ſcaped with life, thankes to his El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt brother; but <hi>Jeſus</hi> had not one <hi>Reuben</hi> to ſpeak for him, none but a <hi>woman,</hi> &amp; ſhe could not prevaile, the of <hi>Kings</hi> the earth ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, and the <hi>Rulers</hi> taking counſel together againſt the <hi>Lord,</hi> and againſt his <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for againſt the holy child <hi>Ieſus</hi> both <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> with the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and the people of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were gathered together; they gathered them together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſoul of the righteous, that they might condemn the innocent blood, <hi>They reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, Come, let us kill him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kill him.</hi> As the <hi>Devil</hi> is a murderer, ſo all thoſe that are of his party thirſt after blood. <hi>Shimei</hi> did a great deal of wrong to <hi>David</hi> in calling him ſo, but otherwiſe <hi>Bloody-man,</hi> and man of <hi>Belial</hi> may well go together, for there is no man deſperately wicked, but he is a blood-thirſty man. It hath been thus from the beginning of the world, and will be ſo to the end. <hi>Cain was of that wicked one,</hi> what is next <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and ſlew his brother,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.12. This was
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170350:71"/>alſo the reſolution of wicked <hi>Eſau, The dayes of mourning for my father are at hand, then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will I ſlay my brother Jacob, Gen.</hi> 27.41. Thus <hi>Pharaoh</hi> commanded the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Mid-wives to murder every male-child of the <hi>Hebrewes, if it be a Son, then ye ſhall kill him, Exod.</hi> 1.6. And thus <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew all the children in <hi>Bethleem,</hi> from two years old and under. <hi>Math.</hi> 2.16. Thus we read of <hi>Herodias,</hi> that nothing would ſatiate her malice but St. <hi>I hn Baptiſt</hi>'s blood. <hi>Math.</hi> 14.8. Thus the <hi>Iewes</hi> cryed out againſt St. <hi>Paul, away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, for it is not fit that he ſhould live, Act.</hi> 22.22. and <hi>Act.</hi> 23.12. we find ſome that <hi>bound themſelves under a curſe</hi> (they took the <hi>Covenant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſaying, that they would neither eat nor drink, till they had killed Paul.</hi> And the whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>drunk with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Ieſus, Revel.</hi> 17.6. I might be almoſt infinite in examples, but this in our Text ſhall be <hi>instar omnium,</hi> we may ſee the bloody-mindednes of wicked men by theſe chief <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who conſpired not to baniſh or impriſon, but each to murder <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>Son,</hi> they <hi>reaſoned among themſelvs, ſaying, come let us kill him.</hi> And the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the multitude, and of the chief Prieſts
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170350:71"/>prevailed, this treaſon ſtood not alway in conſultation, but went on to action; what the common counſell determined wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the common people executed greedily, they caſt the <hi>Heir</hi> out of the vineyard; and ſlew him with this dreadfull impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>His blood be on us, and on our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> And ſeeing our Maſter was thus uſed, we muſt expect no better meature, but even to be killed all the day long, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh, and to be counted as ſheep appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſlaine, the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and the <hi>Omega</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> is writ in blood,</p>
                  <q>Sanguine fundata est Eccleſia, ſanguine crevit, Sanguine firmatur, ſanguine finis erit.</q>
                  <p>And we need not wonder at this, if we believe our <hi>Saviour,</hi> for it is but that which he told us long agoe, that we ſhould be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and hunted after for his ſake, yea, the time will come, ſaith he, that whoſoever killeth you will think he doth <hi>God</hi> ſervice. A prophecy that ſeemeth to point directly at our very dayes, when the bloudieſt of <hi>Souldiers</hi> think themſelves the beſt of <hi>Saints,</hi> when murdering of loyal <hi>Chriſtians</hi> goeth for pure religion. But though our blood be ſhed like water on every ſide, yet our God
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170350:72"/>that is true and holy, will, in his good time, judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth, there will on day be a ſtrict inquiſition made for blood, for the blood of <hi>Strafford</hi> &amp; <hi>Canterbury,</hi> for the blood of <hi>Lucas</hi> and <hi>Liſle,</hi> for the blood of <hi>Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> and <hi>Chaloner,</hi> for the blood of <hi>Yeomans, Bourchier,</hi> and <hi>Burleigh,</hi> for the blood of <hi>Dunkin,</hi> and others in <hi>Kent;</hi> there will be a time, I ſay, if not in this, yet in the next world, when all the righteous innocent blood that hath of late years been ſhed in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſhall be required at the hands of this <hi>Tyrannical</hi> I will not call it, but a <hi>Satanical</hi> generation.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I paſſe from the third part of the Text, which was the <hi>Manner</hi> of the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> conſpiracy, in theſe words, <hi>They rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned among themſelves, ſaying, Come let us kill him,</hi> to the fourth and laſt, the <hi>End</hi> of their conſpiracy, which was, that they might be Lords of the Mannour, <hi>that the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may be ours. But now the Husbandmen,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In every action, there is both <hi>Opus,</hi> and <hi>Intentio oper antis,</hi> the doing of the work, and the end for which we do it, and by an <hi>Hysteron Proteron,</hi> the laſt of theſe is firſt, what is laſt in execution, the ſame is firſt in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, the <hi>End</hi> being alway the <hi>beginning</hi> of the action.</p>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:170350:72"/>
                  <p>Now it is an <hi>Axiome</hi> in Philoſophy, <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; bonum convertuntur,</hi> let the action be what it will, <hi>good</hi> is alway propounded for the <hi>End,</hi> either <hi>Honestum</hi> or <hi>Iucundum,</hi> or <hi>Utile,</hi> either an honeſt, or a pleaſant, or a profitable end, they that do evill, will ſay they do this that good may come of it, good to themſelves at leaſt, though hurt to others, or if it be not good indeed, yet it ſhall ſeemingly be good, and the laſt of thoſe three ends, the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto themſelves, <hi>Bonum utile,</hi> they ſet up profit for their end, <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi> They propound the ſame end with thoſe ſinners that <hi>Solomon</hi> cautioneth us to take heed of, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.11, 13. Where hope of gain is uſed as a motive to invite others to joyn with them, <hi>Come, let us lay wait for blood, let us lurk privily for the innocent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, we ſhall find all pretious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our houſes with ſpoil.</hi> And at the 19. <hi>ver.</hi> there is juſt ſuch another paſſage, <hi>So are the wayes of every one that is greedy of gain, which taketh away the life of the owners thereof.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>— Quid non mortalia pectora cogis</l>
                        <l>Auri ſacra fames? —</l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:170350:73"/>There is not any villany but will go down with a man, if it have a golden bait. <hi>The love of money is the root of all evil.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Balaam</hi> will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if he may gain but the rewards of divination. <hi>Achan</hi> will take of the accurſed thing, if he may gain a <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> garment, two hundred ſhekels of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and a wedge of gold. <hi>Saul</hi> will ſpare the ſpoile of <hi>Amalek,</hi> if he may gain good ſtore of rich plunder. <hi>Gehazi</hi> will tell an arrant lie to <hi>Naaman,</hi> if he may gain two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, and new clothes. <hi>Iudas</hi> will betray his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> if he may gain thirty pieces of ſilver, The <hi>Souldiers</hi> will ſay that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſtollen out of the grave, if the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> will give them large mony. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> will plot <hi>Naboths</hi> death, if ſhe may gain his vineyard; ſhe proclaimed a faſt, yet knew no other godlineſſe but gain; and this likewiſe ſet the chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> awork to conſpire the death of <hi>Chriſt, Come,</hi> ſay they <hi>let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi> That we may be no longer <hi>dreſſers,</hi> but <hi>poſſeſſors</hi> of the vineyard, that there may be no Superiour, no Lord, over us, but that the <hi>Church</hi> may be ruled and governed as we liſt, that the doctrine and diſcipline of it may be what we ſee good; nay, that we
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170350:73"/>may have dominion as well over mens <hi>free-hold,</hi> as their <hi>faith,</hi> that their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and coffers may both be at our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. This was the end that the cheif <hi>Prieſts</hi> aimed at, when they conſpired againſt the Heir, <hi>come, let us kill him, that the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may be ours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And herein the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> looketh very like them, who ſtileth himſelf Chriſts <hi>Vicar,</hi> St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, he ſaith that he is the right <hi>Heir,</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> of Chriſts whole <hi>Church,</hi> he arrogateth the title of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop,</hi> he chalengeth (as it were) the <hi>Wardſhip,</hi> nay the <hi>Lordſhip</hi> of the Church, whatſoever he <hi>ſaith</hi> muſt go for <hi>Goſpel,</hi> meerly becauſe he <hi>ſaith</hi> it, he taketh upon him more than <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> authority, even that which is <hi>Gods</hi> peculiar, <hi>To forgive ſins,</hi> for which cauſe fall the ſilly people unto him, and thereout he ſucketh no ſmall advantage, it is a maſſe of money that his <hi>Pardons</hi> annually bring in to him. And other ſtratagems he hath, but all to enrich himſelf, he will releaſe men out of his pretended <hi>Purgatory,</hi> if they will give him money enough, he will warrant they ſhall be heirs of Heaven, though herein he contradict himſelf, for ſometimes he telleth them, that they can never be ſure of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven til they come thither; yet thus he befool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170350:74"/>the people, he will warrant them an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in <hi>heaven,</hi> if they will make him their Heir on <hi>Earth.</hi> His whole Religion indeed is nothing elſe but a politick project to get money, he feedeth not the flock of Chriſt, but feedeth upon it, he keepeth the people in ignorance, ſeeking not them, but theirs, <hi>He</hi> and all his <hi>Cardinals, Monks,</hi> and <hi>Abbots,</hi> they ſeek their own profit and preferment, their own gain and greatneſs, like theſe cheif <hi>Prieſt</hi> in our Text, whoſe aim was to get the inheritance, <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Let us kill him that the inheritance may be ours.</hi> And ſo I have gone thorow the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts of the <hi>Text,</hi> a few words of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and I have done.</p>
                  <p>Our Text is a plain conſpiracy againſt our <hi>Saviour.</hi> And the conſpiracy of Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers againſt our <hi>Soveraign</hi> will match it right. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> let out his vineyard to <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſo our <hi>Soveraign</hi> did (as it were) let out his Kingdome to <hi>States-men,</hi> he gave them power to prune and dreſſe it, to take off ſuperfluities, to rectifie enormities, he gave them their hearts deſire, and denied them not the requeſt of their lips, he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that which none but a moſt indulgent <hi>Landlord</hi> would ere have granted; they ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a leaſe of him, and he gave them a long
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170350:74"/>leaſe, longer than any of their <hi>Predeceſſours</hi> ever had, he made them no Tenants for <hi>yeares,</hi> much leſſe at <hi>will,</hi> but reſerving his <hi>fee-ſimple,</hi> I mean his <hi>Negative</hi> voice, he gave it under his hand that he would not re-enter, till they themſelves conſented to it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O fortunatos nimium, bona ſi ſua n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rint, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricolas!</hi> What men were ever ſo happy, as theſe might have been? How might the glory of their <hi>God,</hi> of their <hi>King,</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> and even of <hi>themſelves</hi> have been advanced by them? But neglecting the three firſt, they aimed chiefly at the laſt, at their <hi>own</hi> glory. For aſſoon as their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky leaſe was ſealed, they ſtraight way thought themſelves free-holders, taking <hi>Regal</hi> power upon them, as if the <hi>Militia,</hi> the Kings <hi>Inheritance,</hi> had been theirs, they deveſted their <hi>Soveraign</hi> of it, and inveſted <hi>themſelves</hi> with it, making the <hi>Heir</hi> of three <hi>Kingdomes</hi> (though no child in any thing, but malice) to differ nothing from a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, when he was Lord of all. For, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, they took upon them to un-make, and to make Lawes, ſaying, we have the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> power, who is Lord over us? And that they might the better enjoy the <hi>Crown,</hi> they entred into <hi>Covenant</hi> againſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170350:75"/>the <hi>Miter,</hi> reſolved to aboliſh the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent government of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> root and branch. And becauſe the <hi>King</hi> againſt his oath and conſcience would not yeeld to this, Come, ſaid they, let us compell him to it by force of arms; they ſet the people awork firſt to mutiny, then to fight againſt him, as who ſhould ſay, we have no part in <hi>Charles,</hi> neither have we inheritance in the ſon of <hi>James,</hi> every man to his tents, <hi>O England,</hi> they proclaimed open war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Adherents,</hi> giving out Commiſſions to kill and ſlay all perſons that ſhould oppoſe them, their <hi>Soveraign</hi> Lord the <hi>King</hi> was not excepted, for bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets cannot diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Scepter</hi> and a <hi>Shovel,</hi> the ſword (as <hi>David</hi> ſaid) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth one as well as another. But ſeeing they could not kill him in the field, they have ſince attempted it in priſon; it is too apparent that the <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion had an hand in that late conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy againſt him. Nor is it only <hi>Carolus,</hi> but even <hi>Rex</hi> that they ſtrike at going about not only to kill the <hi>Perſon,</hi> but the very <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of the King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Let us break his bands aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and caſt away his cords from us;</hi> Come, let us make no more <hi>addreſſes</hi> to him, but
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170350:75"/>let us make our ſelves a <hi>Free-State,</hi> that the name of <hi>Monarchy</hi> may be no more in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. And to effect this, they have made the Kingdom not only a <hi>field,</hi> but even a <hi>ſea</hi> of blood, breathing out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſlaughter againſt all loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, killing and ſlaying, butchering and murthering their brethren, whoſe blood they have ſhed like water on every ſide, like that woman in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves drunk with the blood of <hi>Saints,</hi> and with the blood of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is no marvel if theſe blood-hounds will not have God's <hi>Commandments</hi> read in <hi>Churches,</hi> for one of theſe telleth them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſlly, they muſt do no murther, and as almoſt all the reſt, ſo moſt eſpecially that ſixth <hi>Commandment</hi> they count <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> for murdering of men is their profeſſion, and a great part of their <hi>Religion,</hi> as if <hi>Mars</hi> were their god, and <hi>Mahomet</hi> their <hi>Meſsiah.</hi> Let them uſurp the name of Chriſtians while they will, I am ſure their bloody practiſes proclaim them arrant <hi>Turks, Chriſtianity</hi> is for the ſaving of mens lives, <hi>Turciſm</hi> for the deſtroying of them, and ſuch is the Religion of theſe Rebels, Deſtruction is in their way, they are ſtill
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170350:76"/>oppoſing of <hi>Treaties;</hi> the way of peace have they not known, like horſleaches they never think they have blood enough, they would have it even to the horſe bridles, as if they had a mind to ſwim in blood.</p>
                  <p>And all this under pretence of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> a pretence ſo pitiful and ſo thread-bare, that <hi>I</hi> wonder men are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to be ſeduced by it, for <hi>Religion</hi> was ever made the ſtalking horſe to <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion;</hi> and indeed this muſt be the pretence, or elſe the deſign will ſoon be daſht, for ſhould they proclaim themſelves open <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſts,</hi> and profeſs the ſubverting of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> I think the world is not ſo bad, but that it would be ready to tear them all in pieces. They are bound therefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend piety, like <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi> but their actions tell the world that they aim at other ends, even at <hi>Libertiniſm,</hi> that they may be lawleſs, that they may do what they liſt, that they may roar and whore, yet never be queſtioned or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled, for there are no men living more given to the <hi>fleſh,</hi> than they that pretend ſo extreamly to the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> but chiefly the <hi>Inheritance,</hi> the Kingdoms <hi>wealth</hi> is that they aim at, they ſeek not the Kingdom
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170350:76"/>of God, but the riches of this Kingdom, that the Revenue of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and the Patrimony of the <hi>Miter,</hi> and the eſtate of every loyal Subject may be theirs. Moſt truly may that of the <hi>Prophet</hi> be applyed to them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Their eyes, and their hearts are not but for their covetouſneſs, and for to ſhed innocent blood, and for oppreſsion, and for violence to do it,</hi> witneſs their <hi>Sequeſtrations,</hi> their <hi>Decimations,</hi> their <hi>Confiscations,</hi> their <hi>Contributions,</hi> their <hi>Excize,</hi> their <hi>Fift,</hi> and <hi>Twentieth</hi> part, beſides their greedineſs in getting all the gainful offices in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Their love of money hath been the root of all evils, we may ſee this by their dividing of the ſpoil, their ſharing of the Kingdomes wealth among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, eſpecially by their ſacrilegious ſelling and uſurping of <hi>Church-lands,</hi> they had long-ago ended the Wars, or rather they had never begun it, but to get theſe Lands; they kill, as St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaketh, becauſe they deſire to have, to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens poſſeſſions, the whole world, and even their own conſcience bear witneſs to this Truth. And their <hi>Chaplains</hi> of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> are juſt like them, thoſe <hi>Iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Rebels</hi> that love the wages of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that have four ſhillings a day to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170350:77"/>make <hi>Rebellion</hi> good by <hi>Scripture;</hi> an heart they have exerciſed about covetous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, through covetouſneſs with fained words, making merchandiſe of men, Their aim is to get the greateſt <hi>Livings,</hi> even <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities,</hi> which once they ſo much railed at; and under the name, forſooth, of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturers,</hi> they creep into <hi>Deans</hi> and <hi>Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries</hi> houſes, ſome get Maſter-ſhips of <hi>Colledges,</hi> ſome of <hi>Hoſpitals;</hi> all their aim is that the <hi>Inheritance,</hi> the profitable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments may be theirs.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not need to rake this Dunghil, nor ſtir this <hi>Camerina</hi> any further. It is moſt evident how bloody and covetous all theſe rebellious vine-dreſſers are. What therefore ſhall the Lord of the vineyard do unto them? Sure in Juſtice he might deſtroy them (though he deligheth more in Mercy, and might let out his vineyard to others, he might diſcard theſe unjuſt Judges, he might diſplace theſe unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Stewards, theſe <hi>Zimries</hi> deſerve no peace, no pardon, that would have ſlain their Maſter, theſe <hi>Sheba's</hi> deſerve to have their heads thrown over the wall, theſe <hi>Hamans</hi> to be executed upon their owne gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, thoſe mine enemies (might the King ſay) which would not that I ſhould raigne
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170350:77"/>over them, bring them hither, and ſlay them before me,
<q>
                        <l>— ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> eſt lex juſtior ulla,</l>
                        <l>Quam necis artifices arte perireſua.</l>
                     </q> They might juſtly be ſerved, as the <hi>Scythian</hi> Queen ſerved <hi>Cyrus,</hi> have their heads thrown into a blood-bowl, with this expro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of their Tyranny, <hi>Satiate vos ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Sanguiſugae, quem ſitiſtis.</hi> Their heads ſhould go down to the grave with blood, theirs eſpecially that have ſhed the blood of war in Peace, that for meer envy, have murdered their Captives in cold blood. And methinks indeed theſe men of blood ſhould have ſuch an Hell within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that, like <hi>Cain,</hi> they ſhould be afraid that every one that meeteth them, will ſlay them. For blood thirſty men, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh, ſhall not live out half their dayes, if they do, they ſeldome die peaceably in their beds,
<q>
                        <l>Ad generum Cereris ſine caede &amp; vulnere pauci</l>
                        <l>Deſcendunt — &amp; ſicca morte tyranni.</l>
                     </q> But to ſpeak no more of thoſe that are <hi>abſent,</hi> let me now apply my ſelf to you here <hi>preſent,</hi> and let me now intreat you to be no
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170350:78"/>longer-partakers in their ſins, walk not ye in the way with them, refrain your feet from then path, for their feet run to evil, and make haſte to ſhed blood; and blood-ſhed, rethren, how light ſoever now eſteemed, is a moſt crying ſin, the cries of it enter into the ears of the Lord of <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Waſh therefore not your hands only, but your <hi>hearts</hi> too from this ſin, let no bloody thoughts any longer lodge in you. As the death of men is dear in the ſight of <hi>God,</hi> ſo let it be in your ſight. Remember what Almighty God ſaith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5, 6. <hi>Surely the blood of your lives will I require, at the hand of every mans brother will I require the life of man. Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> Take heed then of ſhaking hands with thoſe men that delight in blood.</p>
                  <p>This ſin will not ſuffer God to be quiet, till he avenge it. To the ſlain his ears are open, but faſt ſhut to thoſe that ſlay them, all your dayes of <hi>Faſting</hi> and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation will be ineffectual, if ye be ſtill for War, though ye make never ſo many prayers. God will not hear you, ſo long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your hands are full of blood. Waſh your ſelves therefore, I beſeech you, make
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170350:78"/>you clean from the blood of all men, be no longer acceſſory to murder, by raiſing money to maintain War; ye know that no Murderer (no not a ſecond-hand Murderer) hath eternal life abiding in him. Let then your prayer be, that God would deliver you from this kind of blood-guiltineſs, and hereafter make better uſe of your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, make it not the price of blood. <hi>Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be he,</hi> ſaith God by <hi>Jeremy, that keepeth back his ſword from blood,</hi> Jer. 48.10. A place of Scripture that <hi>Aſſembly-men</hi> have ſtrangely wreſted of late years, preſſing it upon mens conſcience as a warrant for them to cut throats, urging it as a <hi>Commiſsion</hi> and <hi>command</hi> for them to kill and ſlay; and many thouſands have followed their pernicious Doctrine, even <hi>London,</hi> the ſometime faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full City is become an Harlot, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs did once lodge in it, but now Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. But let not theſe bloody wolviſh Prophets ſeduce you any more. <hi>Wo to the bloody City,</hi> this is the voice of the Lords Prophets, <hi>And if any man</hi> teach you <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let him be accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O that ye would know therefore in this your day the things that belong unto your peace, leſt otherwiſe they be hid for ever from your eyes. Conſider what Almighty
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170350:79"/>God faith to the <hi>Jewes, Iſa.</hi> 1.19, 20. For the very ſame he ſaith now to you, <hi>If ye be willing and obedient,</hi> willing to have your <hi>King</hi> reſtored, and will henceforth be obedient to him, <hi>Ye ſhall eat the good of the Land,</hi> but if ye refuſe his gracious pardon, and reſolve ſtill to rebel againſt him, <hi>Ye ſhall be devoured with the ſuord, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> If ye ſtill keep up the ſword, ye will in the end periſh by it; your ſword will certainly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate your own heart. Obey not them therefore that think they can kill the body, and that would have you make a trade of killing, but obey him that can kill body and ſoul, whoſe expreſs Command is, that ye ſhall not kill. If ye will not follow peace, ye ſhall never ſee the Lord, if here ye baniſh that from you, he will hereafter baniſh you from him, he will renounce you with thoſe words of <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 139.19. <hi>Depart from me, ye bloody, ye blood-thirsty men.</hi> And as God abhorreth the blood-thirſty, ſo doth he the covetous man, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10. He that ſaid, Do not <hi>kill,</hi> ſaid alſo, Do not <hi>covet,</hi> as therefore ye muſt abſtain from <hi>blood,</hi> ſo muſt ye from <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs;</hi> let not this be once named amongſt you, as becometh Saints, but learn of the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170350:79"/>Apoſtle in whatſoeuer ſtate ye are, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be content; ſee that ye covet no mans ſilver, or gold, or apparel, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving food and rayment, be therewith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Ye know whoſe Law it is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours houſe,</hi> take heed then, brethren, of coveting <hi>Biſhops houſes,</hi> or any thing elſe that is anothers, and not yours. <hi>All covet, all loſe,</hi> ye have good Scripture for it. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.10. <hi>I will give their wives unto others, and their fields to them that ſhall inherit them, for every one from the leaſt even unto the greatest is given to covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; from the Prophet even unto the Priest;</hi> They that greedily get away other mens, beget a gangrene in their own Eſtates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <q>De malè quaeſitis vix gaudet tertius Haeres.</q> Take heed therefore, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and beware of covetouſneſs; the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ingeminated, and therefore the more emphatical, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.15. Conſider alſo what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. <hi>No covetous man, who is an Idolater, hath any inheritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of God.</hi> And conſider what the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 9. <hi>They that will be rich</hi> (as it were whether God will or no) <hi>fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170350:80"/>temptation and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which drown men in destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and perdition.</hi> Covetouſneſs tempteth men to murder; this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that which maketh <hi>Rebels</hi> ſo bloody as they are; From whence come. Wars and fightings among you? Surely <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> hath been the Original of them all; the lower ſort of people ſtrive to be in an <hi>higher</hi> room; the <hi>poor</hi> would fain turn Tables with the <hi>Rich,</hi> they would thus have every <hi>valley</hi> to be filled, and every <hi>mountain</hi> and hill to be laid low, as if in this ſenſe, every man were bound to ſeek anothers wealth; they that were born to nothing, ſtrive to get others birth-rights, calling themſelves, forſooth, the <hi>Saints,</hi> who, ſay they, muſt inherit the earth; they would make themſelves rich, that have nothing, and others poor, that have great riches.</p>
                  <p>But to conclude, this brethren, is not the office of <hi>Saints,</hi> but of the King of <hi>Saints,</hi> it is the Lord that maketh poor, and maketh rich, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.7. Preſume not then to take <hi>God</hi>'s office out of his hand, ſtrive not <hi>per fas &amp; nefas</hi> to make your ſelves rich, if <hi>God</hi> have made you poor, but be content with that portion of outward things that he hath given you. <hi>The ſilver is mine, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170350:80"/>the gold is mine, ſaith the Lord of hoſts,</hi> Hag. 2.8. Deny him not therefore that priviledge, which your own ſelves chalenge, give him leave to do what he pleaſeth with his own. Let not the leaſt root of covetouſneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in you, remember that godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with contentment is great gain; if the riches of others increaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them, ſeek not theſe things <hi>below,</hi> but thoſe <hi>above,</hi> ſtrive not for an inheritance on <hi>earth,</hi> but to have one in <hi>heaven;</hi> that ye may baniſh <hi>cruelty;</hi> let <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs</hi> be baniſhed firſt, that ye may not thirſt after other mens blood; covet not their <hi>goods. Haſt thou killed,</hi> ſaid God to <hi>Ahab, and alſo taken poſſeſsion?</hi> Well, ye know what became of him and <hi>Jezebel</hi> for this. Stifle therefore not only your mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therous, but alſo your covetous thoughts. If you muſt needs be killing, mortifie your earthly members; if ye muſt needs be <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting,</hi> covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, <hi>God</hi> hath choſen the poor of this world, rich in faith, to be heirs of his Kingdom; labour therefore to get the gold of faith, whereby ye may be rich towards God; and then, though here ye have no temporal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet hereafter ye ſhall have one far better, ye ſhall be Heirs apparent unto
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170350:81"/>Heaven, ye ſhall inherit glory, God will give you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified: Though now you are in your <hi>nonnage,</hi> yet at the laſt day ye ſhall be perfect men; ye ſhall attain to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ſhall then invite you to enter upon your <hi>Inheritance,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Come ye bleſsed of my father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A SEVERE</hi> Sentence <hi>AGAINST SEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE</hi> CITIZENS.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon PREACHED At S<hi rend="sup">T</hi>. <hi>Maries in</hi> Oxford, Upon <hi>Sunday,</hi> March 17. 1644.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:82"/>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:170350:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A SEVERE SENTENCE AGAINST <hi>SEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE CITIZENS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>JONAH 3.4.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>And he cryed, and ſaid, yet fourty dayes, and <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhall be overthrown.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere are two of the divine <hi>Attributes,</hi> which are Gods <hi>Mercy,</hi> and his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ſo that I may ſay with the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 11.22. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> here <hi>the goodneſs and the ſeverity of God,</hi>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:170350:83"/>for the words of our Text are both a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,</hi> and a <hi>Commination;</hi> as they give warning, ſo there is Mercy in them, <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc quadraginta dies, yet fourty dayes;</hi> as they threaten, ſo there is judgement in them, <hi>Subvertetur Nineveh,</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</hi> This might be the general divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe words. But if we examine them more particularly, they will afford us theſe five parts. Here is firſt the <hi>Preacher,</hi> He, the <hi>Prophet Jonah.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The <hi>Manner</hi> of his preaching, <hi>He cryed.</hi> Thirdly; The <hi>Matter</hi> of his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he threatned an <hi>overthrow.</hi> Fourthly, The place of his preaching, the City <hi>Nineveh.</hi> Fifthly, The <hi>Time,</hi> when his Preaching or Prophecy was to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed and fulfilled, and that was within <hi>fourty dayes, And he cryed, and ſaid, yet fourty dayes, and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And of theſe in order: I begin with the firſt part, the <hi>Preacher,</hi> He, the Prophet <hi>Jonah.</hi> And in him we may obſerve four things; His <hi>Name,</hi> His <hi>Countrey,</hi> His <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> His <hi>Commiſsion.</hi> The firſt thing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the Preacher or Prophet, is his <hi>Name,</hi> which I ſhall little more than name, <hi>Jonah,</hi> which is <hi>Hebrew</hi> for a <hi>Dove.</hi> And
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170350:83"/>in ſome ſenſe every <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Preacher</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Jonah,</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Dove,</hi> not only innocent and harmleſs, but alſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and revengeleſs, without gall or bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, putting up any wrong or injury, without deſire of revenge, like a <hi>Dove.</hi> The ſecond thing obſervable in the <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Preacher</hi> here, is his <hi>Countrey,</hi> he was a <hi>Jew,</hi> I am an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſo he told the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. An Hebrew, and ſent to the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> who were <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> why ſhould they give any credit to ſuch a fellow? Suppoſe a Weather-beaten wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Jew (Jonah</hi> look'd now like ſuch a one) ſhould come into our chief <hi>City,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim that within fourty dayes it ſhould be overthrown, O how ridiculous would men think ſuch words as theſe, they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly take them but for ſome <hi>Jewiſh fables.</hi> But theſe <hi>Ninevites</hi> were nothing ſo incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous as men are now adayes, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred not with fleſh and blood, but repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the preaching of <hi>Ionah,</hi> though a <hi>Iew,</hi> though a meer ſtranger to them. But the men of our age are ſo far from giving heed to ſtrangers, that thoſe of their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot bring them to repentance. The third thing obſervable in the <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Preacher</hi> here, is his <hi>Parentage,</hi> he was the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170350:84"/>ſon of <hi>Amittai,</hi> chap. 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. Now <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittai,</hi> being interpreted, is as much as <hi>True</hi> or <hi>Truth.</hi> And this <hi>Amittai</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought by ſome to have been that ſon of the widdow of <hi>Zerephath</hi> raiſed up by <hi>Elijah.</hi> The probability whereof is taken from thoſe words of the widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman. 1 <hi>King</hi> 17. <hi>ult. By this I know that thou art a man of God, and that the word of the Lord in thy mouth is Truth.</hi> From whence ſome would obſerve, that becauſe the woman found <hi>Elijah</hi> a true <hi>Prophet</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of her ſon to life, therefore ſhe called her ſons name <hi>Amittai,</hi> True, or Truth. But this cannot be ſo for two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as <hi>Luther</hi> hath well obſerved. For firſt, <hi>Elijah</hi> lived, we know, in the days of <hi>Ahab.</hi> But <hi>Ionah</hi> and <hi>Amittai</hi> lived in the dayes of <hi>Jeroboaem</hi> the ſecond. Secondly, The widdow of <hi>Zarephath</hi> was a <hi>Zidonian,</hi> and ſo a <hi>Gentile.</hi> But <hi>Jonah</hi> and <hi>Amittai</hi> were of <hi>Gath-Hepher</hi> in the Tribe of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulon,</hi> and therefore <hi>Jewes,</hi> 2 <hi>King</hi> 14.25. But to paſs by this Genealogie, we will obſerve only in general, that our <hi>Prophet</hi> here was the ſon of <hi>Amittai,</hi> that is, the ſon of <hi>Truth.</hi> And ſo indeed ſhould all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> all <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Word be, ſons of <hi>Amittai,</hi> like this our Prophet here, not
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170350:84"/>ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſie, but rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Word of Truth.</p>
                  <p>But how few ſuch ſons of <hi>Amittai:</hi> are there at this day? Our Saviours prediction is long ſince come to paſs; falſe Prophets are riſen up amongſt us, and have deceived many, ſuch as have changed the truth of God into a lye, privily bringing in moſt damnable Hereſies. And too too many fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their pernicious wayes; by reaſon of whom, the way of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the good old way of Truth is evil ſpoken of. Thus a wonderfull and horrible thing is committed in our land. The Prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy falſely, and the people love to have it ſo; and what will they do, unleſs it pleaſe God to reſtrain them in the end thereof?</p>
                  <p>But here perhaps ye may ask, as <hi>Pilate</hi> once did, what is truth, how ſhall we know the ſons of <hi>Amitai,</hi> theſe ſons of truth, how ſhall we try the ſpirits whether they be of God? For anſwer to which I muſt lead you to the third thing obſervable in our <hi>Prophet</hi> here, and that in his <hi>warrant</hi> or <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> he was ſent from God. And he was ſent <hi>twice</hi> to <hi>Nineveh</hi> before he went thither once, he had one commiſſion in the firſt Capter, and another in this third. And ſo had the Apoſtles of our bleſſed Saviour, one in the tenth of St. <hi>Mathow,</hi> and another in
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170350:85"/>the eight and twentieth. <hi>No man taketh this honour to himſelf.,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apostle, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron, Heb.</hi> 5.4. If any man ſhall intrude himſelf, we are to brand him for a falſe prophet, for he that entereth not by the dore into the ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, by the dore of <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> ordination, as well as that which ſome call their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded inſpiration, the ſame is a thief and a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. And how many ſuch thieves and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are there at this day? Such are they which preſume to preach when they were never ſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> great is the company of ſuch pitifull preachers, as ſome call them, but the Lord gave them not the word; though now therefore they ſtretch forth their mouth unto the heaven, and though their tongue goeth thorow the world, yet our <hi>Saviour</hi> at the laſt day will put ſuch a queſtion to them, as they ſhall never anſwer, wherefore did ye preach my law, how durſt ſuch as you take my covenant in your mouth?</p>
                  <p>And ſo I paſſe from the firſt part of the Text, which was the <hi>Preacher,</hi> He, to the ſecond, which is the <hi>Manner</hi> of his preaching, he <hi>Cryed.</hi> And this is the tenour of many other prophets commiſſions as well as his. For thus <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> commiſſion runneth, <hi>c.</hi> 58. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not,</hi> &amp;c. And thus <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> Cry in the ears of <hi>Jeruſalem, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170350:85"/>Thus likewiſe <hi>Hoſea</hi>'s commiſſion runneth, cry aloud at Beth-aven. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 8. And we read of S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> that he was a Cryer in the wilderneſſe. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.3. And ſo ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all <hi>prophets,</hi> all <hi>preachers</hi> of the word be.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Praedico</hi> ſome will have derived from <hi>Praeco,</hi> the <hi>Preacher</hi> therefore ſhould be a publick <hi>Cryer,</hi> to cry the loſt ſheep of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or he ſhould be a <hi>Cryer</hi> to rouſe men from carnal ſecurity, or, as it were, a <hi>Bell man,</hi> like St, <hi>Paul,</hi> telling them it is high time for them to awake out of ſleep. For if men be not dead in ſin, yet ſure they are aſleep, if not faſt aſleep, yet their eares are dull of hearing. <hi>Preachers</hi> therefore muſt not whiſper, they muſt cry aloud. Not as if they ſhould be like <hi>Plinies</hi> nightingale neither, <hi>vox, et praeterea nihil,</hi> their Doctrine to conſiſt meerly in their voice, for what St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith of the wrath of man, the ſame may I ſay of his voice, the voice of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God. And yet how is vociferation and lung-labour cryed up in theſe dayes! if he do but thunder and thump, Oh! <hi>non vox hominem ſonat,</hi> who teacheth like him, will the women ſay, a great prophet they cry out is riſen up among them. But a <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> whole duty conſiſteth not in making of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170350:86"/>a great noiſe, there muſt not only be words to ſound, but there muſt be ſound words, there is a <hi>Dixit</hi> in the Text, as well as a <hi>Clamavit,</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> did not only cry, but cryed, and ſaid, which leadeth me briefly from the ſecond part of the Text, the manner of <hi>Ionah's</hi> preaching, he <hi>cryed,</hi> to the third, which is the <hi>Matter</hi> of his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſaid there ſhould be an overthrow,</p>
                  <p>There are three names eſpecially given to <hi>Prophecy</hi> in holy <hi>Scripture.</hi> Firſt, it is called <hi>the word of the Lord,</hi> from the Lords reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. Secondly, it is called <hi>a viſion,</hi> from the Prophets attending to it. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is called <hi>a burden,</hi> from the peoples groaning under it.</p>
                  <p>The name given to this prophecy of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> is <hi>verbum Domini,</hi> the word of the Lord, <hi>ch.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. But by the argument of it, this ſeemeth to challenge rather the title of <hi>Nahum's</hi> prophecy, which is <hi>Onus Nineve,</hi> the burden of <hi>Nineveh, Nah.</hi> 1.1. For it threatneth the city of <hi>Nineveh</hi> with utter ruine and deſolation, <hi>Subvertetur Nineve,</hi> Nineveh ſhall be overthrown. As if he ſhould have ſaid, though <hi>Nineveh,</hi> like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> be full of goodly buildings, yet there ſhall not be left in it one Stone upon another, which ſhall not be thrown down; it
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170350:86"/>ſhall be made empty, it ſhall be made waſte, it ſhall be turned upſide down. And if <hi>Nineveh</hi> had been ſerved ſo, (as indeed afterward it was) yet Almighty God might have asked as <hi>David</hi> once did in another caſe, what have I now done? Is there not a cauſe; For though our Text make no mention of it, yet if we look back to the ſecond verſe of the firſt Chapter; we ſhall find it there, <hi>Ariſe, go to</hi> Nineveh <hi>that great City;</hi> but why? the reaſon followeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the verſe be out, <hi>For their wickedneſs is come up before me.</hi> The iniquity of theſe <hi>Ninevites</hi> was as great as their City, and this was the reaſon why God told them that they ſhould be overthrown. Sin is that which provoketh Almighty God, both to execute and to threaten Judgement. Which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us all to fear the cauſe for fear of the effect; to eſchew evil, left we provoke God to threaten us with Judgement. It is a fearfull thing, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to fall into the hands of the living God. He ſhal rain, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> ſnares upon the ſinners, fire and brimſtone, ſtorm and tempeſt, this ſhall be their portion to drink. When the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> ſpeaketh of God in Judgement, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth him terrible and dreadfull, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth him in the moſt affrighting man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170350:87"/>that can be imagined. I will give you but one expreſſion or inſtance for all the reſt, <hi>Our God is a conſuming fire,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle. Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>ult.</hi> The Nations are but as a drop of a bucket, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.15. Now if that fire at <hi>Elijas</hi> ſacrifice made nothing, as it were, of twelve barrels, but licked up the whole trench-full of water; what would become of us, think we then, if God ſhould enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to judgement with us, when we, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, even all the Nations of the earth are but as one drop of a bucket, and God is a conſuming fire: we muſt needs cry out as thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did at the promulgation of the Law: ſurely this great fire will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume us. Let us then, brethren, give no entertainment to the evil of ſin, leſt the evil of puniſhment dog and ghoſt it at the heels, leſt we provoke God to threaten us as his Prophet here threatens <hi>Nineveh, Subvertetur Nineve, Nineveh ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; Overthrown,</hi> ſaith he, oh but <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> this is a hard ſaying, who can hear it? for moſt men are like <hi>Ahab,</hi> they hate a <hi>Michaiah,</hi> a plain-dealing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet or Preacher, becauſe he prophecyeth no good concerning them, but evil. Or they are like thoſe who are complained
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170350:87"/>of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.10. <hi>Which ſay to the Seers, ſee not, and to the Prophets, prophecy not unto us right things, ſpeak unto us ſmooth things, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy deceits.</hi> And this being the humour of moſt men, how then durſt <hi>Jonah</hi> threaten the <hi>Ninevites</hi> with an <hi>Overthrow?</hi> yes, as <hi>St. John Baptiſt</hi> reſolved to tell <hi>Herod</hi> of his inceſt, though he loſt his head for it; ſo let the <hi>Ninevites</hi> here take it how they will, <hi>Jonah</hi> is reſolved to do his meſſage; <hi>Subvertetur Nineve,</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be overthrown.</hi> Here is an inſtruction then for all thoſe that are the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not to play the <hi>Gnathoes,</hi> not to be <hi>Placentia-Preachers,</hi> not to faſhion their Sermons according to the humour and temper of their Diſciples, though indeed, <hi>Is quaeſtus nunc eſt multo uberrimus,</hi> this is the way to thrive, I know, for this cauſe fall the people unto them, and thereout ſuck theſe <hi>Temporizers</hi> no ſmall advantage. But this muſt not be our practiſe, we have not ſo learned Chriſt: We muſt not be the devils Fidlers, to play what tune the people bid us, nor muſt we be the <hi>Devils</hi> upholders to ſew pillows under mens elbowes; nor muſt we be the devils <hi>Plaisterers</hi> to daub men up with untempered mortar; we muſt not make fair weather, preaching peace, peace to ſinners,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170350:88"/>when there is no peace to the wicked, but we muſt plainly denounce wrath &amp; vengeance againſt impenitent ſinners, unleſs ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converted, threatning them that they ſhall be confounded: we muſt deal with them as <hi>Jonah</hi> dealeth here with the City <hi>Nineveh,</hi> who threatneth it with a <hi>Subverte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, it ſhall be overthrown.</hi> And ſo I paſs from the third part of the Text, the <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>Jonah</hi>'s preaching, an <hi>overthrow,</hi> to the fourth, which is the place of his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the City <hi>Nineveh, Subvertetur Nineve, Nineveh ſhall be overthrown.</hi> And this <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh, Strabo telleth us,</hi> was the <hi>Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis of Aſſyria,</hi> the chief City of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſituate by the river <hi>Lycus.</hi> A City we know it was, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Civitas,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Multus,</hi> from the multitude of people that uſe to be in Cities. In the Original it is called a <hi>City of God,</hi> which at firſt ſight ſeemeth ſomewhat ſtrange, ſeing there was neither Worſhip, nor Temple, nor Prophet of God in it. <hi>Luther</hi> thinketh it was ſo called from the care of God to preſerve it. But I am rather of <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this, who will have it called a City of <hi>God,</hi> by an <hi>Heb a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſm,</hi> for ſo indeed the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> when they ſpeak of an high <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> a tall <hi>Cedar,</hi> or a great <hi>City,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170350:88"/>Gods dwelling is on high, and becauſe he is of ſuch immenſity, therefore they think they cannot expreſs theſe things ſo to the life, as by calling it a Mountain, or a Cedar, or a City of god. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which ſhould be <hi>Civitas. Dei,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Original,</hi> is rendred <hi>Civitas magna,</hi> by St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> whom our <hi>Engliſh Tranſlators</hi> follow, calling it a great City. But if <hi>Nineveh</hi> were ſo great a City, even of three dayes journey, as we read, how then durſt <hi>Jonah</hi> be ſo bold as threaten it after this manner? Yes, he had good reaſon for it, for Prophets muſt not be afraid of the face of men, though briars and thorns were with them, and though they dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Scorpions: we that are <hi>Preachers</hi> muſt of all other, be full of godly courage and reſolution, not fearing to denounce wrath and vengeance againſt ſinners, though for number they be many, though for Power mighty, <hi>Jonah</hi> here threatneth <hi>Nineveh,</hi> though an exceeding great City. <hi>Nineveh,</hi> I ſay, a great City. <hi>Little Zoar,</hi> we know was ſpared; <hi>Great Nineveh</hi> muſt be overthrown. God regardeth not ſo much the goodlineſs, as the goodneſs of a City. Nay, the greater it is, if wicked, the greater puniſhment he ſtill layeth upon it. For it is with ſinfull
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170350:89"/>places, as with ſinfull perſons, the mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> famous the one, the more infaemous the other; <hi>Nineveh-ſins, London-ſins, City-ſins,</hi> theſe are exemplary, leading ſins, they may do a great deal of miſchief in the Countrey; the <hi>Ninevites</hi> ſins were ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated from the greatneſs of their City.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Nineveh</hi> is intepreted <hi>Specioſa,</hi> fair or beautifull. An Epithite given alſo to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was indeed called beauty in the abſtract, the perfection of beauty, the joy of the whole earth, as may be eaſily gathered from <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.15. And yet as beautifull as theſe Cities were, there was neither of them ſpared. What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ye have heard. And though <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſcaped awhile, yet ſhe went not ſtill unpuniſhed, but returning to her old ſins, <hi>Nahum</hi>'s prophecy fully came to paſs, and this likewiſe of our Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> here, <hi>Nineveh was overthrown.</hi> God regardeth no beauty, but the beauty of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, beauty in the Abſtract, without this, it is no Beauty, but deformity, <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> though never ſo beautifull, yet God threatneth this very <hi>Nineveh</hi> to overthrow it. And ſo I paſs from the fourth part of the Text, the place of <hi>Jonah</hi>'s preaching,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170350:89"/>the City <hi>Nineveh,</hi> to the fift and laſt, which is the <hi>Time</hi> when his prophecy or preaching was to be accompliſhed and fulfilled, and that was within fourty dayes. <hi>And he cryed and ſaid, yet fourty dayes, and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be overthrown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourty,</hi> but why ſo? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, yet three dayes, ſo it is in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> and how come they to fall ſhort of the <hi>Original</hi> ſeven and thirty dayes? The ordinary <hi>gloſs</hi> anſwereth it thus, <hi>Sive per quadraginta dies, ſive per triduum, idem Chriſtus ſignificatus est,</hi> whether it be fourty, or three dayes, the ſame <hi>Chriſt</hi> is hereby ſignified, who was three dayes in the grave, and afterwards fourty dayes converſant with his Diſciples. But this ſeemeth to me a very affected and far fetcht anſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> will have a further my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie in it. <hi>Tres dies,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Fidem Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis, quadraginta poenitentiae tempus ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant,</hi> the three dayes in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> ſaith he, point at faith in the holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> the fourty dayes, in the <hi>Original,</hi> point at time of repentance; and therefore, as he thinketh, was this voluntary miſtake and difference between the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> to ſignifie that faith and repentance are the way to avert Gods Judgements. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170350:90"/>the one of theſe by three dayes aimed at ſuch a faith, I will not ſay; that the other by forty dayes aimeth at repentance, this is ſomewhat probable; For <hi>Numerus quadragenarius, poenitentialis eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rupert.</hi> the number of forty is a penitential number; it is ſaid therefore to theſe <hi>Ninevites</hi> here, <hi>Adhuc quadraginta dies, yet fourty dayes,</hi> to let them know that there was yet time of grace and repentance for them, and to admoniſh them that they husband well this time of their viſitation. For as other dayes, ſo even the day of grace and repentance hath an end. <hi>Eſau</hi> found no place of repentance, though he ſought it carefully with Tears, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. The very time of repentance laſteth but for a time, according to that of the Angel, which ſware by him that liveth for ever and ever, that there ſhould be time no longer, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.6. Let this acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate our repentance, while there is time for us to repent, while there is <hi>Adhuc qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draginta dies, yet fourty dayes.</hi> Ye may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how our Saviour bewaileth <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> for trifling away this precious time, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41. <hi>He beheld the City, and wept over it, ſaying, If,</hi> or, <hi>O that thou hadst known, even thou at leſt, in this thy day, the things that belong unto thy peace, but now
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170350:90"/>they are hid from thine eyes. For the dayes ſhall come upon thee, that thine enemies ſhall caſt a trench about thee, and compaſs thee round; and keep thee in on every ſide, and ſhall lay thee even with the ground, and thy children within thee, and they ſhall not leave in thee one ſtone upon another, becauſe thou knewest not the time of thy viſitation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is moſt dangerous, brethren, to trifle away the day of grace and mercy, <hi>Behold now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of ſalvation.</hi> It will be too late for us to knock when the door of mercy is ſhut; to day, if we will hear Gods voice, harden we not our hearts. God ſuffered the manners of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> fourty years in the wilderneſs, and he would have ſuffered the manners of theſe <hi>Ninevites</hi> fourty days in the City; but I am ſure he hath no where promiſed to bear with us ſo long, he hath promiſed no years, nay he hath promiſed us no dayes, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, even this very next night our ſouls may be required of us. Let us not then deſpiſe or abuſe Gods goodneſs and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, let us not drive off our repentance till the nine and thirtieth day: we have a common ſaying, that we were better leave than lack, the <hi>Ninevites</hi> here ſeem to have made good uſe of it, for they repented as
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170350:91"/>ſoon as the word was out of <hi>Jonab</hi>'s mouth, though they had <hi>Adhuc quadraginta dies, yet fourty dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But here ariſeth a queſtion that muſt needs be anſwered, namely, Why Gods threatnings come not to paſs? for we read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. That God threatned <hi>Abimeleck</hi> with preſent death, <hi>Thou art but a dead man for the woman that thou haſt taken,</hi> yet we know, that <hi>Abimeleck</hi> died not at that time: So likewiſe God threatneth <hi>Hezekiah</hi> with death, 2 <hi>King</hi> 20.1. <hi>Set thine houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die, and not live;</hi> yet we know there were added unto his dayes fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years. In like manner God threatneth <hi>Nineveh</hi> to overthrow it within <hi>fourty dayes,</hi> and yet when theſe <hi>fourty dayes</hi> were expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Nineveh</hi> was not overthrown. And how cometh this to paſs, that Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings ſhould not take effect? I anſwer, as Gods promiſes, ſo his threatnings like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are not abſolute, but conditional, for there is a twofold Will in Almighty God, <hi>Voluntas ſigni,</hi> and <hi>Voluntas beneplaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> the Will of the ſign, or the ſign of Gods Will, which is the revealed Will of God, and the Will of the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or the good pleaſure it ſelf, which is the ſecret Will of God. Now to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170350:91"/>only in the caſe of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> (for one anſwer may ſerve for all objections of this nature) that <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhould be overthrown within fourty dayes, this was <hi>voluntas ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> the will of the ſign, the revealed Will of God, but that <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhould repent, &amp; ſo not be overthrown, this was <hi>voluntas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neplaciti,</hi> the Will of the good pleaſure, the ſecret Will of God. Neither were theſe two Wills contrary, but the one of them wrought for the effecting and bringing about of the other. The revealed Will of God, his threatning of the <hi>Ninevites</hi> within <hi>fourty</hi> dayes to overthrow them, this brought them to repentance, that ſo his ſecret Will might be fulfilled in ſparing of them. Though <hi>Nineveh</hi> therefore were not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, yet God might ſafely threaten ſo to ſerve it, <hi>yet fourty dayes and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be overthrown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo I have gone thorow the parts of the Text ſeverally. Let us now put them altogether again, and ſee what general in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction they will afford us. The propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our inſtruction may be this, That God uſually lets off a <hi>Warning-piece,</hi> before a <hi>Murdering-piece,</hi> ſeldome executing any Judgement either perſonal or national, but he ſends ſome kind of <hi>Herald</hi> or other to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170350:92"/>give warning of it. And God hath both an <hi>extraordinary</hi> and <hi>ordinary</hi> way of threatning and giving warning of Judgement either of which is twofold. Firſt his <hi>extraordinary</hi> way is either <hi>immediate</hi> or <hi>mediate, private</hi> or <hi>publick;</hi> Private, by inſpirations; Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, by apparitions. Firſt, God threatneth and giveth warning of Judgement, with an <hi>Adhuc qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ragintadies,</hi> as it were, <hi>Yet fourty days</hi> by private inſpirations. Thus he gave <hi>Noah</hi> warning of the flood. Thus he gave <hi>Abraham</hi> warning of the deſtruction of <hi>Sodome.</hi> Thus he gave <hi>Samuel</hi> warning of the deſtruction of <hi>Elie</hi>'s houſe. And thus he warned all his <hi>Prophets</hi> of his approaching Judgements, according to that of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Amos, Surely the Lord will do nothing, but he revealeth his ſecret to his ſervants the Prophets, Amos</hi> 3.7. Secondly, God threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens and giveth warning of Judgement with an <hi>Adhuc quadragintadies,</hi> as is were, <hi>Yet fourty dayes,</hi> by publick apparitions. Thus he gave the <hi>Jewes</hi> warning of the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Jeruſabem,</hi> and that by two very prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſignes, the one tendered to their eares, the other to their eyes; the former was an hideous voice, heard often in the ſiege of <hi>Jeruſalem, Linquamus has ſedes,</hi> or <hi>Migre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Come, let us be gone, let us leave
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170350:92"/>this curſed place, thought by ſome to have been the voice of the tutelar and protecting <hi>Angels;</hi> thought by others to have been an extraordinary voice of Almighty <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. The other was a prodigious blazing ſtar, which <hi>Joſephus</hi> telleth us, ſtood many moneths together right over <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And thus likewiſe ſhall God give warning of the general and laſt Judgement, <hi>When there ſhall be ſignes in the Sun, and in the moon, and in the stars,</hi> Luke 21.25.</p>
                  <p>And as God hath an <hi>extraordinary,</hi> ſo he hath an <hi>ordinary</hi> way of giving warning of Judgement. And this likewiſe is two-fold, <hi>Domeſtick,</hi> by the preaching and miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Word; <hi>Forreign,</hi> by the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and adminiſtration of his Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, God threatneth and giveth warning of Judgement, with an <hi>Adhuc quadraginta di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, yet fourty dayes,</hi> by the miniſtration of his word. Thus he warned the primitive diſciples by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who <hi>ceaſed not to warn every one night and day with tears,</hi> Acts 20.31. Though we have no <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> as they had under the Law, though <hi>Miniſters</hi> are not acquainted with Gods purpoſes by immediate inſpiration, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we may in ſome ſort, prognoſticate a Judgement, and may ſpeak in a ſtrict ſenſe,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170350:93"/>as the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God. For if every man can diſcern the face of the sky, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpeakes, why may not <hi>Miniſters</hi> the ſignes of the times? yes, without Queſtion we may do it, when the heaven is covered with black clouds, we may conclude there will be a ſtorm; ſo when the earth is clouded with horrid ſins, we may conclude there will be a judgement, by comparing of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things with ſpiritual, by looking into Gods ancient wayes, and conſidering how God hath dealt with ſinners heretofore, though we cannot abſolutely determine; yet we may give a near gueſs, when a ſtorm is impending, when Judgement to the uttermoſt is coming on a Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, God threatneth and giveth warning of Judgement with an <hi>Adhuc qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draginta dies,</hi> as it were <hi>yet fourty dayes,</hi> by the adminiſtration of his Juſtice, by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he executeth upon others. Their harms are our warnings, <hi>Nam tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet:</hi> We have a common ſaying; that the burnt child dreads the fire. In malice we ſhould be children, but in this we ſhould be men, to dread the fire before ever we are burnt; the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others ſhould be inſtruction for us. I conclude this point briefly with that in the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170350:93"/>phecy of <hi>Zephaniah,</hi> c. 3. v. 6, 7. Where God telleth <hi>Jeruſalem, That he had cut off the Nations, ſo that their towers were deſolate, he had made their streets waſte, that none paſſed by; their Cities were deſtroyed, ſo that there was no man, there was no inhabitant.</hi> And wherefore was all this done? why did God ſo miſerably overthrow thoſe other Nations? Why, only to give <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> warning, leſt ſhe were ſerved ſo too, <hi>I ſaid, Surely thou wilt fear me, thou wilt receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> And ſo ye have briefly the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wayes how God giveth warning of, and threatneth Judgement: With like bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ye ſhall have the principal reaſons why he doth it. And theſe are of three ſorts. The firſt concerneth all <hi>men.</hi> The ſecond concerneth the <hi>righteous.</hi> The third concerneth the <hi>wicked.</hi> The firſt reaſon is extended unto all men, which is this, God letteth off a <hi>warning-piece, Adhuc quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gintadies, yet fourty dayes,</hi> that hereby he may bring ſinners to repentance. For <hi>Ad poenas tardus Deus eſt, ad praemia velox,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Poet,</hi> God is flow to anger, and of great goodneſs, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmist,</hi> he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but rather he ſhould turn from his wickedneſe and live, why will ye die, Ohouſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſeeing I have no
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170350:94"/>pleaſure in the death of him, that dieth, ſaith the <hi>Lord.</hi> It was once the policy of the King of <hi>Syria</hi> ſuddenly to ſurprize the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But the <hi>King</hi> of all <hi>Kings</hi> goeth not ſo covertly to work, for being deſirous of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, he uſually acquainteth men with his intention, hereby, if it be poſsible, to bring them to repentance, to ſee if there be any hope of their converſion, that ſo he may never bring them to confuſion. This was his manner of dealing with the people of the old world. He ſent not the flood upon them of a ſudden, but threatned them with it an hundred and twenty years, had they repented all that while, the flood had been prevented, had <hi>they</hi> wept in ſo many years, the <hi>heavens</hi> had not wept fourty dayes, all thoſe ſixſcore years the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God waited for their amendment, he ſpake but in the future ſenſe, I will deſtroy man whom I have created. But when once he perceived that his <hi>warning-peece</hi> was ſlighted, then have at them in good earneſt, a <hi>murdering-peece</hi> goeth off, he proceedeth then to a ſpeedy execution of his Juſtice, and ſpeaketh in the preſent tenſe, I, even I do bring a flood of water upon the earth to deſtroy all fleſh. This was alſo his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dealing with theſe <hi>Ninevites</hi> in our
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170350:94"/>Text, he deſtroyed them not, as in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but warned and threatned them by his Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> here, <hi>Yet fourty dayes, and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be overthrown.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſon hereof concerneth the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> only, which is this, God letteth off a <hi>Warning-peece, Adhuc quadraginta dies, yet fourty dayes,</hi> that his people may make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for their own ſafety and ſecurity: God many times lets alone the <hi>tares</hi> for the <hi>wheat-ſake;</hi> he often ſpareth the wicked for the righteous-ſake, but he ſeldome or never ſlayeth the righteous with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. And therefore when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to bring a Judgement upon any place or nation, he uſeth to threaten and give warning of it before he ſend it, to the intent that ſuch as fear him may provide for their own ſafety. Thus we read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. that God threatneth the plague of hail be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſent it on the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> even in this ſenſe, had been moſt true, there had been but one event to the righteous and to the wicked, they had all been in the field, and they had periſhed altogether. God therefore gave warning of it a day before hand, that ſuch as feared him might, as they did, make proviſion for their own ſafety. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170350:95"/>we read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. that God threatned to ſlay the firſt-born in <hi>Egypt</hi> ere he ſlew them, and therefore commanded the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> to keep cloſe that bloody night; none of them to go out at the door of his houſe untill the morning. <hi>Wicked men</hi> have a care of one anothers ſafety, and therefore warn each other of approaching danger, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by that letter which occaſioned the diſcovery of the <hi>Powder-Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſon.</hi> And ſhall not the righteous God much more tender the ſafety of his ſecret ones? yes, he doth. And therefore when the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angel, when Gods Judgements are abroad, God would have his faithful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as it were, keep at home. We have a pregnant Text to this purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20. <hi>Come my people, enter thou into thy Chambers, and ſhut thy doors about thee, hide thy ſelf, as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be overpaſt.</hi> The third reaſon hereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the wicked only, which is this, God lets off a <hi>warning-peece, Adhuc qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragintadies, yet fourty dayes,</hi> that the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may have no plea againſt the Juſtice of his proceedings. If God ſhould puniſh ſinners before he warneth or threatneth them, his way might ſeem to be unequal, and ſinners might begin to plead for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170350:95"/>after this manner. It is very true, we have done amiſs, for who can ſay my heart is clean? But we, like all other ſinners put far off from us the evil day, not thinking thy judgements had been ſo nigh unto us.</p>
                  <p>We never ſaw it rain, when the sky was all over bright and clear, black clouds are wont to come before a ſtorm, thou threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt the old world before thou ſenteſt the flood, hadſt thou dealt but ſo with us, we would ſoon have been new men, we would have repented of the evil of ſin, and ſo have prevented the evil of puniſhment. Theſe and other ſuch like cavils might ſinners uſe, if God ſhould execute his Judgements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them without threatning. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prevent this, that he may gag, as it were, and muzzle the mouth of iniquity, that the mouth of all wickedneſs may be ſtopped, that ſinners may have no plea, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay for themſelves, but may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained in ſpight of their hearts to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the equity of his proceedings, ſaying, <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord, and true are thy judgements,</hi> to this end he threatneth and giveth warning before he proceedeth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, <hi>Yet fourty dayes and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be overthrown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo ye have briefly the ſeveral ways,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170350:96"/>and the principal reaſons, how, and why God threatneth and giveth warning of his Judgements. Let us now, for the cloſe of all, apply this to our ſelves, examining whether or no, as God here threatned <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh,</hi> ſo he hath not likewiſe threatned and given us warning of his Judgements. And firſt, for Gods extraordinary way of premonition. For the former branch of it, I will not ſay that God hath warned us by immediate inſpirations, No, let <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> ſay what they will, that way of warning is long ceaſed, God revealeth neither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor his intentions to us in theſe dayes any other way than he and they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in his written Word. But though he have not warned us by inſpirations, yet he hath warned us by apparitions, by won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in heaven above, and by ſignes in the earth beneath, as in our Engliſh <hi>Chronicles</hi> we have manifold examples.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, For Gods ordinary way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, For the former branch of it, God hath warned us of judgement by the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> of his Word.</p>
                  <p>We may read, 1 <hi>King</hi> 19.17. <hi>That</hi> Eliſha <hi>had a ſword as well as</hi> Hazael <hi>or</hi> Jehu, <hi>him that eſcapeth the ſword of</hi> Jehu, <hi>ſhall</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha <hi>ſlay.</hi> And when <hi>Eliſha</hi> draweth his
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170350:96"/>ſword, when Gods Miniſters unſheath the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, when they give warning of thoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which they ſee comming on a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it is a manifeſt argument that the devouring ſword, the ſword of <hi>Hazael</hi> and <hi>Jehn,</hi> the ſword of War, and the enemy is at hand. And have not <hi>Eliſha</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> long ſince drawn their ſwords? Have not Gods <hi>Miniſters</hi> for many years given you warning of his Judgements? There is none, I hope, ſuch a ſtranger to the <hi>Temple</hi> as to deny it. And yet here we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth, in another caſe, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.1. <hi>Quis credidit audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui noſtro?</hi> Who hath believed our report? Propheſy of future judgements while we will, we were as good ſay nothing, we ſpeak but into the air, men give us the hearing, but as ſure as the Lord liveth, they believe us not. Moſt truly therefore may that be applyed unto us, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Behold and regard, and wonder marvelouſly, for I will work a work in your dayes, which ye will not believe, though it be told you.</hi> Though we, I ſay, be thus threatned, yet for all this, we regard it not. Well, the men of <hi>Nineveh</hi> therefore ſhall riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the men of this generation,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170350:97"/>and ſhall condemn them, for they, we know, repented at the preaching of <hi>Jonah,</hi> but we are ſo far from repenting, that we will not believe; we ſin by infidelity, we will not believe God, we ſin by incredulity, we will not believe Gods <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out ſelves, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> would once have flattered our <hi>Saviour Christ,</hi> with a <hi>Nequaquamerit,</hi> this ſhall not be unto us. And yet the <hi>Ninevites</hi> could ſee no ſuch probability of danger, as we may ſee, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we wilfully ſhut our eyes; without are fightings, within are fears, hoſtility abroad, no great tranquillity at home, for all this we ſtop our ears, we think the <hi>fourty dayes</hi> will never be out. God hath warned us of judgement likewiſe by the <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of his Juſtice, by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he hath inflicted upon other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We have heard what a grievous famine there was in <hi>Germany</hi> of late years, where men, like ſo many <hi>Nebuchadnezzars,</hi> were fain to eat graſs like oxen, yea, like ſo many <hi>Cannibals,</hi> were ready to cat up one another. We have heard alſo what grievous Wars have been there and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries; and becauſe we were not bettered by their ſufferings; God hath put <hi>England</hi> into the <hi>Swords</hi> commiſſion, ſaying, <hi>Sword, go thorow this land,</hi> we know that it
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170350:97"/>hath ſeized on us, as well as upon our ſiſter. Countries. <hi>But O thou Sword of the Lord, how long will it be ere thou be quiet? Put up thy ſelf into thy ſcabbard, reſt and be still.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that the <hi>ſword</hi> may reſt and be ſtill, while it is called to day, let us deſire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace; and the only condition that I know is contrition, godly ſorrow for our ſins. For how can we hope for peace with men, ſo long as we are at defiance with Almighty God? Can we poſſibly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or can we ſay, we ſhall have peace, ſo long as we follow the vain imaginations of our hearts? No, let us not deceive our ſelves. What peace, ſaid <hi>Jehu</hi> to <hi>Joram,</hi> ſo long as the Whoredomes of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and her Witchcrafts are ſo many? So what peace, may I ſay, can we hope for, ſo long as our abominations and impieties are ſo many? No, there is no peace to the wicked. We may flatter our ſelves, and ſay, we ſhall never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, the Lord of his goodneſs hath made our hill ſo ſtrong. But if we turn not from our ſins, God will turn us up-ſide down, he will drive us out of our land, as he drove out the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and he will give it to ſome Neighbour of ours that is better than we, he will take away the Kingdnme
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170350:98"/>of God, that is, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of the Kingdome from us, and he will give it to a Nation that ſhall bring forth the fruits thereof. For we have heard what he hath done to other Nations by deſtroying them utterly, <hi>Jam ſeges eſt ubi Troja fuit,</hi> and ſhall we be ſo beſotted as ſtill to think we ſhall eſcape? No, If we husband not well this <hi>Adhue,</hi> we muſt expect a <hi>Subvertetur,</hi> if we deſpiſe or abuſe Gods goodneſs and mercy, there is nothing to be looked for but judgement &amp; ſeverity, that which is threatned againſt the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> ſhall certainly be executed upon us, though not within fourty dayes, yet within a ſhort time <hi>we ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</hi> For what if the voice of joy and health be within many of our dwellings, yet if we repent not with theſe <hi>Ninevites,</hi> God will ſend his <hi>pale horſe</hi> among us, pining ſickneſs, peſtilence and death. What if our Garners be full and plenteous with all manner of ſtore, what if our ſheep bring forth thouſands, and ten thouſands in our ſtreets, yet if we repent not with theſe <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevites,</hi> God will ſend his <hi>black horſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, famine and cleanneſs of teeth in all our coaſts, our fruitful land God will make barren, for the wickedneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs of us that dwell therein. What
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170350:98"/>if our eyes ſwell with fatneſs, yet if we do but what we liſt, we ſhall find that God hath but fatted us up againſt the day of ſlaughter. As for Gods <hi>red war-horſe,</hi> we more than hear him daſh, I am ſure, we find by ſad experience, that of <hi>Solomon</hi> moſt true, that there is a time of War, as well as a time of peace. Again, what if the <hi>Sun-ſhine</hi> of the Goſpel light our feet now into the way of peace? What if the Lord give us the word, and great be the company of the orthodox Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? yet if we repent not with theſe <hi>Ninevites,</hi> our <hi>Candleſtick</hi> ſhall be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, there ſhall be a <hi>Famine not of bread on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo of hearing the word of God, the time will come when we ſhall deſire to ſee one of the dayes of the Son of man, and ſhall not ſee it, we ſhall wander from ſea to ſea, and from the North even unto the Eaſt, we ſhall run to and fro to ſeek the word of the Lord, and ſhall not find it,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are threatned, <hi>Amos.</hi> 8.11, 12. In a word, what if our land for the preſent, were as the garden of <hi>Eden?</hi> yet if we repent not with theſe <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevites,</hi> it ſhall be turned into a wilderneſs; it ſhall be an habitation for <hi>Ziim</hi> and for <hi>Jim,</hi> the <hi>Cormorant</hi> and the <hi>Bittern</hi> ſhall poſſeſs it, <hi>Owls</hi> ſhall dwell in it, <hi>Satyres</hi>
                     <pb n="186" facs="tcp:170350:99"/>ſhall daunce in it, God ſhall ſtretch out upon it the line of confuſion, and the ſtones of emptineſs, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaketh; he that hath exalted the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> up to heaven, as he threatned <hi>Capernaum,</hi> will bring her down to hell, ſhe that ſitteth as <hi>Queen</hi> of the Nations, and <hi>Princeſs</hi> among the <hi>Provinces,</hi> that liveth in pleaſure, and ſaith, ſhe ſhall ſee no mourning, if ſhe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not her ſelf in the aſhes of humiliation, ſhe ſhall be humbled by ſome other into the aſhes of deſtruction, ſhe ſhall ſadly ſit down in the duſt, and ſhall no more be called tender and delicate. She that hath the noiſe of harpers heard in her, and that in ſome places yet rejoyceth at the ſound of the <hi>Organ,</hi> ſhe that hath in her the voice of the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> and of the <hi>Bride,</hi> ſhe that is ſo thronged, and crowded with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of people, that they go in and out at her gates by hundreds and by thouſands, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaketh; yet if ſhe repent not, like theſe <hi>Ninevites,</hi> ſhe ſhall utterly be overthrown, the dayes ſhall come upon her when no more pleaſant voice ſhall be for ever heard in her, but <hi>Lacrymae</hi> ſhall be all her leſſon; <hi>Wo</hi> and <hi>Alas</hi> ſhall be her note, and every head in her, inſtead of perfume; ſhall be covered with aſhes, every limb, inſtead of ſilk, ſhall be girded
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170350:99"/>with ſackcloth; every hand inſtead of clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſhall be wrung; every cheek, inſtead of painting, ſhall be furrowed with tears; nay her very gates ſhall mourn for want of paſſengers, her houſes ſhall drop down for want of Inhabitants, and her <hi>Temples</hi> ſhall be ruinated for want of Worſhippers. But why ſpeak I all this while in the future tenſe? for hath not Almighty God begun with us already? Yes, he hath, I am ſure, the wrath of God hath been long revealed from heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of men, for he hath moved the land and divided it, ſo that out enemies are thoſe of our own houſe; and for theſe diviſions that are among us, there are great thoughts of heart, many mens hearts fail for fear, and for looking after thoſe things that are coming on us. Yet as dangerous as our condition is, let us not deſpair of Gods goodneſs toward us; As I would not ſeem to bring you in fear where no fear is, ſo neither would I have your fear ſwallow up your hope, for if we do but repent of the evil of our ſins, God will likwiſe repent of the evil of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. We have a moſt pregnant Text for this, with which I conclude, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170350:100"/>Nation, and concerning a Kingdom to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it, if that Nation, againſt whom I have pronounced, turn from their evil, I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them.</hi> To wind up all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in one word of exhortation, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and be converted, that our ſins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord. Let Gods <hi>warning-peece</hi> reclaim us, and then his <hi>murdering-peece</hi> ſhall never go off; let us repent while there are <hi>Adhuc quadraginta dies, yet fourty dayes,</hi> ſo ſhall we eſcape the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Subvertetur,</hi> the <hi>overthrow</hi> here threatned. And let us make no long tarrying to turn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, let us not put off our repentance from day to day, but let this very day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be the birth-day of our new birth, I and ye, and all that hear me this day, let us now turn every one of us from our evil wayes, and from the wickedneſs that is in our hands. Which if we do, God himſelf will likewiſe turn and repent, he will turn our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity and our captivity as the rivers in the south, he will turn from his fierce anger, that yet we periſh not. Which we humbly beg of him, not for any of our own merits, we utterly renounce them all, but for the merits of his eternal <hi>Son our bleſſed Saviour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170350:100"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
